Chapter XVII Roasts and Salads

In the first part of this work I explained the fundamental principles governing the treatment of Roasts, and I now have to add only a few words to what has already been said. Recipes may be consummate in detail and in accuracy, and still they will be found wanting in the matter of Roasts; for experience alone can tell the operator whether the joint he is treating be old or young, fresh or stale; whether it must be cooked quickly or slowly, and all the theories that I might advance on this subject, though perhaps they might not be useless, would at least prove impracticable nine times out of ten.

I shall not prescribe any limit of time for Roasts, except in very special cases, and even so that limit will only be approximate.

Nothing can be made precise in the matter; long practice alone, away from books, will teach it; for book-rules can only be understood when the light of practical knowledge is focussed upon them.

Accompaniment of Roasts

It struck me as desirable that I should give in this chapter the recipes of the various preparations which, in England, are served with Roasts:—Yorkshire Pudding, Veal Stuffing, &c. Having treated of the accompanying sauces to Roasts in Part I, I need only recall them here.

Yorkshire Pudding (For Beef Roasts)

Mix one-half lb. of sifted flour with six eggs and one quart of boiled milk, adding the eggs one by one and the milk little by little. Season with salt, pepper and nutmeg.

Pour this preparation into a deep baking-pan, containing some very hot dripping, and bake in the oven. If the joint be roasted on the spit, put the Yorkshire pudding under it, on taking the former out of the oven, and let it thus become saturated with the gravy and fat that fall from the roast.

Cut into squares or lozenges, and set these round the Roast or serve them separately.

Sage and Onions Stuffing
(For Turkeys, Ducks and Geese)

Bake four large onions in the oven with their skins on. This done, peel them and finely chop them; fry them in butter with a pinch of dry green chopped sage. Add bread-crumbs, soaked in milk and pressed, equal in weight to the onions, and half the weight of chopped veal fat.

Veal Stuffing (For Veal and Pork)

This stuffing is made from equal quantities of chopped suet, sifted bread-crumbs, and chopped parsley. Season with salt and pepper as for an ordinary forcemeat, and be liberal with the nutmeg.

Cohere this forcemeat with three small eggs per two lbs. of the above preparation.

Roasts of Butcher’s Meat

I must remind the reader of this principle, viz.: that however natural it may seem in a dinner to serve a roasted joint as a Remove, a piece of butcher’s meat must never stand as a Roast.

Roasts really only comprise Fowl and Feathered Game, provided the menu only announces one roast. If two are announced, the second generally consists of some kind of crustacean, such as a Lobster, a Spiny Lobster or Crayfish, generally served in the form of a Mousse; or of a preparation of foie gras, i.e.: either a Pâté, a Terrine, a Mousse or a Parfait sometimes, too, by a very good ham or a derivative preparation thereof.

Beef Roasts

Roast Ribs of Beef

Clear the joint of the vertebræ and the yellow ligaments. Roast before a moderately fierce fire, and place the joint if possible in an uncovered braising-pan, the sides of which may protect the meat during the cooking process.

Roast Upper-fillet

Break the projecting bones of the vertebræ, and sever the yellow ligament at various points. For this joint the heat should be fiercer than in the previous case, the limit of time being less.

Roast Sirloin

These enormous pieces are scarcely trimmed; the excess of flank alone is suppressed; but the fillet must remain covered by a considerable thickness of fat, which protects it while roasting.

Without this precautionary measure, the under-cut would be cooked long before the upper-fillet, and would dry up.

The fire should be concentrated, regular and not too fierce for this joint. The flat bones of the vertebrae must be broken at their base, but not detached.

Fillet of Beef

Fillet of beef intended for roasting should be carefully cleared of its two sinewy envelopes. But, since this trimming tends to let it dry while cooking, were the meat left as it stands, it is customary to lard it with strips of fresh fat bacon, which protect it; or it may be wrapped in slices of bacon. In certain circumstances, it is covered on top and beneath with slices of beef fat, flattened to the thickness of a rasher of bacon by means of a beater, and tied on with string.

Fillet of beef should be cooked with a somewhat fierce fire, and, in England, it is usually kept underdone towards the centre.

N.B.—Large roast joints of beef are always accompanied by Yorkshire pudding, grated Horse-radish or Horse-radish sauce (№119 or 138).

Rotis De Veau (Veal Roasts)

In my opinion, the spit does not suit veal, whatever be the quality of the latter. Poëling (№250) is preferable and suits it better.

The quality of meat can but be enhanced under the treatment I suggest, more particularly as the poëling-liquor constitutes a much richer gravy than that which generally accompanies veal roasted on the spit. In English cookery roast veal is always accompanied by boiled ham or breast of bacon. Veal Stuffing poached in steam in a special mould, and cut into slices, is sent at the same time.

Roast joints of veal are generally the Loin, the best end, the Neck or the Fillet.

Sometimes, too, but more rarely, the Cushion is roasted.

Rotis De Veau (Veal Roasts)

Mutton and Lamb are the best possible meats to roast, and, as far as they are concerned, the culinary treatment might be limited to roasting.

True, good results are obtained from poaching mutton and poëling home-lamb; but it is advisable only to have recourse to these methods when a menu requires varying.

The Mutton joints roasted are the Leg, the Double or Pair of Hind-legs, the Baron or (Hindquarters), the Saddle and the Neck.

The Shoulder also makes an excellent roast, but it may only appear on more or less unimportant menus.

Roast joints of mutton and lamb are always accompanied by Mint Sauce (№136).

Pork Roasts

Pork roasts may only appear on very ordinary menus, and really belong to domestic cookery. The pork joints for roasting are the Legs, the Fillets, and the Neck.

The joints selected should be those derived from very young animals, and the rind should be left upon them, and cut deeply in criss-cross lines, so as to form a lozenge pattern.

Pork should always be roasted before a fierce fire, and it is accompanied by its gravy and Sage and Onions or Apple sauce (№112). Sometimes Apple sauce is replaced by Cranberry sauce (№115); while Roberts sauce Escoffier is also admirably suited to these roasts.

Venison Roasts

I have already pointed out that Roebuck is not very much eaten in England, and that this excellent ground game must be used without having been marinaded. Every piece of roebuck must be trimmed and cleared of tendons, larded with larding bacon, or, at least, carefully wrapped in the latter; and roasted before a fierce fire and kept underdone towards the centre.

The joints of roebuck most commonly roasted are the Legs and the Saddle.

The fallow Deer and the Stag supply the greater part of the Venison consumed in England; and when these animals are of good quality their flesh is covered by a thick coat of white fat, which is very highly esteemed by connoisseurs. Only the neck and the haunch are roasted, and the latter consists of one leg with half of the saddle attached.

This venison is never marinaded, but it should be kept for as long as possible in a dry and well-aired place, that the meat may be gamy.

Before hanging the joint, dredge it well with a mixture of flour and pepper, that it may keep dry and free from the flies.

When about to prepare this Venison, scrape off the coating of flour; wrap it in an envelope of firm suet dough. Cover the whole with oiled paper, tied on with string; and place the joint before a regular, red fire, concentrated and fierce.

When the joint is thought to be cooked, peel off its envelope; season it with salt; sprinkle it with a few pinches of flour, and plenty of melted butter, and brown it as quickly as possible.

Large joints of Venison allow of the following adjuncts: Poivrade sauce and its derivatives, such as Venison Sauce and Grand-Veneur sauce; also the Cumberland and Oxford sauces of English cookery. Generally a sauce boat of red-currant jelly is sent with these joints, unless the accompanying sauce already contains some of it.

Fowl Roasts

Pullets

Large birds, when roasted, should always be salted inside, trussed and covered with slices of bacon. They should be cooked before a concentrated and moderately fierce fire. About ten minutes before unhooking them, remove their covering of bacon, that their breasts may colour.

A bird is known to be cooked when the juice which issues from it, if it be held over a plate, is white. Having ascertained that it is cooked, set it on a very hot dish and serve it instantly.

In England it is customary to surround the fowl with grilled sausages or slices of bacon, and to send a sauceboat of bread sauce (№113) at the same time as the gravy.

Truffled Pullets

Empty the pullet intended for truffling, by means of a little hole on the side of the belly, and remember to keep the skin of the neck whole. This done, remove the collar bone at the summit of the breast, and detach the skin from the whole of the breast.

For a fine pullet, there will be needed one and one-half lbs. of truffles.

After having well brushed and washed the truffles, carefully peel them; select one of the largest; cut it into slices, and put these aside.

Now quarter the other, letting each piece weigh about three oz.

Pound the truffle peel with two lbs. of very fresh pork fat, and rub the whole through a sieve. Take about one-half lb. of this fat: melt it, together with a bay-leaf; and, when it is quite liquid, add the quartered truffles to it (seasoned with salt and pepper), and simmer the whole for about ten minutes.

This done, take it off the fire; leave to cool almost entirely under cover, and mix with what remains of the truffled fat.

Stuff the pullet with this preparation, and slip between the bird’s skin and the flesh of its breast some thin slices of bacon. Upon the slices of bacon place the reserved slice of truffle; carefully sew up all the openings in the pullet with very thin string wrap it in one or two sheets of buttered paper; put it on the spit, and stand it before a concentrated fire which should be kept at an even heat throughout the process of roasting.

About one-quarter of an hour before serving, remove the paper and the slices of bacon, that the breast may colour. Set on a hot dish, and send the gravy, which should be kept rather fat, separately.

The time allowed for roasting a fine fowl is somewhere between one and one-quarter to one and one-half hours.

Chicken à la Reine and Spring Chickens

The directions given for the pullet also apply to other kinds of fowl, provided the difference in size be taken into account.

Spring Chickens à la Russe

Truss the chicken and soak its breast for five minutes in boiling water, that the flesh and the skin may be stiff.

Lard it with thin strips of bacon and anchovy fillets; fill it with smooth, truffled sausage-meat, and roast it on the spit.

At the last moment, when the bird is cooked, baste it by means of a special paper horn, with burning melted bacon fat, which should frizzle the fowl’s skin as it falls upon it.

Serve a Rémoulade sauce separately.

Roast Chicks

These birds should, if possible, be cooked “à la casserole”.

Roast Young Turkeys

Before trussing the young turkey, clear its legs of all tendons; an operation effected by means of two incisions made on the inside of the legs, above and below the last joint. Seize the tendons one by one; fasten them to a braiding needle, and gently turn the latter, thus rolling the tendons round it.

Young turkey is covered with slices of bacon and roasted like the Pullet.

It may be stuffed with Sage and Onions (№1944), or it may be accompanied by Veal Stuffing (№1945), poached in steam in a special mould, and cut into slices set around the bird.

It is often accompanied, also, by boiled or grilled bacon, or grilled sausages. A Bread sauce or a Cranberry sauce maybe served in addition to the gravy.

Truffled Young Turkeys

Proceed as for truffled pullet, after taking the difference of size into account in order to increase the quantity of truffles and fat, sis also the time limit.

Roast Gosling

The Gosling, in order to be roasted, should just have reached its full growth. In England the bird is stuffed with Sage and Onions (№1944), and it is always accompanied by Apple Sauce (№112).

This roast must not stand waiting, and ought to be served very hot.

Caneton Rôti (Roast Duckling)

Aylesbury duckling, which is equal to the Nantes variety, is generally stuffed with Sage and Onions before being roasted.

Its most usual adjunct is Apple Sauce, which is sometimes replaced by melted, red-currant jelly or a Cranberry Sauce.

Caneton Rouennais

See the various recipes dealing with this bird (№1754 to №1764).

Pintade (Guinea Fowl)

This bird is only roasted when quite young, and it is treated like the pheasant, with which it has some points in common.

Young Pigeons (Squabs)

Select them fresh from the nest and very plump. They must be roasted before a very fierce fire and only just done. Their skin must be kept crisp.

Ground-game Roasts

Hare

The piece supplied by the hare for roasting is the “Râble” (the back), which constitutes that part of the animal reaching from the root of the neck to the tail, the latter being included.

The “Râble” should be cleared of all tendons, and delicately larded with bacon.

Roast before a fierce fire for twenty minutes, and have it only just done. The usual adjunct to this piece is Poivrade Sauce. In Northern countries, the adjunct is most commonly some slightly-sugared, stewed apples, or red currant jelly.

In Germany, the pan in which the Râble is roasted is swilled with sour cream, and this cream constitutes the accompaniment. Sometimes a few drops of lemon juice or a tablespoon of melted meat glaze is added.

Young Rabbit

The various recipes for Hare also apply to the young wild rabbit.

Feathered-game Roasts

Faisan Rôti

Everything I said in the preceding chapter concerning the classification of feathered game applies in this instance.

All birds intended for roasting should be young, plump, and fat. They should also be high in the case of pheasants, partridges, and the various kinds of woodcock and snipe.

A pheasant for roasting should always be covered with slices of bacon.

An excellent practice which greatly improves the bird is that of stuffing it with a piece of fresh pork fat, pounded with peelings of fresh truffles, if possible.

Instead of well-pounded fresh pork fat, an equal weight of fresh butter may be used.

This fatty substance impregnates the meat when it melts, and keeps the bird from becoming dry while cooking. The method also applies to partridge. Roast pheasant is generally accompanied by two trimmed half-lemons and a dish of potato chips. The gravy, which should be fat, is served in a sauceboat, and bread sauce or some bread-crumbs fried in butter are sent at the same time.

Faisan Rôti à la Périgourdine

Stuff the pheasant with two oz. of pounded fresh pork fat, two oz. of foie-gras trimmings, and a similar quantity of raw-truffle parings, the whole pounded together and combined with one-half lb. of raw truffles, cut into large dice.

After having covered the pheasant with slices of bacon, roast it in accordance with the directions given under Truffled Pullet. It is better, however, to cook and serve it in a cocotte.

Faisan Rôti à la Gunzbourg

Bone two fine snipes; empty them of their intestines; fry these in butter, and crush them on a plate. Chop up the meat of the snipes, combining half its weight of cream with it, and as much butter; season with salt and pepper, and add the crushed intestines and four oz. of truffles cut into large dice.

Stuff a fine pheasant with this preparation; roast it “en casserole”, or rather in a cocotte.

At the last moment sprinkle with a little fumet, prepared from the snipes’ carcasses.

Partridges

The above recipes, dealing with pheasants, may be applied to partridges.

Quails

Select them white, very fat, and with the fat firm.

Wrap them in a buttered vine-leaf and a thin slice of bacon, and roast them before a fierce fire for ten or twelve minutes.

Dish on small bread-crumb croûtons, fried in butter with half-lemons.

Serve their gravy, which, of course, should be very short, separately.

Roast Ortolans

Wrap each in a vine-leaf; set them on a tray, moistened with salted water, and cause them to set in a fierce oven for four or five minutes.

The small amount of water lying on the bottom of the utensil produces an evaporation which prevents the ortolans’ fat from melting; consequently there is no need of slices of bacon, butter, or gravy.

Each ortolan may be served in a half-lemon, shaped like a basket.

N.B.—The ortolan is sufficient in itself, and it ought only to be eaten roasted. The products sometimes served as adjuncts to it, such as truffles and foie gras, are deleterious, if anything, to its quality, for they modify the delicacy of its flavour, and this modification is more particularly noticeable the more highly flavoured the adjunctive products may be.

With its accompaniments it becomes a sumptuous dish, for the simple reason that it is expensive; but it does not follow that the true connoisseur will like it; it must be plainly roasted to suit him.

Ortolans aux Questches

Cut two large questches into halves, and allow one half for each ortolan. Garnish the inside of each with a piece of butter the size of a hazel-nut; set them on a tray, and put them in the oven. When they are almost cooked, on each half of the questches place a moistened ortolan, wrapped in a vine-leaf, and bake them in a very hot oven for four minutes.

Salt them when taking them out of the oven, and sprinkle them, by means of a brush, with verjuice.

Serve them as they stand, but the questches are not eaten they only serve as a support for the ortolan.

Ortolans au Suc d’Ananas

Heat some fresh butter in a flat, earthenware cocotte, and allow one-quarter oz. of it to each ortolan. Roll the previously salted ortolans in this butter, and put them in a very hot oven for three minutes.

When taking them out of the oven, sprinkle them with a few tablespoonfuls of very cold pineapple juice. Cover the cocotte, and serve immediately.

The cocotte should be just large enough to hold the ortolans.

Roast Woodcock

It should be just sufficiently high. Remove its gizzard; truss it, piercing the legs with the beak, after having drawn the eyes; cover it with slices of bacon, and cook it before a good fire for from fifteen to eighteen minutes. Dish on a cushion of fried bread, and serve the swilling-liquor separately, which in this case should be brandy and a few drops of good game gravy.

Snipes and Becots

For the preparation, proceed as for the woodcock.

Cause to set before a fierce fire, and cook for nine minutes.

Grives et Merles de Corse
(Thrushes and Corsican Blackbirds)

Truss them, and wrap them in slices of bacon. Insert a juniper berry into the thrushes. Roast before a moderately fierce fire for ten or twelve minutes, and dish on small cushions of fried bread.

Serve a very short gravy separately.

Mauviettes
(Larks)

Wrap them in very thin slices of bacon, and impale them on a skewer, or discard the slices of bacon, and merely impale then on a skewer, separating them by blanched squares of breast of bacon.

Roast for ten minutes before a fierce fire.

Dish on small fried croûtons, with quarters of lemon and bunches of watercress all round.

Canards Sauvages (Wild Duck)
Sarcelles (Teal)
Pilets (Widgeons and Pintails)

These birds are not covered with slices of bacon, and are roasted before a fierce fire.

Wild duck must be kept underdone, and, in view of this, twenty minutes suffice for the roasting. Dish with lemons and bunches of watercress all round.

Wild duck, roasted English-fashion.—Treat it as above; send an apple sauce to the table with it.

Wild duck à la Bigarrade.—This is roasted in a similar manner.

Surround it with sections of orange, skinned raw, and serve a clear Bigarrade sauce separately.

The teal, which is a small, wild duck, is roasted before a fierce fire for from ten to twelve minutes, and is surrounded with lemons and watercress.

Widgeons and pintails are treated like the teal, but they are allowed three or four minutes more in the roasting.

Pluviers Dorés (Golden Plover)
Vanneaux (Lapwing)
Chevaliers Divers (Various Sandpipers)

These birds are not covered with slices of bacon; they must be roasted before a very fierce fire, and kept somewhat underdone. They must be served as soon as ready, as waiting is prejudicial to them.

They admit of no accompaniment or garnish, except a very short gravy.

Grouses, Coqs de Bruyère (Black Game)
Gelinottes (Hazel-hens)

These birds must be very fresh when roasted, and should be kept moderately underdone.

They allow of the same adjuncts as pheasant, i.e., bread sauce, bread-crumbs, potato chips, and gravy; and their breasts alone are served as a rule. Grouse and hazel-hens, when they are young, make incomparably fine roasts.

Salads

Salads are of two kinds: simple, or compound. Simple, or raw salads always accompany hot roasts; compound salads, which generally consist of cooked vegetables, accompany cold roasts.

The Seasoning of Salads

Oil seasoning may be applied to all salads, and is made up of three parts of oil to one part of vinegar, with salt and pepper.
Cream seasoning is particularly well suited to salads of early-season lettuce and cos lettuce, and is made up of three parts of very fresh and not very thick cream to one part of vinegar.
Egg seasoning is prepared from crushed hard-boiled yolks of egg, mixed in the salad-bowl with oil, vinegar, salt, and pepper. The whites of egg, cut into thin strips, are added to the salad. This seasoning may also be a light mayonnaise sauce.
Bacon seasoning is used especially for dandelion, red-cabbage, and corn salads. In this case the oil is replaced by the grease of the bacon dice, which are melted and frizzled in the omelet-pan. This grease is poured, while hot, with the bacon dice, over the salad, which should be in a hot salad-bowl and already seasoned with salt, pepper, and the vinegar which has served in swilling the omelet-pan.
Mustard with cream seasoning is used particularly with beetroot salads, with salads of celeriac, and with green salads wherein beetroot plays a major part. It is made up of a small tablespoonful of mustard, mixed with one-third pint of fresh and somewhat thin cream, the juice of a fair-sized lemon, salt, and pepper.

N.B.—I should like to point out that mayonnaise sauce must only be used in very small quantities in the seasoning of salads. It is indigestible, and many constitutions cannot suffer it, especially at night at the end of a dinner.

Raw onion should likewise only be used in salads with great moderation, in view of the fact that so many do not like it. In any case, it should be finely ciseled, washed in fresh water, and pressed in the corner of a towel.

Simple Salads

They comprise, in the first place, those salads known under the name of green salads. Such are lettuce, cos lettuce, chicory, endive, batavia, celery, corn-salad, dandelion, purslain, dittander, rampion, salsify leaves, white dandelion, &c.

Salads de Betterave (Beetroot Salad)

Beetroot is really the accompaniment of compound and simple salads, and it is always best to cook it in the oven. If it be prepared specially as a salad, cut it into a julienne or into thin roundels; flavour it with onions, first baked in cinders and then finely chopped, and season it with mustard sauce or with oil, according to fancy. Always add some chopped herbs.

Celery Salad

For salads, only the fibreless, white celery is used—commonly known as English celery. Cut it into pieces, and cisel these into very thin strips without altogether separating the latterattheirbase. Placeincoldwaterforafewhours, that the strips may curl; drain and season with a mustard sauce with cream.

Celeriac Salad

Cut the celeriac into a fine julienne or paysanne.

Season, according to fancy, with a mustard sauce with cream, or a clear mayonnaise sauce containing plenty of mustard.

Cauliflower Salad

Divide the cooked and somewhat firm cauliflowers into small bunches, cleared of all stalk. Season with oil and vinegar, and flavour with chopped chervil.

Red-cabbage Salad

Suppress the midribs of the leaves; cut the leaves into a julienne, and season them with oil and vinegar six hours in advance. The julienne of cabbages may be parboiled for a few minutes to modify the rawness of the vegetable; it should then be cooled and seasoned as above.

Cucumber Salad

Peel and thinly slice them; sprinkle the slices with table-salt, and let them stand for two hours. Dry, and season them with oil, vinegar, and chopped chervil.

Haricot Beans and Lentil Salads, &c.

Thoroughly drain the vegetable, whatever be its kind; season with oil and vinegar, and add some chopped parsley. Serve separately some thinly-ciscled, washed, and pressed onion.

Potato Salad

Cut some long, fair-sized potatoes, cooked in salted water and lukewarm, to the shape of corks, and divide up the latter into thin roundels.

Season with oil and vinegar, and add some chopped herbs.

Potato Salad à la Parisienne

Select potatoes which do not crumble, such as the vitelottes or new kidney potatoes. Cook them in salted water; cut them to the shape of corks, and slice them (while still lukewarm) into thin roundels. Put them into a salad-bowl, and sprinkle them with two-thirds pint of white wine per two lbs. of potatoes. Then season with oil and vinegar, add some chopped chervil and parsley, and stir with care lest the roundels break.

Tomato Salad

Select some medium-sized and rather firm tomatoes, and scald them. Then skin them; cut them in two crosswise; press them to clear them of juice and seeds; cut them into thin strips; season them with oil and vinegar, and add some chopped tarragon.

Compound Salads

Unless they leave the kitchen to be served immediately, compound salads are dished without their constituents being mixed. As the latter are generally of various colours, they are seasoned and dished in distinct heaps of contrasted shades.

The dishing of compound salads is finished by means of borders consisting of pieces of very red beetroot, gherkins, truffles, roundels of potatoes, and radishes. The method of arranging these vegetables constitutes the decoration, and the latter, being subject to no rules, is merely a matter of taste.

I do not advise the moulding of compound salads, for the increased sightliness resulting therefrom is small compared with the loss in the taste of the preparation. The simplest form of dishing is the best, and fancifulness should not be indulged in, beyond the arrangement of the vegetables in a pyramid, surrounded by a decorated border of jelly.

Salade Allemande

Take equal quantities of potatoes and apples, gherkins, and herring-fillets, all cut into dice and arranged in heaps. Season with hard-boiled egg sauce, and decorate with very red beetroot.

Salade Américaine

Peel and press some tomatoes, and cut them into thin slices; cut some potatoes into thin roundels, and prepare a short julienne of celery.

Decorate with roundels of hard-boiled eggs and thin onion rings.

Season with oil and vinegar

Salade Andalouse

Peel and quarter some small tomatoes; cut some mild capsicums jiilienne-iashion; cook some rice plainly in salted water, keeping each grain separate; add a little crushed garlic and chopped onion and parsley.

Season with oil and vinegar.

Salade Belle-Fermière

This salad consists of curled celery and equal quantities of plain-boiled potatoes, beetroot, and capsicum—all these vegetables cut julienne-isLshion, the celery measuring one-third, and the other ingredients two-thirds of the whole.

Season with mustard sauce with cream.

Salade Cressonniére

This salad consists of curled celery and equal quantities of plain-boiled potatoes, beetroot, and capsicum—all these vegetables cut julienne-fashion, the celery measuring one-third, and the other ingredients two-thirds of the whole.

Salade Isabelle

Thinly slice equal quantities of raw mushrooms, celery, cooked potatoes, and artichoke-bottoms. Dish in distinct heaps.

Season with oil and vinegar, and add some chopped chervil.

Salade Danicheff

Take equal quantities of sliced and blanched celeriac, thin roundels of potatoes, slices of artichoke-bottoms, strips of raw mushrooms, and green asparagus-heads, and arrange them in heaps.

Deck with crayfishes’ tails, hard-boiled eggs, and truffles. Season with mayonnaise sauce.

Salade Demi-Deuil

Take equal quantities of a julienne of potatoes and a julienne of very black truffles. Decorate with rings of truffle girding small roundels of potato, and rings of potato girding small roundels of truffle. Alternate the two forms of rings.

Season with a mustard sauce with cream.

Salade d’Estrées

Take equal quantities of curled celery and a moderately small julienne of raw truffles. Season, when about to dishup, with a mayonnaise sauce with mustard, slightly flavoured with cayenne.

Salade à la Flamande

This consists of a coarse julienne of endives, a similar julienne of potatoes, an onion baked in its skin, cooled, peeled, and chopped, and some fillets of herring cut into dice, the quantities being in the proportion of one-half of the whole for the endives, one-quarter of the whole for the potatoes, and the remaining quarter for the onion and fillets of herring.

Season with oil and vinegar, and add some chopped parsley and chervil.

Salade Francillon

Take some potato salad “à la Parisienne”, previously marinaded in Chablis wine, some mussels (cleared of their beards, and poached with celery), and slices of very black truffle, the three constituents being in the proportion of one-half, one-quarter, and one-quarter respectively.

Set the potato salad on the bottom of the salad bowl, and lay thereon, by way of decoration, the mussels and the truffles in alternate layers.

Salade Italienne

Take equal quantities of carrots, turnips, potatoes, tomatoes, and French beans—all cut into regular dice; also peas, small stoned olives, capers, anchovy fillets in small dice, and herbs for the seasoning.

Use hard-boiled eggs for the decoration.

Season with mayonnaise sauce.

Jokey-club Salad

Take equal quantities of asparagus-heads and a julienne of raw truffles; the two should be seasoned separately some time in advance.

Cohere, when about to dish, with a very little highly-seasoned mayonnaise sauce.

Salade Lacmé

Take equal quantities of red capsicums and tomato sauce; plain-boiled rice, kept very white, and with each grain distinct and ciseled, washed, and pressed onion.

Season with oil and vinegar, and flavour with curry.

Salade de Legumes

Take equal quantities of carrots and turnips, raised by means of a grooved spoon-cutter potato dice; French beans; cut lozenge-form peas; small flageolets, and asparagus-heads; arrange them in distinct heaps, and set a fine bunch of cauliflower in the middle.

Season with oil and vinegar, and add some chopped parsley and chervil.

N.B.—For vegetable salad, use freshly-cooked and uncooled vegetables as much as possible.

Salade Lorette

Take equal quantities of corn salad, and a julienne of beetroot and celery. Season with oil and vinegar.

Salade Mignon

Take equal quantities of shelled shrimps’ tails, artichoke-bottoms, cut into dice, and very thin slices of black truffle arranged to form a border. Season with highly-seasoned mayonnaise sauce with cream.

Salade Monte-Cristo

Take equal quantities of lobster-meat, cooked truffles, and potatoes and hard-boiled eggs in dice, and arrange them in distinct heaps.

In their midst place the very white heart of a lettuce. Season with mayonnaise sauce with mustard, and add some chopped tarragon.

Salade Niçoise

Take equal quantities of French beans, potato dice, and quartered tomatoes. Decorate with capers, small, stoned olives, and anchovy fillets.

Season with oil and vinegar.

Salade Niçoise

Take equal quantities of white chicken meat, very red tongue, celery-sticks cut julienne-iashion, and a julienne of truffles. Arrange these constituents in very regular heaps, and in the middle of them set a heap of asparagus-heads. Decorate with a border consisting of roundels of cocks’ kidneys and roundels of gherkins, laid alternately.

Season with very thin mayonnaise sauce.

Salade Parisienne

Clothe a Charlotte-mould with very clear jelly, and garnish its bottom and sides with thin collops of spiny-lobster’s tail decked with truffles. Fill the mould with a vegetable salad (№2011) combined with a quarter of its volume of lobster or spiny-lobster remains, cut into dice, and cohered by means of a cleared mayonnaise.

Leave to set in the cool, and, when about to serve, turn out on a napkin.

Salade Mascotte

Take some green asparagus-heads, some hard-boiled lapwings’ eggs, some sliced cocks’ kidneys, some slices of truffle, and some crayfishes’ tails.

Decorate according to fancy, making use of the ingredients of the salad for the purpose.

Season with mustard sauce with cream.

Salade Rachel

Take equal quantities of sticks of celery, raw artichoke-bottoms, truffles, potatoes, and asparagus-heads, all, except the latter, being cut julienne-fashion.

Slightly cohere the salad with mayonnaise sauce.

Salade Régence

Take equal quantities of sliced cocks’ kidneys, shavings of raw truffles, asparagus-heads, and celery cut lengthwise into extremely thin strips.

Season strongly with oil and lemon juice.

Salade Russe

Take equal quantities of carrots, potatoes, French beans, peas, truffles, capers, gherkins, sliced and cooked mushrooms, lobster meat, and lean ham—all cut julienne-iashion, and add some anchovy fillets.

Cohere the whole with mayonnaise sauce; dish, and decorate with some of the ingredients of the salad, together with beetroot and caviare.

Salade Sicilienne

Take equal quantities of celeriac, russet apples, tomatoes, and artichoke-bottoms—all four cut into dice.

Season with oil and lemon juice.

Salade Trédern

Take twenty-four crayfishes’ tails, cooked as for bisque, and cut lengthwise; twenty-four oysters (cleared of their beards), poached in lemon juice; and three tablespoonfuls of asparagus-heads. The three constituents should have barely cooled. Complete with fine shavings of raw truffles.

Season with condimented mayonnaise sauce, combined with a purée made from the crayfishes’ carcasses, pounded with two tablespoonfuls of fresh cream.

Salade Truffles

Cut some raw, peeled truffles into very thin shavings.

Season with a sauce consisting of hard-boiled egg-yolks, seasoned with salt and freshly-ground pepper, and finished with oil and lemon juice.

Salade de Truffles Blanches

Cut some raw, white, Piedmont truffles into thin shavings.

Season with a sauce consisting of hard-boiled egg-yolks seasoned with salt and pepper, and finished with mustard, oil, and vinegar.

Salade Victoria

Take equal quantities of spiny-lobster trimmings, asparagus-heads, truffles, and cucumbers—all cut into dice.

Season with a mayonnaise sauce, combined with the spiny-lobster’s creamy parts and a purée of coral.

Salade Waldorf

Take equal quantities of russet apples and celeriac, both cut into dice, and halved and peeled walnuts, soaked in fresh water for one-quarter hour, and well drained.

Season with clear mayonnaise sauce.

Chapter XVIII Vegetables and Farinaceous Products

The preparatory treatment of vegetables—parboiling and braising, &c.—having been explained in Chapter X, as also the preparation of purées, creams, and vegetable garnishes, it is now only necessary to deal with each vegetable separately.

Artichokes

Artichauts à la Barigoule

Take some very fresh and tender artichokes. After having trimmed their tops, take off the outermost leaves; parboil the artichokes; remove their hearts, and completely clear them of their chokes. Season them inside, and fill them with a preparation of Duxelles (№224), combined with a quarter of its weight of fresh, grated, fat bacon, and as much butter.

Wrap the stuffed artichokes in thin slices of bacon; string them,andsettheminasaucepanpreparedforbraising. Braise them gently with white wine, and cook them well.

When about to serve them, remove the string and the bacon, and dish them.

Strain the braising-liquor, and clear it of grease; thicken it with the necessary quantity of good half-glaze sauce; reduce it sufficiently to produce only a very little sauce, and pour the latter over the artichokes.

Cœrs d’Artichauts à la Clamart

Select some very tender small artichokes, and trim them.

Set them in a buttered cocotte, with a small quartered carrot and three tablespoonfuls of freshly-shelled peas to each artichoke, add a large faggot and a little water, and salt moderately. Cover and cook gently in a steamer. Whenabout to serve, withdraw the faggot, and slightly thicken the liquor with a little manied butter.

Serve the preparation in the cocotte.

Artichokes with Divers Sauces

Cut the artichokes evenly to within two-thirds of their height; trim them all round; string them, and plunge them into slightly-salted boiling water. Cook them rather quickly; drain them well, just before serving them, and remove the string.

Dish on a napkin, and send a butter, a Hollandaise, or a mousseline sauce, &c., at the same time.

When artichokes, cooked in this way, have to be served cold, remove their chokes, dish them on a napkin, and send a Vinaigrette sauce separately.

Artichauts à la Provençale

Select some very small Provençal artichokes; trim them,and put them in an earthenware stewpan containing some very hot oil. Season with salt and pepper; cover the stewpan, and leave to cook for about ten minutes.

Then add, for each twelve artichokes, one pint of very tender, freshly-shelled peas, and a coarse julienne of one lettuce.

Cover once more, and cook gently without moistening. The moisture of the peas and the lettuce suffices for the moistening, provided the stewpan be well covered and the fire be not too fierce—both of which conditions are necessary to prevent evaporation on too large a scale.

Quartiers d’artichauts à l’Italienne

Turn, trim, and quarter some fair-sized artichokes. Trim the quarters, removing the chokes therefrom; rub them with a piece of lemon to prevent their blackening plunge them one; by one into fresh water; parboil and drain them. This done, set them in a sautépan on a litter of aromatics, as for braising make them sweat in the oven for seven or eight minutes; moisten with white wine; reduce the latter; and moisten again, to within half their height, with brown stock. Cook gently in the oven until the quarters are very tender.

When about to serve, set them in a vegetable dish; strain the cooking-liquor; clear it of grease, and reduce it; add an Italian sauce to it, and pour this sauce over the quartered artichokes.

Fonds d’artichauts Farcis

Select some medium-sized artichokes; clear them of their leaves and their chokes; trim their bottoms, rub them with lemon to prevent their blackening, and cook them in a Blanc (№167), keeping them somewhat firm.

After having drained them, stuff them with a little Duxelles, prepared according to №224. Arrange them on a buttered dish; sprinkle the Duxelles with fine raspings and a little melted butter, and set in a hot oven for a gratiri to form.

Serve a Madeira sauce at the same time

Fonds d’artichauts à la Florentine

Prepare the artichoke-bottoms as above.

Meanwhile fry a large, chopped onion in butter; add thereto two-thirds lb. of parboiled and chopped spinach per twelve artichokes. Stir over an open fire, that all moisture may evaporate, and add salt and pepper, a piece of crushed garlic the size of a pea, a tablespoonful of anchovy purée, and two tablespoonfuls of Velouté. Cook gently for ten minutes.

Stuff the artichoke-bottoms with this preparation; arrange them on a buttered dish; coat with Mornay sauce; sprinkle with Gruyère, cut brunoise-fashion, and set to glaze in a fierce oven.

Upon withdrawing the dish from the oven, sprinkle the artichoke-bottoms with a few drops of melted anchovy butter.

FONDS d’ARTICHAUTS aux POINTES d’ASPERQESPrepare the artichoke-bottoms as above; stew them in butter,

and garnish them with asparagus-heads, cohered with cream,and heaped in pyramid-form.

Lay them on a buttered dish; coat with Mornay sauce, andset to glaze quickly.

FONDS d’ARTICHAUTS SAUTES

Remove the leaves and the chokes from the artichokes, trimthe bottoms, and slice them up raw. Season them with saltand pepper; toss them in butter; set them in a vegetable-dish,and sprinkle them with herbs.

PUREE OU CRBME d’ARTICHAUTS

Take some very tender artichokes; trim and turn thebottoms, and half-cook them, keeping them very white. Com-plete their cooking in butter, and rub them through a fine sieve,together with the butter used in cooking.

Put the pur^e thus obtained in a saucepan, and add to itthe half of its bulk of mashed, very smooth, and creamy potatoes.

Finish the pur£e with a little fresh and a little hazel-nutbutter, the latter being used to increase the flavour of the arti-chokes.

ASPARAGUS (Asperges)

The best-known varieties of asparagus in England are: —

1. The Lauris asparagus, which is par excellence the early-season kind.

2. The green, Parisian asparagus, which is very small, andof which the most diminutive sticks, also called sprew, servefor garnishes.

3. The Argenteuil asparagus—very much in demand whileit is in season.

4. English asparagus, which is somewhat delicate inquality, but inclined to be small. During the season thereare, besides, several other kinds of asparagus imported fromSpain or France, which, though not equal to the four kindsabove mentioned, may nevertheless be used for soups or gar-nishes instead of asparagus-heads or sprew.

Asparagus should be had as fresh as possible; it shouldbe cleaned with care, quickly washed, tied into faggots, andcooked in plenty of salted water. Certain kinds, the flavour ofwhich is somewhat bitter, should be transferred to other wateras soon as cooked, with the view of reducing their bitterness.

Asparagus is dished on special silver drainers, or onnapkins.

A5PERGE5 à la FLAMANDE

According to Flemish custom, asparagus is served with onehot, hard-boiled half-egg, and one oz. of melted butter perperson. The egg-yolk is crushed, seasoned, and finished withthe butter by the consumers themselves. This accompanimentmay also be prepared beforehand and served in a sauceboat.

ASPERGES AU GRATIN

Dish the asparagus in rows, and coat the heads of eachrow with a little Mornay sauce. When all are dished, two-thirds cover the bunch with a band of buttered paper, andcoat the uncovered portion with Mornay sauce. Sprinkle withgrated Parmesan; glaze quickly at the salamander, remove thepaper, and serve at once.

ASPERGES à la MILANAISE

Having thoroughly drained the asparagus, set it on along, buttered dish sprinkled with grated Parmesan; arrangeit in successive rows, each of which sprinkle in the regionof the heads with grated Parmesan. When about to serve,cover the cheese-powdered parts copiously with nut-brownbutter, and set to glaze slightly at the salamander.

s s 2

ASPERGES à la POLONAISE

Thoroughly drain the asparagus; set it on a long dish,in rows, and besprinkle the heads with hard-boiled egg-yolkand chopped parsley, mixed. When about to serve, cover theheads with nut-brown butter, combined with one oz. of veryfresh and fine bread-crumbs per four oz. of butter.

ASPARAGUS WITH VARIOUS SAUCES

Butter sauce, Hollandaise, Mousseline, and Maltese saucesare the most usual adjuncts to asparagus. B6arnaise saucewithout herbs is also served occasionally, likewise melted butter.

When eaten cold, it may be served with oil and vinegaror a mayonnaise—more particularly a Chantilly mayonnaise,i.e., one to which beaten cream has been added.

SPREW WITH BUTTER (Pointes d’Asperges)

Sprew or green asparagus is chiefly used for garnishing oras a garnishing ingredient, but it may also be served as avegetable with perfect propriety. Cut the heads into two-inchlengths, and put them together in faggots.

Cut what remains of them into bits the size of peas. Afterhaving washed the latter, plunge them into boiling saltedwater, and cook them quickly, that they may keep green.

This done, thoroughly drain them; let their moistureevaporate by tossing them over the fire; cohere them withbutter, away from the fire, and dish them in a timbale with thefaggots on top.

They are usually served in small patty crusts, or in smalltartlet crusts, with a few sprew tops on each small patty ortartlet.

POINTES d’ASPERGES à la CREME

Prepare them, and cook them in salted water as above.

Their cohesion with cream is in pursuance of the procedurecommon to other vegetables similarly prepared, and they areserved like those of No. 2044.

Egg-Plant (Aubergines)

AUBERGINES A d’EGYPTIENNE

Cut them into two lengthwise; trim them round the edges;cisel the middle of each with the view of facilitating the cook-ing process, and cook them.

Drain them; remove the pulp from their insides, and setthe shells on a buttered gratin dish.

This done, chop up the withdrawn pulp; add thereto a little

chopped onion cooked in oil, and the same quantity of verylean, chopped, and cooked mutton as there is egg-plant pulp.

Fill the egg-plant shells with this preparation; sprinklewith a few drops of oil, and set in the oven for fifteen minutes.On withdrawing the dish from the oven, set on each egg-planta few roundels of tomato, tossed in oil; sprinkle with choppedparsley, and serve.

AUBERGINES AU GRATIN

Fry the egg-plants as above; empty them, chop up theirpulps, and add to it an equal weight of dry Duxelles (No.223). Garnish the shells with this preparation, set them on agratin dish, sprinkle them with raspings and a few drops ofoil, and cause the gratin to form.

Surround the egg-plants with a border of light half-glazesauce when serving.

AUBERGINES FRITES

Cut the egg-plants into thin roundels; season and dredgethem, and fry them in smoking oil. Dish them on a napkin,and serve immediately, that they may be eaten crisp. If theywait at all, they soften, and thereby lose quality.

AUBERGINES à la PROVENCALE

Proceed as for No. 2047, but replace the Duxelles bytomatoes tossed in oil and flavoured with a little garlic.

Set the gratin to form in the same way, and surround theegg-plants with a border of tomato sauce when taking them outof the oven.

AUBERGINES SOUFFLEES

Cut some fine egg-plants into two; cisel them, and fry themin the usual way; remove the pulp from their insides, andset the shells on a buttered gratin dish. Finely chop the with-drawn pulp, and mix therewith an equal quantity of reducedBechamel sauce, combined with grated Parmesan.

Add some white of egg beaten to a stiff froth, allowing asmuch of it as for an ordinary souffle.

Garnish the egg-plant shells with this preparation, and cookin a moderate oven, as for ordinary souffle. On withdrawingthe dish from the oven, serve instantly.

AUBERGINES à la TURQUE

Peel the egg-plants and cut them, each lengthwise, intosix slices.

Season, dredge, and fry these slices in oil; pair them off, andjoin them together by means of a very firm preparation of raw

egg-y°ll<s and grated, fresh cheese. When about to serve, dipthem into batter, and fry them in smoking oil.

Dish on a napkin with very green fried parsley.

These stuffed slices of egg-plant may be treated & Vanglaiseinstead of with batter.

CARDOONS (Cardons)

Treatment and Cooking Process.—After having suppressedthe green outside leaf-stalks, detach the white ones all round,and cut these into three-inch lengths. Peel these lengths, rubthem with lemon, that they may not blacken, and throw them,one by one, into fresh acidulated water.

Prepare the heart of the cardoon in the same way, afterhaving withdrawn the fibrous parts, and cook the whole ina Blanc (No. 167), with one lb. of chopped veal fat, sprinkledover its surface, that the cardoon may be kept from blackeningby exposure to the air.

Cook gently for about one and one-half hours.

CARD0N5 AU PARMESAN

After having well drained the sections, build them into apyramid in successive layers. Sprinkle each row with a fewdrops of good half-glaze sauce, and with grated Parmesan.Cover the whole with the same sauce; sprinkle with gratedParmesan, and set to glaze quickly.

CARDONS à la MORNAY

Proceed exactly as above, but replace half-glaze sauce byMornay sauce. Glaze quickly, and serve immediately.

CARDONS à la MILANAISE

Proceed as for “Asperges k la Milanaise” (No. 2041).

CARDONS WITH VARIOUS SAUCES

They may be served either with gravy, or Half-glaze, Cream,Hollandaise, Mousseline, Italienne, or Bordelaise sauces.

The sauce is either poured over them or served separately.

If the sauce be poured over the cardoons, they are dished ina timbale; if the sauce be sent separately, they may be servedon a silver drainer, like asparagus.

CARDONS à la MOELLE

Dish the cardoons in a pyramid on a round dish; cover themwith a marrow sauce (No. 45), and surround them with verysmall puff-paste patties garnished with poached marrow dice.Or dish the cardoons in a timbale, and set thereon the heart

cut into roundels and arranged in a crown, with a slice ofpoached marrow on each roundel of heart.

Cover the whole with marrow sauce.

C(EUR de CARDON aux FINES HERBES

Having cooked the heart of the cardoon, trim it all roundso as to give it the cylindrical shape, and cut it laterally intoroundels one-third inch thick.

Roll these roundels in some pale, thin, buttered meat glaze,combined with chopped herbs. Prepared in this way, the heartof a cardoon constitutes an excellent garnish for Tournedosand sauted chickens.

Carrots (Carottes)

CAROTTES GLACISES POUR GARNITURES

New carrots are not parboiled; they are turned, whole,halved, or quartered, according to their size, and then trimmed.If old, they should be turned to the shape of elongated olives,and parboiled before being set to cook.

Put the carrots in a saucepan with enQUgh water to coverthem well, one-half oz. of salt, one oz. of sugar, and two oz.of butter per pint of water.

Cook until the water has almost entirely evaporated, so thatthe reduction may have the consistence of a syrup. Saute thecarrots in this reduction, that they may be covered with abrilliant coat.

Whatever be the ultimate purpose for which the carrots areintended, they should be prepared in this way.

CAROTTES à la CRfeME

Prepare the carrots as above, and, when the moistening isreduced to the consistence of a syrup, cover them with boilingcream.

Sufficiently reduce the latter, and dish in a timbale.

CAROTTES à la VICHY

Slice the carrots, and, if they be old, parboil them.

Treat them exactly after the manner of the “GlazedCarrots” of No. 2059; dish them in a timbale, and sprinklethem with chopped parsley.

PUREE de CAROTTES

Slice the carrots, and cook them in slightly-salted water, withsugar and butter, as for “Glazed Carrots,” and a quarter oftheir weight of rice. Drain them as soon as they are cooked;rub them through a fine sieve; transfer the pur£e to a saut£-

pan, and dry it over a fierce fire, together with three oz. of butterper lb. of pur£e.

Now add a sufficient quantity of either milk or consomm6 togive it the consistence of an ordinary pur£e. Dish in a timbalewith triangular croutons of bread-crumbs, fried in butter at thelast moment.

This pur£e is very commonly served as a garnish withbraised pieces of veal.

FLAN aux CAROTTES

This is served either as a vegetable or a sweet.

Line a flawn ring with good, short paste (No. 2358); coatthe inside of the flawn with a round piece of paper, and fill itwith rice or split peas. Bake it without letting it brown; re-move the split peas or the rice, as also the paper, and garnishthe flawn crust with a slightly sugared pur6e of carrots. Coverthis pur^e with half-discs of carrot cooked as for No. 2059, andkept unbroken. Coat with the cooking-liquor of the carrotsreduced to a syrup, and put the flawn in the oven for fiveminutes.

CELERY (Celeri)

Celery for braising should be non-fibrous, white, and verytender. Cut the sticks till they measure only eight inches fromtheir roots; remove the green leaves all round; trim the root;wash with great care, parboil for one-quarter hour, and cool.

This done, braise them after recipe No. 275. When theyare cooked, cut each stick into three pieces, and double up eachsection before dishing and serving.

VARIOUS PREPARATIONS OF CELERY

The recipes given for cardoons may be applied to celery.On referring to the respective recipes, therefore, celery may beprepared: —

Au Parmesan, Sauce Mornay, a la Milanaise, Italienne,Hollandaise, with gravy, &c.

pur£e de celeri

Slice the celery; parboil it, and stew it, until it is quitecooked, in a little very fat consomme.

Drain as soon as cooked; rub through a sieve, adding thewhile the cooking-liquor cleared of all grease; thicken the pur^ewith about one quart of very white and firm potato pur^e;heat; add butter at the last moment, and dish in a timbale.

PUREE de CELERI-RAVE (Celeriac)Peel the celeriac; cut it into sections, and cook it in saltedwater.

Drain and rub it through tammy, adding plain-boiled,quartered potatoes the while in the proportion of one-third ofthe weight of the pur£e of celeriac.

Put the pur^e in a sautdpan; add to it three oz. of butterper lb.; dry it over a fierce fire, and bring it to its normal con-sistence by means of milk. When about to serve, add butter,away from the fire, and dish in a timbale.

CIipes

Those cepes which are barely opened or not opened at allare not parboiled. Contrariwise, those which are open shouldbe washed, parboiled, and stewed in butter, after having beenwell dried.

CEPES à la BORDELA1SECollop the cepes; season them with salt and pepper; putthem into very hot oil, and toss them until they are thoroughlyfrizzled. Almost at the last moment add, per one-half lb. ofcepes, one oz. of cepe stalks, which should have been putaside and chopped up, one teaspoonful of chopped shallots,and a tablespoonful of bread-crumbs—the object of which is toabsorb any excess of oil, once the cepes have been served.

Toss the whole together for a few minutes; dish in a tim-bale, and complete with a few drops of lemon juice and somechopped parsley.

C^PES a la cremeCollop the cepes, and stew them in butter with a dessert-spoonful of chopped onion per one-half lb. of cepes; the onionshould have been cooked in butter, without colouration.

When they are stewed, drain them; cover them with boilingcream, and boil gently until the latter is completely reduced.At the last moment finish with a little thin cream, and dish ina timbale.

CEPES à la PROVEN£ALEProceed as for No. 2068, but substitute for the shallots somechopped onion and a mite of crushed garlic.

Dish in a timbale, and complete with a few drops of lemonjuice and some chopped parsley.

CEPES à la ROSSINIProceed as for No. 2069, and add to the ctpes one-third oftheir weight of thickly-sliced, raw truffles, stewed at the same

time as the former. When about to serve, finish with a littlepale melted meat glaze, and dish in a timbale.

Mushrooms (Champignons)

Cookery includes under this head only the white Parisianmushroom and the meadow mushroom, which is the kind socommonly used in England.

The other kinds are always identified by special and properterms.

CHAMPIGNONS à la CR&MEProceed as described under No. 2069.

CHAMPIGNONS SAUTES

After having washed the mushrooms, dried, and ciseledthem, and seasoned them with salt and pepper, toss them withbutter in a frying-pan over a fierce fire. Sprinkle them withchopped parsley at the last moment, and dish them in a timbale.

CHAMPIGNONS GRILLES

Take some large Parisian or meadow mushrooms. Care-fully peel them; season them; smear them with oil, by meansof a brush, and grill them gently.

Set them on a round dish, and garnish their midst withwell-softened, Maitre-d’Hotel butter.

CHAMPIGNONS FARCIS

Select some fine, medium-sized mushrooms; suppress theirstalks; wash them, and dry them well. Set them on a dish;season them; sprinkle them with a few drops of oil; put themin the oven for five minutes, and garnish their midst withDuxelles (No. 224) shaped like a dome, and thickened or notwith bread-crumbs.

Sprinkle the surface with fine raspings and a few drops ofoil or melted butter, and set the gratin to form in a somewhatfierce oven.

FLAN GRILLE aux CHAMPIGNONS

Line a buttered flawn-mould with good lining paste (No.

).

Garnish it with very fresh and barely opened English mush-rooms, tossed in butter with a little chopped onion, coheredwith cream, and cooled.

Moisten the edges of the flawn-mould, and deck it withcriss-cross strips of short paste, as for a latticed apple-flawn.

Gild the lattice work; bake the flawn in a very hot oven, andserve it the moment it is withdrawn.

TARTELETTES GRILLEES aux CHAMPIGNONSThese tartlets constitute an excellent and beautiful garnish,more particularly for Tournedos and Noisettes. Proceed ex-actly as for No. 2076, but use tartlet moulds the size of whichis determined by the dimensions of the piece or preparationwhich they are to accompany.

TURNED AND GROOVED MUSHROOMS

FOR GARNISHING

Take some very fresh mushrooms; wash and drain themquickly.

Suppress their stalks flush with their heads; turn or groovethe latter with the point of a small knife, and throw them, oneby one, into a boiling liquor prepared as follows: —

For two lbs. of mushrooms, put one-sixth pint of water,one-third oz. of salt, two oz. of butter, and the juice of oneand one-half lemons, in a saucepan. Boil; add the mushrooms,and cook for five minutes. Transfer to a bowl immediately,and cover with a piece of buttered paper.

PUR^E de CHAMPIGNONSClean, wash, and dry two lbs. of mushrooms. Quickly peelthem, and rub them through a sieve. Put this pur^e of rawmushrooms into a saut^pan with two-thirds pint of reducedBechamel sauce, and one-sixth pint of cream. Season with salt,white pepper, and nutmeg; reduce over an open fire for a fewminutes, and finish, away from the fire, with three oz. of bestbutter.

MORELS (Morilles)The Spring mushroom or Morel is the one most preferredby connoisseurs. There are two kinds of morels—the pale andthe brown kind—both excellent, though some prefer the formerto the latter, and vice versS.

In spite of what connoisseurs may say regarding the errorof washing morels, I advocate the operation, and urge thereader to effect it carefully, and without omitting to open outthe alveolate parts, so as to wash away any sand particles thatmay be lodged therein.

The Cooking of Morels.—If they be small, leave themwhole; if large, halve or quarter them. After having properlydrained them, put them in a saucepan with two oz. of butter,the juice of a lemon, and a pinch of salt and another of pepperper lb. of morels. Boil, and then stew for ten or twelve minutes.Never forget that the vegetable juices produced by the morelsshould be reduced and added to their accompanying sauce.

MORILLES à la CREME

Proceed as for Cepes and Mushrooms with Cream.

MORILLES FARCIES

Select some large morels, and wash them well.

Suppress their stems; chop them up, and prepare them likea Duxelles (No. 223).

Add to this Duxelles half of its bulk of very smooth sausage-meat.

Open the morels on one side; fill them with the preparedforcemeat, and set them on a buttered dish, opened side nether-most.

Sprinkle with fine raspings, and use plenty of melted butter;cook for twenty minutes in a moderate oven, and serve thedish as it stands.

MORILLES à la POULETTE

Cook them as described under No. 2080, and add them to aPoulette sauce (No. 101), together with their cooking-liquorreduced.

Dish in a timbale, and sprinkle with a pinch of choppedparsley.

MORILLES SAUTEES

After having thoroughly washed the morels, dry them wellin a towel, and halve or quarter them according to their size.

Season them with salt and pepper, and saute them withbutter in an omelet-pan, over a sufficiently fierce fire, to avoidthe exudation of their vegetable moisture. Dish them in atimbale; squeeze a few drops of lemon juice over them, andsprinkle them with chopped parsley.

TOURTE de MORILLES

Cook the morels as explained under No. 2080, and drainthem well.

Reduce their cooking-liquor by a quarter, and add to ittwo tablespoonfuls of very thick cream and one oz. of butterper lb. of morels.

Heat this sauce without boiling it, toss the morels in it, andset them in a tourte crust, or merely in the centre of a crown ofpuff-paste, lying on a dish.

Morels prepared in this way may also be served in a Vol-au-vent crust (No. 2390).

MOUSSERONS, ORONGES, GIROLES

These varieties of esculent fungi are not much liked inEngland.

The best way to prepare them is to toss them quickly inbutter.

BRIONNE (Chow-chow)

This excellent vegetable, which has only become known quiterecently, is beginning to be appreciated by connoisseurs. It isin season from the end of October to the end of March—thatis to say, at a time when cucumbers and vegetable marrows areover. It greatly resembles these last-named vegetables, andis prepared like them, while the recipes given for cardoons mayalso be applied to it.

CHICORY, ENDIVE AND BELGIAN CHICORY(Chicoree Frisee, Escarole, Endive)

Three kinds of chicory are used for cooking, viz: —

1. Curled chicory, improperly termed “Endive” inEngland.

2. Flemish chicory, which is genuine endive in its primitivestate, i.e., grown in the open air. It greatly resembles Escarole.

3. Brussels chicory, or the Belgian kind; obtained fromcultivating the root of Flemish chicory in the dark.

This last kind is quite different from the first two, both withregard to its quality and its culinary treatment, and it will bedealt with later under the name of “Endive.”

CHICOREE à la CR^ME

Parboil the chicory for ten minutes in plenty of boilingwater. Cool it; press the water out of it, and chop it up.

Cohere it with four and one-half oz. of pale roux per twolbs. of chicory; moisten with one quart of consomm£; seasonwith salt and a pinch of powdered sugar, and braise in theoven, under cover, for one and one-half hours.

Upon withdrawing it from the oven, transfer it to anothersaucepan; add three-fifths pint of cream and two oz. of butter,and dish in a timbale.

PAIN de CHICOREE

Braise the chicory as described above.

Upon withdrawing it from the oven, mix with it (per lb.)five stiffly-beaten eggs; put it into an even, buttered mould,and set to poach in a bain-marie.

Before unmoulding the “loaf,” let it rest awhile, that themiddle may settle. Turn out just before serving, and coverwith a cream sauce.

PUREE de CHICOREE

Braise the chicory, and rub it through a sieve. Mix it withone-third of its bulk of smooth mashed potatoes with cream;heat; add butter away from the fire, and dish in a timbale.

638 GUIDE TO MODERN COOKERY

SOUFFLE de CHICOREE

Braise about one-half lb. of chicory, keeping it somewhatstiff, and rub it through a sieve. Add to it the yolks of threeeggs, also two oz. of grated Parmesan and the whites of threeeggs, beaten to a stiff froth.

Dish in a buttered timbale; sprinkle with grated Parmesan,and cook after the manner of an ordinary souffle.

N.B.—This souffle of chicory may also be cooked in smallcases, and it makes an excellent garnish for large pieces ofveal or ham.

CHICOREE à la FLAMANDE

Cut the chicory into twTo-inch lengths; parboil it; cool it,and then proceed for the rest of the operation as describedunder No. 2089—the only difference being that it is notchopped.

ENDIVES OR BRUSSELS CHICORY

Whatever be the purpose for which they are intended, en-dives should always be cooked preparatively as follows: —

After having washed and cleaned them, put them in a well-tinned saucepan containing (per three lbs. of endives) a liquorprepared from the juice of a lemon, a pinch of salt, one oz.of butter, and one-fifth pint of water. Cover the saucepan;boil quickly, and complete the cooking on the side of ihe firefor from thirty to thirty-five minutes.

Endives may thus be served plain, and constitute a veryfavourite vegetable or garnish. They may accompany allRelev^s of butcher’s meat.

Some cardoon recipes may also be applied to them, moreparticularly a la Mornay, a la Crbme, and a la Milanaise—allof which suit them admirably.

CABBAGES (Choux)

From the culinary standpoint, cabbages may be divided intoseven classes, as follow's: —

1. White cabbages: used almost solely in the preparationof sauerkraut.

2. Red cabbages: used as a vegetable, as a hors-d’oeuvre,or as a condiment.

3. Round-headed or Savoy cabbages: specially suited tobraising and the English method of cooking.

4. Scotch kale and spring cabbages: always prepared inthe English fashion.

5. Cauliflowers and broccoli: the flower of these is most

commonly used, but the leaves are cooked in the English waywhen they are tender.

6. Brussels sprouts.

7. Kohlrabi: the roots of these may be dished as turnips,and the leaves cooked in the English way, provided they beyoung and tender.

WHITE CABBAGE5 (Choux Blancs)

In an extreme case, these cabbages may be braised like thegreen Savoys, but they are usually too firm, and they are there-fore only used in the preparation of sauerkraut.

SAUERKRAUT (Choucroute)

If the sauerkraut be somewhat old, set it to soak in coldwater for a few hours. It is best, however, to avoid thismeasure, if possible, and to use only fresh sauerkraut.

When about to cook it, drain it, if it has been soaked, andpress all the water out of it. Then pull it to pieces in sucha way as to leave no massed leaves; season it with salt andpepper, and put it into a braising-pan lined with slices of bacon.Add, for ten lbs. of sauerkraut, three quartered carrots, threemedium-sized onions, each stuck with a clove, a large faggot,three oz. of juniper berries and one-half oz. of peppercornscontained in a canvas bag, six oz. of goose dripping or lard,and one lb. of blanched breast of bacon, the latter to be with-drawn after one hour’s cooking.

Moisten, just enough to cover, with white consomm^; coverwith slices of bacon; boil, and then cook in the oven for fivehours with lid on.

To serve Sauerkraut.—Withdraw the vegetables, the faggot,and the juniper berries, and set the sauerkraut in a timbale,after having well drained it.

Surround it with thin slices of ham, rectangles of bacon,and some poached Frankfort or Strasburg sausages.

Red Cabbages (Choux Rouges)

CHOUX ROUGES à la FLAMANDE

Quarter the cabbages, suppress the outside leaves and thestumps, and cut the trimmed leaves into a fine julienne. Seasonwith salt, pepper, and nutmeg; sprinkle with vinegar, and putthis julienne into a well-buttered earthenware cocotte. Coverand cook in a moderate oven.

When the cooking is three-parts done, add four peeled andquartered russet apples and a tablespoonful of moist or pow-dered sugar.

Take note that the cooking must be gentle from start tofinish, and that the only moistening should be the vinegar.

MARINADED RED CABBAGES FOR HORS = d’(EUVRECut the cabbages into a small julienne as above, and put

them into a bowl or deep dish. Sprinkle with table salt, andleave to macerate for two days, stirring frequently the while.

Then drain, and put them into a pot with garlic cloves,peppercorns, and one bay leaf. Cover with raw vinegar, orthe latter boiled and cooled, and leave to marinade for a dayor two.

This marinaded cabbage forms an excellent adjunct to boiled

beef.

Choux Verts Pommes (Savoy Cabbages)

BRAISED CABBAGE

Quarter the cabbage; parboil and cool it.

Defoliate the quarters; suppress the outside leaves and themidribs of the remaining leaves; season with salt and pepper,and put the cabbage in a saucepan garnished with slices ofbacon, and containing one quartered carrot, one onion stuckwith a garlic clove, one faggot, two-thirds pint of consomm^,and three tablespoonfuls of stock fat per two lbs. of cabbage.Cover with slices of bacon; boil, and then braise gently for twohours.

CHOU A d’ANGLAISE

Plainly boil or steam the cabbqge. Press all the water outof it, between two plates, and cut it into lozenges or squares.

CHOU FARCI

Take a medium-sized round-headed or Savoy cabbage;parboil it; cool it, and suppress its stump. Slightly open outits leaves, and insert between them raw or cooked mince-meat, combined with chopped onion and parsley, and highlyseasoned. Reconstruct the cabbage, pressing it closely to-gether; wrap it in slices of bacon; string it, and braise itgently for three hours with stock and stock fat.

When about to serve, drain the cabbage; remove the stringand the slices of bacon; set it on a dish, and cover it with afew tablespoonfuls of the braising-liquor, cleared of all grease,reduced, and thickened with some half-glaze sauce.

Send what remains of the braising-liquor separately.

N.B.—The preparation is improved if the mince-meat withwhich the cabbage is stuffed be combined with a quarter of itsbulk of pilaff rice and the same quantity of foie-gras fat.

SOU-FASSUM PROVENCAL

Parboil and cool the cabbage as above; remove the outerlarge leaves, and set them on a net.

Upon this litter of cabbage leaves lay the following pro-ducts, mixed: —

The inside leaves of the cabbage, chopped up and seasoned;one-half lb. of ciseled and blanched white of a leek; one andthree-quarter lbs. of sausage-meat; six oz. of lean bacon, cutinto dice and frizzled; one chopped onion, fried in butter; twochopped tomatoes; a crushed clove of garlic; three oz. ofblanched rice and four oz. of fresh, young peas.

Gather up the ends of the net, and close it in such a way asto reconstruct the cabbage.

Cook it in mutton broth or in ordinary stock for three andone-half or four hours.

Serve the sou-fassum plain, on a round dish.

CABBAGES FOR GARNISH.—A

Parboil, cool, and thoroughly drain the cabbage. Removeas many large leaves as there are balls of stuffed cabbage re-quired, and, if the leaves be too small, use two for each ball.

Chop up the remains of the cabbage; season them with saltand pepper; put a small portion of them on each of the leaves;close the latter in the shape of balls, and set them one by onein a saut^pan.

Then proceed, for the cooking, as directed under “BraisedCabbage.”

210s—CABBAGES FOR GARNISH.—B

Prepare the cabbage as above; insert into the centre of eachball a portion of smooth pork forcemeat, the size of a pigeon’segg, and braise in the same way.

CABBAGES FOR GARNISH.—C

Parboil the necessary quantity of cabbage leaves, in accord-ance with the number of balls required. Cool them; spreadthem out; garnish the middle of each with one tablespoonfulof pilaff rice, mixed with foie-gras pur^e, and close up theleaves to form small packets.

Braise as in the case of No. 2104.

SCOTCH KALE (Choufrise), SPRING CABBAGE (Chouxde Printemps), BROCCOLI LEAVES, TURNIP-TOPS

These various kinds of greens are prepared in the Englishway, as described above, or they may be prepared with butter,like Brussels sprouts. The two above-mentioned modes ofpreparation are the only ones that suit them.

T T

CAULIFLOWER AND BROCCOLI(Chou-fleur et Broccoli)

Broccoli differs from cauliflower in the colour of its flowerand the arrangement of the parts of the latter. In thebroccoli the flower is of a deep violet. English broccoli neverreach the size of those grown in the South of France.

Many do not even grow to a head, while their flowers—thesize of hazel-nuts—are scattered among the interstices of thesurrounding leaves.

Cauliflowers and large broccoli allow of the same treatment.

CHOU-FLEUR à la CREME

Cut the cauliflowers into bunches; remove the small leaveswhich are attached, and cook the cauliflower in salted water.

Thoroughly drain; set the bunches in a timbale, reconstruct-ing the cauliflower in so doing, or on a dish covered with afolded napkin, and serve a cream sauce separately.

CHOU-FLEUR AU GRATIN

Having well drained the cauliflower, dry it in butter for afew minutes; mould it in a bowl, and pour a few tablespoonfulsof Mornay sauce into it.

Coat the bottom of a dish with the same sauce, and turn outthe cauliflower on the dish; completely cover with Mornaysauce; sprinkle with grated cheese mixed with raspings; bedewwith melted butter, and set the gratin to form.

CHOU-FLEUR à la MILANAISE

Set the cauliflower on a buttered dish sprinkled with gratedcheese. Also sprinkle the cauliflower with cheese; add a fewpieces of butter, and set the gratin to form.

On taking the dish out of the oven, sprinkle the cauliflowerwith nut-brown butter, and serve immediately.

CHOU-FLEUR à la POLONAISE

Thoroughly drain the cauliflower, and set it on a buttereddish.

Sprinkle it with chopped, hard-boiled egg-yolks and choppedparsley, mixed. When about to serve, bedew with nut-brownbutter, in which one-half oz. of fine bread-crumbs (per threeoz. of butter) should have been fried.

21,3—CAULIFLOWER WITH VARIOUS SAUCES

Cook the cauliflower in salted water. Drain it thoroughly,and set it in a timbale. Serve at the same time either a sauce-boat of Melted Butter, a Butter, a Hollandaise, or a Mousselinesauce, &c.

PUREE de CHOU-FLEUR dite à la DUBARRYCook the cauliflower in salted water; drain it well; rub itthrough tammy, and combine the resulting pur^e with onequarter of its bulk of somewhat firm, mashed potatoes withcream. Heat; add butter away from the fire, and dish in atimbale.

Brussels Sprouts (Choux de Bruxelles)

CHOUX de BRUXELLES A d’ANGLAISECook them in salted water; drain them well, and dish themon a drainer or in a timbale.

CHOUX de BRUXELLES à la CREMECook the sprouts; drain them well without cooling them;stew them in butter, and chop them up. Then combine themwith as much fresh cream as possible.

CHOUX de BRUXELLES SAUTESCook them, and, after having thoroughly drained them,throw them into an omelet-pan containing some very hot butter.Toss them until they are nicely frizzled; dish them in a tim-bale, and sprinkle them with chopped parsley.

CHOUX de BRUXELLES AU BEURRECook them, keeping them somewhat firm, and drain withoutcooling them.

Put them into a sautdpan; season them with salt and pepper;add two oz. of butter (per lb. of sprouts) cut into small pieces;cover, and stew in the oven for one-quarter hour.

PUREE de CHOUX de BRUXELLES dite FLAMANDEThree-parts cook the sprouts; drain them well without cool-ing them, and complete their cooking by stewing them inbutter. Rub them through tammy, and add to the resultingpuree one-third of its bulk of mashed potatoes.

Heat, add butter away from the fire, and dish in a timbale.

SEA KALE (Chou Marin)This is one of the best and most delicate of English vege-tables.

It is trimmed with great care, washed, and then tied intobunches of from five to six plants, and these are plainly cookedin salted water.

All cardoon recipes, and sauces given for asparagus, maybe applied to sea kale.

T T 2

644 GUIDE TO MODERN COOKERY

CUCUMBER AND VEGETABLE MARROW(Concombres et Courgettes)

Though of different shapes, these two vegetables allow ofalmost the same treatment when they are cooked. They areespecially used as garnishes.

CONCOMBRES à la CREME

Peel, and cut the cucumber to shapes resembling olives;parboil and drain these pieces. This done, three-parts cookthem in butter; moisten with boiling cream, and finish thecooking in reducing the cream. At the very last moment adda little Bechamel sauce with the view of slightly thickening thepreparation, and dish in a timbale.

CONCOMBRES GLACES

After having shaped them like large garlic cloves, quicklyparboil them. This done, treat them as directed under“Carottes glac^es,” and roll them sufficiently in their cooking-liquor, reduced to the consistence of a thick syrup, to thoroughlycoat them with it.

CONCOMBRES FARCIS.—A

Cut the cucumbers into two-inch lengths; peel, parboil, anddrain them. Then hollow them out to form small, round cases;set them side by side in a sautepan, and cook them in butter.When they are three-parts cooked, fill them with a raw, chickenforcemeat, effecting this operation by means of a piping-bag.The forcemeat should be slightly moulded in the cucumbercases.

Complete the cooking of the cucumber, gently, while poach-ing the forcemeat.

CONCOMBRES FARCIS.—B

Peel the cucumbers; split them open lengthwise, and emptythem by means of a root-spoon. This done, parboil and drainwithout cooling them.

Garnish each half-cucumber, level with the edges, with achicken forcemeat, prepared with frangipane, and combinedwith a third of its weight of Duxelles. Reconstruct thecucumbers by placing the halves one against the other; wrapthem each in a slice of bacon, and then in a piece of muslin,and finally string them. This done, braise them in the usualway. When they are cooked, remove their wrappings, andcut them into roundels the thickness of which is determined bythe size of the piece of which they are the adjuncts.

STACHYS (Crosnes du Japon)Whatever be their mode of preparation, stachys must becleaned, parboiled, and kept firm, and cooked in butter withoutcolouration.

CROSNES A LACRSMEAfter having parboiled the stachys and three-parts cookedthem in butter, moisten with boiling cream, and complete theircooking while reducing the cream. Add a little thin, freshcream at the last moment, and dish in a timbale.

CROSNES SAUTES AU BEURREAfter having parboiled, drained, and dried the stachys, putthem in an omelet-pan containing some very hot butter, andtoss them over a fierce fire, until they are well frizzled. Dishin a timbale, and sprinkle moderately with chopped parsley.

CROSNES AU VELOUTECompletely cook the stachys in salted water. Drain them,and cohere them with the required quantity of Velout6 flavouredwith mushroom essence.

CROQUETTES de CROSNESHaving cooked the stachys in salted water, and kept themsomewhat firm, thoroughly drain them and mix them with avery reduced Allemande sauce, in the proportion of one-fifthpint per lb. of stachys. Spread this preparation on a buttereddish, and cool. Now cut this preparation into portions weigh-ing about two oz.; shape these portions like balls, pears, quoits,or otherwise, dip them in beaten eggs, and roll them in veryfine bread-crumbs.

Plunge these croquettes into very hot fat five or six minutesbefore serving; drain them on a piece of linen; salt moderately,and dish on a napkin with very green, fried parsley.

PUREE de CROSNESCook the stachys in salted water, keeping them somewhatfirm, and add thereto four oz. of quartered potatoes per lb. ofstachys.

As soon as they are cooked, drain the stachys and thepotatoes; rub them through a sieve, and dry the purde over avery fierce fire. Add the necessary quantity of milk to bringthe pur£e to its proper consistence; heat; add butter away fromthe fire, and dish in a timbale.

SPINACH (Epinards)Spinach should only be prepared at the last moment, if pos-sible.

After having parboiled it in plenty of boiling salted water,

cool it, press out all its contained water, and, according to cir-cumstances, either chop it up or rub it through a sieve.

If it has to be served with the leaves left whole, merely drainit on a sieve, without either pressing or cooling it.

EPINARDS A d’ANGLAISE

Cook it after having carefully shredded it; drain it well,and dish in a timbale without cooling.

EPINARDS à la CREME

Having chopped up or rubbed the spinach through a sieve,put it into a saut^pan with two oz. of butter per lb., and dry itover a fierce fire.

Now add the quarter of its bulk of cream sauce to it, andsimmer gently for ten minutes.

Dish in a timbale when about to serve, and sprinkle thesurface with fresh cream.

EPINARDS AU GRATIN'

Dry the spinach as above in three oz. of butter per lb., andthen, in the same proportion, add two and one-half oz. of gratedcheese.

Set on a buttered gratin-dish; sprinkle copiously withgrated cheese and melted butter, and set the gratin to form ina fierce oven.

EPINARDS à la VIROFLAY

Spread some large leaves of blanched spinach on a napkin,and in the middle of each lay a subric, the substance of whichshould have been combined with very small croutons of bread-crumb fried in butter. Wrap the subrics in the spinach leaves;cover with Mornay sauce; sprinkle with grated cheese and meltedbutter, and set to glaze in a fierce oven.

SUBRICS d’EPINARDS

Dry the spinach in butter as described above, and add to itper lb. of spinach (away from the fire) one-sixth pint of veryreduced Bechamel sauce; two tablespoonfuls of thick cream;one egg and the yolks of three, well beaten; salt, pepper, andnutmeg.

Make a sufficient quantity of clarified butter very hot in anomelet-pan.

Take up some of the preparation of spinach by means of aspoon, and let the contents of the latter drop (propelled by thefinger) into the butter. Proceed thus in the making of thesubrics, and take care that they do not touch. »When a minute

has elapsed, turn them over with a spatula or a fork, that theirother sides may colour.

Set on a dish or in a timbale, and serve a cream sauceseparately.

CREPES aux EPINARDS

Parboil some well-shredded spinach; dry it in butter; seasonit, and add to it an equal quantity of Yorkshire-pudding paste(No. 1943).

Cook this preparation in a small, well-buttered omelet-panor in deep tartlet-moulds.

N.B.—These spinach pancakes constitute an excellent gar-nish for Relev^s of Beef, Veal, and Ham.

SOUFFLE aux EPINARDS

Make a composition after the directions given under No.2092. Spread this composition in two or three layers, and seton each of the latter a litter of well-cleaned and soaked anchovyfillets, arranged to form a lattice. Finish with a layer of spinachshaped like a dome, and set thereon two crossed rows of anchovyfillets. Cook after the manner of an ordinary souffle.

SOUFFL& aux EPINARDS aux TRUFFES

Proceed as directed in the preceding recipe, but substituteanchovy fillets for some fine slices of truffle.

N.B.—Both these spinach souffles may be served either asvegetables, in which case they are moulded in large timbales,or as garnishes, when they are dished in small cassolettes ofappropriate size.

They are very delicate preparations, which may be variedby watercress souffle—prepared in the same way.

FEUILLES de VIGNE FARCIES OU DOLMAS

(Stuffed Vine Leaves)

Provided the vine-leaves be very tender, they may serve inthe preparation of the following garnish:—Suppress theirstalks; parboil the leaves; drain them well, and arrange threeor four at a time in the form of a circular tray, in the centreof which lay a tablespoonful of pilaff rice to which some foie-gras pur£e has been added. This done, draw the ends of theleaves over the rice, so as to enclose it and to form regularballs of equal size.

Put these balls, well-pressed, one against the other in asaufflpan, the bottom of which should be garnished with slicesof bacon; cover with thin slices of bacon; moisten just enoughto cover, with good consomm^; boil, and then braise gently.

TUBEROUS FENNEL (Fenouil Tubereux)

This vegetable is not very well known in England, where itis sold only by the leading merchants of early-season vege-tables. It is prepared like the cardoons and the marrows.

BROAD BEANS (Feves)

Broad beans should be shelled just before being cooked, andit is quite the rule to peel them. Boil them in salted watercontaining a bunch of savory, the size of which should be inproportion to the quantity of broad beans. When they arecooked and drained, add the leaves of savory (chopped) to them.

FEVES AU BEURRE

Having well-drained and peeled the broad beans, toss themover a fierce fire to dry them, and then finish them, away fromthe fire, with three oz. of butter per lb. of beans.

FEVES à la CREME

After having dried and peeled the broad beans, cohere them(per lb.) with three tablespoonfuls of thick, fresh cream.

PUREE de FEVES

Proceed exactly as for pur£e of peas. This pur^e con-stitutes a very delicate garnish, which is particularly well suitedto ham.

GOMBOS

This vegetable—so common in America and the East—isonly very rarely used in England, where, however, it is nowbeginning to be better known.

There are two kinds of Gombos: the long and the roundkind. The latter is also called Bamia or Bamies. Both kinds areprepared after the same recipes.

GOMBOS à la CREME

After having trimmed them, parboil them in salted waterand drain them. Then cook them in butter, and, just beforeserving them, cohere them with a cream sauce.

GOMBOS POUR GARNITURES

Parboil the gombos until they are two-thirds cooked. Drainthem well, and complete their cooking in the braising-liquor ofthe piece they are to accompany.

If they are to garnish a poulet saute, complete their cookingin some thin veal gravy.

HOP SPROUTS (Jets de Houblon)

The eatable part is separated from the fibrous by breakingoff the ends of the sprouts, as in the case of asparagus or sprew.

After having washed them in several waters, cook them in saltedwater containing, per every quart, the juice of one half-lemon.

Hop sprouts may be prepared with butter, cream, velout6,&c. When served as a vegetable, they are invariably accom-panied by poached eggs, which are laid in a crown round themand alternated by comb-shaped croutons fried in butter.

Haricot-Beans (Haricots Blancs)

HARICOTS BLANCS A d’AMERICAINE (Lima Beans)

Cook the beans as described under No. 274. But add tothe prescribed ingredients one-half lb. of lean bacon per pintof dry beans.

When they are cooked and well drained, mix them with thebacon cut into dice, and cohere them with some good tomatosauce.

HARICOTS BLANCS AU BEURRE

Having well drained the haricot-beans, season them withsalt and pepper and cohere them with two oz. of butter per lb.of cooked beans. Dish in a timbale and sprinkle with choppedparsley.

HARICOTS BLANCS à la BRETONNE

Drain them well and cohere them with a Bretonne sauce, inthe proportion of one-third pint of sauce per lb. of cookedharicot-beans. Dish in a timbale with chopped parsley.

PUREE de HARICOTS BLANCS dite SOISSONNAISE

Rub the haricot-beans through a sieve while they are burn-ing-hot. Add to the pur£e (per lb. thereof) three oz. of butter;dry it over a very fierce fire, and then add some milk to it, tobring it to its proper consistence.

FLAGEOLETS (Haricots Flageolets)

These beans are used more especially fresh; but, when theyare out of season, recourse is often had to preserved or driedflageolets.

They are prepared in the same way as haricot-beans. Theirpur^e, which is very delicate, is known under the name of“Pur£e Musard,” and it is particularly suitable for the gar-nishing of mutton. It is also used as a thickening ingredientin the pur6e of French beans, and nothing can equal it for thepurpose; for, not only is it an unctuous thickening medium, butits flavour is peculiarly adapted to the throwing into relief ofthat of the French beans.

RED BEANS (Haricots Rouges)

Red beans are cooked in salted water with one-third lb. oflean bacon, one pint of red wine, one carrot, one onion stuckwith a clove, and one faggot per quart of beans. The baconshould be withdrawn as soon as cooked. These beans arecohered by means of manied butter, and they are then mixedwith the bacon, which is cut into dice and frizzled in butter.

FRENCH BEANS (Haricots Verts)

French beans are among the greatest vegetable delicacies;but they have to be prepared with the utmost care.

Their quality is such that they are almost always good, inspite of faulty preparation—so common in their case; but, whenthey are cooked with care, no other vegetable can surpass themin perfection of flavour. They should be taken quite fresh, andthey should not be cooked too long. They are best when theyseem a little firm to the teeth, without, of course, being in theleast hard.

They must not be cooled when cooked; they should only besauted over the fire with the view of causing the evaporation oftheir moisture.

After having seasoned them with salt and pepper, add tothem (per lb.) about three oz. of very fresh butter, cut intosmall pieces; saute them so as to effect their leason, andstraightway serve them.

Do not add chopped parsley to French beans, unless it bevery tender and gathered and chopped at the last moment.

HARICOTS PANACHES

This consists of French beans and flageolets, in equal quan-tities, cohered with butter.

pur£e de haricots verts

Cook the French beans in salted water; drain them well, andstew them in butter for eight or ten minutes. Rub themthrough a fine sieve, and mix the resulting pur£e with half itsbulk of very creamy, flageolet pur£e.

Lettuces (Laitues)

LAITUES BRAISI§ES AU JUS

After having parboiled, cooled, and pressed the water outof them, tie them together in twos or threes, and braise themas directed under No. 275. This done, cut them in two, unfoldthe end of each half, and set them on a dish, in the form of acrown; alternating them with heart-shaped croutons fried inbutter. Or, merely dish them in a timbale.

Coat them with the reduced braising-liquor combined withsome thickened veal gravy.

N.B.—Braised lettuces may also be stuffed after the mannerdescribed under No. 2106.

LA1TUES à la MOfiLLEBraise and dish the lettuces as above.

Upon the turban of lettuces, set a crown of large slices ofpoached marrow, and coat with a moderately thick butteredgravy.

LAITUES FARCIESParboil, cool, and press the lettuces.

This done, open them in the middle without touching theirstems, and garnish them with good forcemeat, combined withhalf its bulk of dry Duxelles (No. 223). Reconstruct the let-tuces; string them; braise them, and dish them as directedunder No. 2160.

LAITUES FARCIES POUR GARNITURE

Proceed as directed under Nos. 2104 to 2106.

LAITUES à la CRfeMEProceed as directed under No. 2089.

SOUFFLE de LAITUESProceed as directed under No. 2139.

Lentils (Lentilles)

Lentils are cooked as directed under the “preparation ofdry vegetables” (No. 274).

LENTILLES AU BEURRE

Carefully drain the lentils; dry them by tossing them overthe fire, and cohere them with butter in the proportion of twooz. of the latter per lb. of lentils.

Dish in a timbale, and sprinkle with a little chopped parsley.

PUREE de LENTILLESProceed as for the pur^e of haricot-beans.

VERONIQUE (Laver)As this vegetable is sold already cooked at English markets,it is only necessary to add enough good Espagnole sauce toit, when heating it, to make a properly consistent pur^e.

MAIZE (Ma'is)Take the maize when it is quite fresh and still milky, andcook it either in steam or salted water; taking care to retainthe leaves on the ears. When cooked, the leaves are drawn

back so as to represent stalks, and the ears are bared if theybe served whole. This done, set the ears on a napkin, andsend a hors-d’oeuvre dish of fresh butter to the table withthem.

If the maize has to be grilled, put the ears on a grill in theoven, and, when they have swollen and are of a golden colour,withdraw the grains and set the latter on a napkin. Sometimes,too, the ears are served whole.

When maize is served as an accompaniment, the grains areseparated from the stalk and cohered with butter or cream,exactly like peas.

Failing fresh maize, excellent preserved kinds are to befound on the market.

SOUFFLE de MAIS à la CRFME

Cook the maize in water or steam; rub it quickly throughtammy; put it into a saucepan with a small piece of butter, andquickly dry it.

This done, add sufficient fresh cream to this pur^e to make asomewhat soft paste. Thicken this paste with the yolks of threeeggs, per lb. of pur^e, and combine it with the whites of foureggs beaten to a stiff froth. Mould and cook after the mannerof an ordinary souffle.

SOUFFLE de MAIS AU PAPRIKA

Before rubbing the maize through a sieve, add to it twotablespoonfuls of chopped onion fried in butter, and a largepinch of paprika per lb. of maize. Proceed for the rest of theoperation as in the case of No. 2170.

N.B.—These two souffles are served as a garnish and maybe cooked either in a timbale or in small cassolettes. Theyconstitute excellent adjuncts to large, poached fowls.

CHESTNUTS (Marrons)

Slightly split open the shell on the convex sides of thenuts, and put them in the oven for from seven to eight minutes,on a tray containing a little water, that they may be shelled withease.

Or, split them open in the same way; put them in smallquantities at a time in a frying-basket, and plunge them intovery hot fat. Peel them while they are still quite hot.

STEWED CHESTNUTS

As soon as they are peeled, cook them in enough consomm£to just cover them, and add half a stick of celery per lb. ofchestnuts.

If they are intended for the stuffing of a goose or a turkey,keep them somewhat firm.

BRAISED AND GLAZED CHESTNUTS

Take some very large chestnuts, and dip them in hot fat inorder to peel them. Then set them in one layer, one againstthe other in a sautdpan. If they were heaped, only a poorresult could be obtained.

Moisten them, just enough to cover, with strong veal stock,and stir them as little as possible while they are cooking, soas to avoid breaking them.

When they are three-parts cooked, reduce the moistening,and gently roll the chestnuts in the glaze resulting from thisreduction, that they may be covered with a brilliant coating.

Chestnuts prepared in this way serve more particularly asa garnish.

PUREE de MARRONS

Having thoroughly peeled the chestnuts, cook them in whiteconsomm6, with a celery stalk as in the case of No. 2173, andone-half oz. of sugar per lb. of chestnuts. Continue cookinguntil they may be easily crushed; rub them through tammy,and treat the pur£e as directed in the case of the precedingones.

TURNIPS (Navets)

Whether served as vegetables or as a garnish, turnips areprepared like carrots. They may, therefore, either be servedglazed, or “& la Creme,” &c.

They may also be served stuffed, after the following re-cipes: —

STUFFED TURNIPS.—A

Take some round, medium-sized turnips, fairly equal in size.

Peel them, and, in so doing, shape them nicely; then, by meansof a round fancy-cutter, cut them deeply at their base, pressingthe instrument into the pulp.

This done, thoroughly parboil and empty them.

With the withdrawn pulp, prepare a pur£e, to which add anequal quantity of mashed potatoes. Garnish the turnips withthis pur£e, and shape the visible portion of the latter dome-fashion.

Set the stuffed turnips in a sautepan, and complete theircooking in butter, taking care to baste them frequently.

STUFFED TURNIPS.—B

Prepare the turnips as above; but stuff them with a pre-paration of semolina cooked in consomm^ and combined withgrated Parmesan.

Complete the cooking as directed in the preceding recipe.N.B.—Proceeding in the same way, turnips may be stuffedwith spinach, chicory, and even with farinaceous vegetables orrice, kept very creamy. All these garnishes are at once sightlyand excellent.

PUREE de NAVETS (Turnip Puree)

Slice the turnips and cook them in a little butter, salt, sugar,and the necessary amount of water. Rub through tammy, andthicken the resulting pur£e with only just the required quantityof very good mashed potatoes.

TURNIP-TOPS

Young turnip-tops are very much liked in England as aluncheon vegetable. They should be prepared like “Chouxverts cooked a I’anglaise.”

Onions (Oignons)

STUFFED ONIONS

Take some medium-sized, mild, Spanish onions; cut themat a point one-quarter of their height from the top, and parboilthem thoroughly.

Empty them, leaving only a wall one-third in. thick; chopup the withdrawn parts, and mix them with an equal quantityof Duxelles (No. 225).

Garnish the emptied onions with this preparation; completetheir cooking by braising them, and glaze them at the lastmoment, simultaneously with the formation of the gratin.

N.B.—Proceed in the same way for onions stuffed withspinach, Rizotto, or semolina, &c., as suggested under Nos.2177 and 2178.

Onions may also be garnished with a souffle preparation ofspinach, tomatoes, chicory, &c. Herein lies scope for a greatvariety of excellent and uncommon garnishes.

FRIED ONIONS

Cut them into roundels one-fifth in. thick; separate the rings;season them with salt and pepper; dredge them and fry them invery hot oil.

Drain on a piece of linen and salt slightly.

Onions prepared in this way are used particularly as anaccompaniment.

GLAZED ONIONS

For the preparation without colouration: Peel some smahonions of equal size without grazing them. Set them to cook

in enough white consomm^ to almost cover them, and two oz.of butter per pint of consomm£.

At the last moment roll them in their cooking-liquor, reducedto a glaze.

For the preparation with colouration: Cook the onions verygently in butter, with a pinch of powdered sugar, so that thecooking and the colouring may be effected together.

PUREE d’OIGNONS, dite SOUBISE

See No. 104, in the chapter on sauces.

SORREL (Oseille)

Having shredded the sorrel and washed it in several waters,set it to cook gently in a little water. This done, thoroughlydrain it on a sieve and mix it with a pale roux, consisting oftwo oz. of butter and one oz. of flour. Add one and one-quarterpints of consommd, salt, and a pinch of sugar to it, and braiseit in the oven for two hours.

Then rub it through tammy; thicken it with the yolks ofsix eggs or three whole eggs beaten to a stiff froth and strainedthrough a strainer. Heat, and finish with one-sixth pint ofcream and five oz. of butter.

Dish in a timbale, and sprinkle with strong, veal stock.

OXALIS

Cook this in boiling salted water after having well cleanedand washed it. It may then be prepared “k la Creme,”stuffed, or “au Gratin.”

Oxalis pur£e is called Purde Br^silienne, and is prepared inthe same way as turnip puree.

SWEET POTATOES

Swreet potatoes are generally served, baked in their skins,and accompanied by fresh butter. They may also be preparedaccording to the majority of potato-recipes, especially thefollowing: —

Sautees, Gratinees, Mashed, Duchesse, &c.

They may also be fried; but, in that case, they should beserved the moment they are ready, for they soften very quickly.

Finally, they may be prepared souffle-fashion, after thedirections given under “Souffle de Pommes de Terre.”

PEAS (Petits Pois)

Whatever be the treatment to which peas are to be subjected,always take them very green and freshly gathered, and shellthem only at the last minute. Peas are one of the vegetablesmost prone to lose their quality through want of care. If pre-

pared with pains, the delicacy of their flavour is incomparable;but the slightest neglect on the part of the operator rendersthem savourless and commonplace.

PETITS POIS A d’ANGLAISE

Cook them quickly in salted boiling water; drain them, anddry them by tossing them over a fierce fire. Dish them in atimbale, and serve some pats of very fresh butter separately.

PETITS POIS AU BEURRE

As soon as the peas are cooked, drain them and toss themover a fierce fire, to dry. Then season them with a pinch ofpowdered sugar, and cohere them, away from the fire, withbutter, in the proportion of three oz. per pint of peas.

PETITS POIS à la BONNE-FEMME

Fry twelve oz. of small onions and four oz. of breast ofbacon, cut into dice and blanched in butter; add one-half oz. offlour to the latter; cook the roux for a moment; moisten withone-half pint of consomm£ and boil.

Put one quart of freshly-shelled peas into this sauce; addthe onions and the bacon, together w'ith a bunch of parsley;and cook, reducing the sauce to half in so doing.

PETITS POIS à la FLAMANDE

Prepare one-half lb. of new carrots as though they were tobe glazed.

When half-cooked, add two-thirds pint of freshly-shelledpeas to them. Complete the cooking of the two vegetablestogether, and, at the last moment, add butter away from thefire.

PETITS POIS à la FRANCAISE

Take a saucepan, of a size a little larger than would be neces-sary to just hold the following products, and put into it onequart of freshly-shelled peas; a faggot containing the heart ofa lettuce, two sprays of parsley, and two of chervil; twelvesmall onions, four oz. of butter, one-third oz. of salt, and two-thirds oz. of loaf-sugar. Mix the whole together until it formsa compact mass, and place in the cool until ready for cooking.Add three tablespoonfuls of water, w'hen about to cook the peas,and cook gently with lid on.

When about to serve, withdraw the faggot; cisel the lettuce;add it to the peas, and cohere the whole with butter, away fromthe fire.

N.B.—Raw, ciseled lettuce may be added to the peas; but,as various tastes must be allowed for, it is better to insert the

lettuce whole, and to mix it with the peas afterwards, if it beso desired. The lettuce may also be quartered and laid on thepeas without being mixed with them.

PETITS POIS à la MENTHE

Cook the peas in salted water, together with a bunch of freshmint.

Then prepare them in the English way or “au Beurre,” andlay a few parboiled mint leaves upon them when serving.

219s—PUR^E de POIS FRAIS, dite SAINT-GERMAIN

Cook the peas with just enough boiling water to cover them,and season it with one-half oz. of salt, and one-sixth oz. of sugarper quart. Add a lettuce and a few parsley leaves (tied to-gether). When the peas are cooked, drain them; and reducetheir cooking-liquor while they are being rubbed through asieve.

Work the pur^e with four oz. of fresh butter per quart, andfinally add to it the cooking-liquor, reduced almost to a glaze.

MOULDED PEASE PUR^E FOR GARNISH

Prepare the pur^e as above; but keep it a little creamier. Mixwith it, per quart, two whole eggs and the yolks of three, beatenand strained through muslin. With this preparation, fill somedariole- or baba-moulds, according to the piece for which thetimbales are intended, and poach them in a bain-marie for fromtwenty to twenty-five minutes.

Remember to let them stand for five minutes before un-moulding them.

N.B.—Timbales of haricot-beans, flageolets, or lentil pur£e,are prepared similarly.

CAPSICUM OR PIMENTOS (Poivrons doux)

The capsicums used in cookery are of various kinds: theChilian and Cayenne kinds (Chili and Cayenne peppers) whichhave a strong, burning taste, are only used as condiments.

The large or mild capsicums, green, red, or yellow, are usedmore particularly as garnishes. Although the difference intheir colouration is accompanied by a difference of quality,' theyare not easily distinguished in this respect; and, although thelarge, red Spanish capsicums are the best, the other varietiesmay be treated in the same way as the former.

Whatever be the kind of capsicums used, either grill orscald them in order to skin them, and clear them of their seeds.According to the purpose they are intended for, they are eithercut up or left whole.

U U

658 GUIDE TO MODERN COOKERY

219S—PIMENTOS FARCIS

For this purpose take some small, green, carrot-shaped cap-sicums.

Remove their stems, after having skinned them; empty them,and half-fill them with half-cooked, pilaff rice.

Then set them in a saut^pan, and carefully braise them withexcellent stock.

CAPSICUMS FOR GARNISHING

For this purpose, the large red, Spanish capsicums are best.Braise them when they are peeled, and, when cooked, cutthem up as the requirements may suggest.

PUREE de PIMENTOS

Braise some large, red capsicums, with two-thirds of theirweight of rice. When the whole is well cooked, rub it througha sieve, and add butter to the extent of two oz. per quart of thepreparation.

N.B.—This purde is particularly well suited to poached fowlsand white meats, and it is well to keep it thin.

POTATOES (Pommes de Terre)

Ordinary potatoes are rarely of good quality in England,and they do not lend themselves as well as certain Continentalvarieties do to the various culinary uses to which this valuabletuber may be put.

The very best kinds of potato are almost unknown in Eng-land, and the Dutch and Vitelotte potatoes have to be imported.

POMMES de TERRE A d’ANGLAISE

Turn the potatoes to the shape of large garlic cloves, andcook them in salted water or steam. They accompany moreespecially boiled fish.

The English method is to cook them without salt.

POMMES de TERRE ANNA

Cut them to the shape of cylinders; slice these into thinroundels; wash them, and dry them in a piece of linen.

Set these roundels in circles on the bottom of the mouldproper to this potato preparation, or in a well-buttered thick-bottomed saut^pan; let them overlap one another, and let thelay of each circle be reversed.

Season; spread a coat of butter upon the first layer, andproceed in the same way with a second layer.

Make five or six layers in this way, seasoning and spread-ing butter over each.

Cover the utensil; cook in a good oven for thirty minutes;

turn the whole over, if necessary, to equalise the colouring;turn out upon a saucepan-lid, to drain away the butter, and thentilt the whole on to a dish.

POMMES ANNA FOR GARNISHINGEither dariole- or baba-moulds may be used for this purpose;but they should be tinned copper ones if possible. After havingthoroughly buttered them, garnish them with thin roundels ofpotato, cut to the diameter of the moulds, seasoned, and setone upon the other. Set the moulds on a tray containingenough very hot fat to reach half-way up to their brims, andcook in a very hot oven for twenty-five minutes.

Turn out just before serving.

POMMES de TERRE BERNY

Add chopped truffles to some “Croquette” paste (No. 219),in the proportion of two oz. of the former to one lb. of thelatter; and divide up this preparation into two-oz. portions.Mould these to shapes resembling apricots; dip them in beateneggs (No. 174), and roll them in almonds cut into the thinnestpossible splinters. Plunge the potato balls into hot fat five orsix minutes before serving.

POMMES de TERRE à la BOULANGERS

This preparation has been given in various recipes (see No.

).

POMMES de TERRE BYRONPrepare the required amount of “Pommes Macaire” (No.2228), and cook in butter in a small frying-pan. Dish; sprinklecopiously with cream and grated cheese, and set to glazequickly.

POMMES de TERRE CHATEAUTurn them to the shape of large olives; season them; cookthem gently in clarified butter, that they may be golden andvery soft; and, just before serving, sprinkle them moderatelywith chopped parsley.

POMMES de TERRE à la CREMEVitelotte or new kidney potatoes are needed for this prepara-tion.

Cook them in salted water; peel them as soon as this is done,and cut them into rather thick roundels. Put them in a sautd-pan; moisten, enough to cover them, with boiling cream;season, and reduce the cream.

At the last moment, finish with raw cream.

U U 2

66o

CROQUETTES de POMMES de TERRE

Prepare the necessary quantity of “Croquette” paste (No.219), and divide it into two-oz. portions. Roll these to theshape of corks or pears; treat them a Vanglaise, and put theminto very hot fat, five or six minutes before serving.

CROQUETTES de POMMES de TERRE à la DAUPHINE

Take the required amount of “Pommes Dauphine” pre-paration (No. 220); divide it into two-oz. portions; mould theseto the shape of corks; treat them a Vanglaise, and fry them likeordinary croquettes.

POMMES de TERRE à la DUCHESSE

Use the same preparation as for No. 2210. Mould the por-tions to the shape of small cottage-brioches, galettes or smallloaves, or shape them by means of the piping-bag. Arrangethem on a buttered tray; gild them with beaten egg, and colourthem in a fierce oven for seven or eight minutes before servingthem.

POMMES de TERRE DUCHESSE AU CHESTER

Use the same preparation as for No. 2210, and combine itwith two oz. of grated Chester per lb. Mould it to the shapeof very small galettes; set these portions on a buttered tray;gild them with beaten eggs; cover each with a thin slice ofChester, and set them in the oven for seven or eight minutesbefore serving.

POMMES de TERRE FONDANTES

Cut the potatoes to the shape of large, elongated olives, andlet each weigh about three oz. Gently cook them in butter, ina saut^pan, and take care to turn them over.

When they are cooked, withdraw them, so as to slightlyflatten them with a fork without breaking them. Drain awaytheir butter; return them to the saut£pan with three oz. of freshbutter per every two lbs. of their weight, and cook them withlid on until they have entirely absorbed the butter.

POMMES de TERRE EN ALLUMETTES

Trim the potatoes square, and then cut them into smallrods, of one-fifth in. sides. Put them in hot fat, and let themdry well before draining them.

POMMES de TERRE CHATOUILLARD

Trim the potatoes, and cut them into long even ribbons one-eighth in. thick. Treat these ribbons like “Pommes souffles”(see No. 2221).

CHIPPED POTATOES

Cut the potatoes into thin roundels, by means of a specialplane; put them into cold water for ten minutes; drain them;dry them in linen, and fry them, keeping them very crisp.Serve them cold or hot, with game roasted in the English way.

POMMES de TERRE COLLERETTE

Turn the potatoes to the shape of corks, and cut them with aspecial knife which grooves them. Treat them like chippedpotatoes.

POMMES de TERRE PAILLES

Cut the potatoes into a long, thin julienne; wash them andthoroughly dry them on a piece of linen.

Put them into hot fat; and, at the end of a few minutes,drain them in a frying-basket. Just before serving them,plunge them afresh into smoking fat, that they may be verycrisp; drain them on a piece of linen, and salt them moderately.

POMMES de TERRE PONT-NEUF

Trim the potatoes square, and cut them into rods of half-inchsides. Plunge them into hot fat, and leave them there untilthey are crisp outside and creamy in.

This preparation represents the generic type of friedpotatoes.

POMMES de TERRE SOUFFLEES

Trim the potatoes square, and carefully cut them into slicesone-eighth inch thick. Wash them in cold water; thoroughlydry them, and put them into moderately hot fat. As soon asthe potatoes are in it, gradually heat the fat until they arecooked—which they are known to be when they rise to thesurface of the frying fat.

Drain them in the frying-basket, and at once immerse themin fresh and hotter fat. This final immersion effects the puffing,which results from the sudden contact with intense heat.

Leave the potatoes to dry; drain them on a stretched pieceof linen; salt them moderately, and dish them.

QRATIN de POMMES de TERRE à la DAUPHINOISE

Finely slice two lbs. of fair-sized Dutch potatoes. Put themin a basin, and add thereto salt, pepper, grated nutmeg, onebeaten egg, one and one-half pints of boiled milk, and four oz.of fresh, grated Gruyere.

Thoroughly mix up the whole.

Pour this preparation into earthenware dishes, rubbed withgarlic and well buttered; copiously sprinkle with grated

Gruy6re; add a few pieces of butter, and cook in a moderateoven for from forty to forty-five minutes.

POMMES de TERRE à la HONGROISE

Fry four oz. of chopped onion in butter, together with acoffeespoonful of paprika. Add two peeled, pressed, and slicedtomatoes; two lbs. of potatoes, cut into somewhat thick roundels,and moisten, just enough to cover, with consomm6. Cook,while almost entirely reducing the moistening, and sprinkle withchopped parsley at the last moment.

POMMES de TERRE GRATINEES

This preparation may be made in two ways as follows: —

(1) Make a smooth potato purde; this done, put it into a deep,buttered gratin-d\sh; smooth its surface; sprinkle the latter withgrated cheese mixed with fine raspings; bedew with meltedbutter, and set the gratin to form in a fierce oven.

(2) Bake some fine, well-washed, Dutch potatoes in the oven.As soon as they are cooked, open them lengthwise; withdrawtheir pulp; rub the latter through a sieve while it is still quitehot, and finish it after the manner of an ordinary pur£e.

Fill the half-shells with pur£e; sprinkle the latter with gratedcheese and raspings; lay the half-shells on a tray, and set thegratin to form as above.

On taking the potatoes out of the oven, dish them on anapkin, and serve them immediately.

POMMES de TERRE AU LARD

Frizzle in butter one-half lb. of breast of salted pork, cut intodice and blanched, and twelve small onions. Drain the baconand the onions; mix one oz. of flour with the butter; brown fora few minutes, and moisten with one and one-quarter pints ofconsomm6. Season with a pinch of pepper, and add two lbs.of medium-sized, quartered and well-trimmed potatoes, thebacon and the onions, and a faggot. Cover and cook gently.

Dish in a timbale, and sprinkle moderately with choppedparsley.

POMMES de TERRE LORETTE

Add some grated cheese to the preparation for “PommesDauphine,” in the proportion of one oz. of the former per lb. ofthe latter.

Divide up this mixture into one and one-half oz. portions;mould these to the shape of crescents, and dredge them mode-rately.

Plunge these crescents into very hot fat about six minutesbefore serving.

POMMES de TERRE à la LYONNA1SECut some peeled and plain-boiled potatoes into roundels, andtoss these in butter in a frying-pan. Likewise toss some slicedonions in butter, the quantity of the former measuring one-fourth of that of the potatoes. When the onions are of a nicegolden colour, add them to the sauted potatoes; season withsalt and pepper; saute the two products together for a fewminutes, that they may mix thoroughly, and dish them in atimbale with chopped parsley.

POMMES de TERRE MACAIREBake some Dutch potatoes in the oven. As soon as theyare done, empty them and collect their pulp on a dish; seasonit with salt and pepper, and work it with a fork; adding to it,the while, one and one-half oz. of butter per lb.

Spread this preparation in the form of a galctte on thebottom of an omelet-pan containing some very hot, clarifiedbutter, and brown it well on both sides.

POMMES de TERRE MAIREPrepare these exactly like “Pommes k la Cr£me.”

POMMES de TERRE à la MA1TRE-d’H6TEL

Cook some medium-sized Dutch potatoes in salted water;peel them; cut them into roundels while they are still quite hot,and cover them with boiling milk.

Season them with salt and white pepper; completely reducethe milk, and dish them in a timbale with chopped parsley.

POMMES de TERRE MARQUISEMix some very reduced and very red tomato pur£e with thepreparation for “Pommes Duchesse,” in the proportion of threetablespoonfuls of the former per lb. of the latter.

Set this preparation on buttered trays (by means of a piping-bag fitted with a large, grooved pipe) in shapes resemblinghalf-eggs.

Gild them slightly with beaten eggs, and set them in a some-what hot oven seven or eight minutes before serving.

POMMES de TERRE à la MENTHECook some fair-sized new potatoes in the English w^ay, andadd a bunch of mint to them. Dish them in a timbale, and seta mint-leaf (from the bunch) upon each potato.

664 GUIDE TO MODERN COOKERY

POMMES de TERRE MIREILLE

Cut some medium-sized, raw potatoes into roundels. Seasonthem and saute them in butter. When they are ready, add tothem, per lb., four oz. of sliced artichoke-bottoms, tossed inbutter, and one and one-half oz. of truffle slices.

Saute the whole so as to ensure a complete mixture, anddish in a timbale.

POMMES de TERRE MIRETTE

Cut some raw potatoes into a julienne one-eighth inch wide,and cook them in butter, keeping them very creamy. Add tothem, per lb., two oz. of a julienne of truffles and three table-spoonfuls of melted meat glaze.

Mix; dish in a timbale; sprinkle with grated Parmesan andmelted butter, and set to glaze quickly.

POMMES de TERRE MOUSSELINEPrepare a flawn-crust, baked without colouration.Meanwhile, bake a few Dutch potatoes in the oven; with-draw their pulp; season it with salt and white pepper, and workit over the fire with four oz. of butter and the yolks of two eggsper lb. of its weight. Add one-sixth pint of whisked cream, andset the preparation in the crust, shaping it like a dome. Deco-rate by means of a piping-bag, fitted with a grooved pipe, withsome of the preparation which should have been put aside;sprinkle with melted butter, and set to glaze quickly.

POMMES de TERRE NOISETTES

Cut the potatoes, by means of a round spoon-cutter, intopieces the size of hazel-nuts. Season and cook them in butter,and take care to keep them nicely golden and creamy.

POMMES de TERRE PARISIENNE

Prepare some “Pommes Noisettes” as above; but cut thema little smaller. When they are cooked, roll them in meltedmeat glaze, and sprinkle them with chopped parsley.

POMMES de TERRE PARMESANE

Proceed as directed under “Pommes au Chester”(No. 2213), but substitute Parmesan for the latter.

POMMES de TERRE PERSILLEES

Cook the potatoes in the English way, that is to say, boilthem plainly; drain them well, and roll them in melted butterand chopped parsley.

POMMES de TERRE ROBERT

Prepare a composition of “Pomme Macaire,” and addthereto, per lb., three eggs and a large pinch of chopped chives.Cook in the frying-pan as for “Pomme Macaire.”

POMMES de TERRE à la ROXELANEBake six fine Dutch potatoes in the oven. Withdraw thepulp from their insides, and work it, together with one-third lb.of butter and four egg-yolks, and enough fresh cream to thin it.Complete with the whites of two eggs, beaten to a stiff froth.

Set this preparation in small timbales, made from briochesthe knobs of which have been removed, and the under halves ofwhich have been emptied of all crumb. Sprinkle with choppedtruffle, and bake in a mild oven as for a souffle.

POMMES de TERRE à la SAVOYARDEProceed as for No. 2222; but replace the milk by some con-somme.

POMMES de TERRE à la SAINT-FLORENTIN

Prepare some “Pommes Croquettes” paste (No. 219).Combine therewith (per lb.) two oz. of chopped, lean ham.Roll the portions into the shape of corks; dip them in beateneggs, and roll them in vermicelli. This done, flatten so as togive them a rectangular shape, and fry them in very hot fat.

POMMES de TERRE SCHNEIDERProceed as directed under No. 2230; but for the milk sub-stitute some consomm6. Reduce in the same way, and finishwith butter, melted meat glaze, and chopped parsley.

POMMES de TERRE SUZETTEPeel some fine, Dutch potatoes, and turn them to the shapeof eggs. Cut them flat at one end that they may stand upright,and bake them on a tray in the oven.

Open them like a boiled egg; put aside the pieces thus cutoff, and withdraw the pulp from their insides. Season this pulp,and work it; adding to it the while, per lb., two oz. of butter,two egg-yolks, a few tablespoonfuls of thick cream, and a littlesalpicon of the white of a chicken, tongue, truffles, and mush-rooms. Fill the potato-shells with this preparation; readjustthe covers, and set them in the oven for ten minutes.

On withdrawing them from the oven, set the potatoes on adish, and glaze them with melted butter.

POMMES de TERRE VOISIN

Prepare these exactly like “Pommes Anna,” but sprinkleeach layer of potato-roundels with grated cheese. The cookingis the same.

POMMES NANA (For Garnishing)

Cut the potatoes into a julienne; season them, and mouldthem by heaping them into well-buttered, dariole-moulds. Cookthem, like “Pommes Anna” (for garnishing), on a tray con-taining some very hot fat.

On taking them out of the oven, turn them out and sprinklethem with Chateau sauce.

MASHED POTATOES

Peel and quarter some Dutch potatoes, and quickly cookthem in salted water. When they feel soft to the touch, drainthem; rub them through a sieve, and work the pur£e vigorouslywith three oz. of butter per lb. of potatoes. Then add, little bylittle, about one-half pint of boiling milk, in order to bring thepur£e to the required consistence. Heat without boiling, andserve.

Remember that mashed potatoes should be only just cooked,and that if they be allowed to wait they lose all their quality.

QUENELLES de POMMES de TERRE

Prepare a composition as for “Pommes Duchesse,” and addthereto (per two lbs.) three whole eggs and one-third lb. offlour. Divide up the preparation into one and one-half oz.portions; mould these to the shape of corks or quoits, or mouldthem by means of a spoon, and set them in a buttered saut^pan.Poach them in salted water; drain them; set them on a buttereddish sprinkled with grated cheese; dredge with grated cheese;sprinkle with melted butter, and set the gratin to form.

On taking the dish out of the oven, sprinkle the quenelleswith nut-brown butter.

SOUFFLE de POMMES de TERRE

Prepare a pint of mashed potatoes with cream; add theretothe raw yolks of three eggs and their whites beaten to a stifffroth. Set in a buttered souffle saucepan, or in small porcelaincases, and cook like an ordinary souffle.

Rice (Riz)

RIZ AU BLANC (For Fowls and Eggs)

Wash one-half lb. of Carolina rice; put it into a saucepan;cover it with plenty of cold water; salt it, and parboil it forone-quarter hour.

This done, drain it and put it into a saut^pan with two andone-half oz. of butter cut into small pieces. Mix with a fork;cover, and place in a moderate oven for fifteen minutes.

RIZ AU GRASParboil one-half lb. of Carolina rice; drain it; fry it in butter,and moisten it with twice as much white and rather fat con-somme as would be needed just to cover it. Set to boil, and thencook it gently in the oven for fifteen minutes.

RIZ à la GRECQUEPrepare some “Pilaff” rice. Add to it, per lb. of its weightone half-onion, chopped and fried in butter, together with twooz. of fat sausage-meat, divided into small portions, and two oz.of ciseled lettuce; cook the whole, and complete with one-quarterpint of peas, cooked “k la Frangaise,” and one and one-halfoz. of red capsicums cut into dice.

This garnish is mixed with the rice seven or eight minutesbefore serving.

RIZ A d’INDIENNEParboil one-half lb. of Patna rice in salted water, for fifteenminutes; stirring it from time to time the while.

Drain it; wash it in several cold waters; lay it on a napkin,and set the latter on a tray or on a sieve. Dry for fifteenminutes in a steamer or in a very moderate oven.

RIZ PILAFF

Fry one chopped half-onion and one-half lb. of Carolina ricein two oz. of butter. Stir over the fire, until the rice is wellaffected all over; moisten with one quart of white consomm£;cover, and cook in a moderate oven for eighteen minutes.Transfer it to another saucepan as soon as it is cooked.

PILAFF RICE (For the Stuffing of Fowls)Pilaff rice is frequently used in stuffing fowls.

For this purpose, when it is cooked, it is combined (per quart)with a little cream, four oz. of foie-gras dice, and as muchtruffle, also in dice. The rice should only be three-parts cookedfor stuffings; for it completes its cooking inside the bird. Forthis reason the cream is added, that the rice may absorb itwhile its cooking is being completed.

RIZ PILAFF à la TURQUE

Prepare some pilaff rice as directed under No. 2255, and,while it is cooking, add to it enough saffron to make it of anice, golden colour. When cooked, add four oz. of peeled andconcassed tomatoes to it.

RIZOTTO à la PIEMONTAISE

Fry a medium-sized onion in butter, and add to it one-halflb. of Piedmont rice. Put the rice on the side of the stove;add some saffron to it and stir it until it is well saturated withbutter. Moisten the rice with about one quart of consomm^per lb. The consomm£ should be added to the rice in sevenor eight instalments, and as fast as it becomes absorbed, a freshsupply should be forthcoming. When adding the liquor, stirthe rice with a wooden spoon.

Cook the rice under cover, and, to the resulting preparation,which should thus be creamy, add a few pieces of fresh butterand some grated Parmesan.

The dish may be finished, either with shavings of whitetruffles or ham cut into dice.

SALSIFY or OYSTER PLANT (Salsifis)

There are two kinds of salsify :—the white and the black,which is also called “viper’s grass.”

After having carefully scraped and washed it, cook it in ablanc. The same preparations suit the two kinds.

FRIED SALSIFY

After having thoroughly drained it, cut it into three andone-half lengths, and put these on a dish.

Season with salt and pepper; add lemon juice, a few drops ofoil, some chopped parsley, and leave to marinade for fromtwenty-five to thirty minutes, taking care to toss the salsify fromtime to time. This done, drain the lengths of salsify, dip themin some thin batter; plunge them in very hot fat, and drainthem when the batter is quite dry. Dish them on a napkin withfried parsley.

N.B.—It is not absolutely necessary to marinade salsify; thequestion is one of taste.

SALSIFIS SAUTE

Cut it into two-inch lengths; dry them very well, and tossthese in butter in an omelet-pan, until they are of a nice goldencolour. Season, and dish in a timbale with fried parsley.

SALSIFIS à la CREME

Proceed as directed in the case of other vegetables preparedin this way.

Tomatoes

GRILLED TOMATOES

Take some whole tomatoes, if possible; oil them copiously,and grill them gently.

TOMATES FARCIES

If the tomatoes to be stuffed be large, cut them in twolaterally; if they be medium-sized or small, a lateral slice cutfrom their stem-ends is sufficient. In any case, press themslightly in order to exude their juice and seeds; season theminside with salt and pepper; set them on an oiled tray, and half-cook them in the oven.

Finally, stuff them as their designation on the menu re-quires.

TOMATES FARCIES AU GRATIN

Having prepared the tomatoes as above, stuff them withsomewhat stiff Duxelles; sprinkle with raspings and a few dropsof oil, and set the gratin to form in a hot oven.

On taking the dish out of the oven, surround the tomatoeswith a thread of clear tomated half-glaze sauce.

TOMATES FARCIES à la PROVENCALE

Prepare the tomatoes as follows :—Cut them in two; removetheir seeds; season them, and place them, cut side undermost,in an omelet-pan containing very hot oil. Turn them overwhen they are half-cooked; cook them for a little while longer;lay them on a gratin-dish, and stuff them with the followingpreparation :—For six tomatoes, fry two tablespoonfuls ofchopped onion in oil; add four peeled, pressed, and concassedtomatoes, a pinch of chopped parsley, and a crushed clove ofgarlic, and cook under cover for twelve minutes. Completewith four tablespoonfuls of bread-crumbs, soaked in consomm£and rubbed through a sieve; two anchovies also rubbed througha sieve, and finish with some somewhat fat, braised-beef gravy.When the tomatoes are stuffed, sprinkle them with bread-crumbscombined with grated cheese; sprinkle with oil, and set thegratin to form.

These tomatoes may be served either hot or cold.

TOMATES FARCIES à la PORTUGAISE

Stuff the tomatoes with pilaff rice combined with a quarter

of its volume of concassed tomatoes. Dish this rice in theshape of a regular dome, and sprinkle it with chopped parsley.

N.B.—In addition to the above recipes, tomatoes preparedas already directed may also be garnished with minced chicken

or lamb meat, or with scrambled eggs, sprinkled with gratedParmesan, and then set to glaze at the salamander.

TOMATES SAUTEES à la PROVENCALE

Having halved, pressed, and seasoned the tomatoes, putthem, cut side undermost, in an omelet-pan containing very hotoil. Turn them over when they are half-cooked, and sprinklethem with a little chopped parsley, together with a mite ofgarlic, and some bread-crumbs. Place them in a moderateoven in order to finish their cooking, and dish the tomatoes themoment they are withdrawn from the oven.

PUREE de TOMATES

See Tomato Sauce (No. 29).

SOUFFLE de TOMATES à la NAP0L1TA1NE

Prepare one-half pint of very reduced tomato pur^e, andcombine therewith two oz. of grated Parmesan, two tablespoon-fuls of very stiff Bechamel sauce, and the yolks of three eggs.

Add the three whites, beaten to a stiff froth, and spread thepreparation in layers in a buttered, souffle timbale; setting uponeach layer a litter of freshly-cooked macaroni, cohered withbutter and grated Parmesan. Cook like an ordinary souffle.

Jerusalem Artichokes (Topinambours)

TOPINAMBOURS A d’ANGLAISE

Cut the Jerusalem artichokes to the shape of large olives,and gently cook them in butter, without colouration. Seasonthem, and cohere them with a little thin Bechamel sauce.

TOPINAMBOURS FRITS

Peel and cut the Jerusalem artichokes into thick slices.Cook these in butter; dip them in batter, and fry them at thelast moment.

PUREE de TOPINAMBOURS

Peel, slice, and cook the Jerusalem artichokes in butter.Rub them through a sieve, and work the pur^e over the fire,with two oz. of butter per lb. Add enough mashed potatoes tothicken the preparation, and complete with a few tablespoonfulsof boiling milk.

SOUFFLE de TOPINAMBOURSProceed as for No. 2250.

Truffles (Truffes)

Truffles are used especially as a garnish; but they may alsobe served as a vegetable or a hors-d’oeuvre.

When so served, they should be prepared very simply; forthey require no refining treatment to make them perfect.

TRUFFES SOUS LA CENDRE

Take some large truffles, and clean them well. Season themwith salt and pepper and a few drops of liqueur brandy; com-pletely enclose them in a layer of patty paste, and bake themin the oven from twenty-five to thirty minutes.

Serve them in their case of paste.

TRUFFES AU CHAMPAGNE

Take some fine, well-cleaned truffles; season them, and cookthem, with lid on, in champagne.

This done, set them in a timbale, or in small silver sauce-pans.

Almost completely reduce the champagne; add thereto alittle thin, strong, veal stock; strain the whole through muslin;pour it over the truffles, and place these on the side of the stovefor ten minutes without allowing the stock to boil.

TRUFFES à la CREME

Cut one lb. of raw, peeled truffles into thick slices. Seasonthem with salt and pepper, and cook them very gently in twooz. of butter and a few drops of burnt liqueur brandy.

Reduce to a stiff consistence one-half pint of cream withthree tablespoonfuls of Bechamel sauce; add some truffle cook-ing-liquor and the necessary quantity of cream; complete withtwo oz. of best butter; mix the truffles with this sauce, and servein a vol-au-vent crust.

TRUFFES à la SERVIETTE

Under this head are served “Truffes au Champagne,” therecipe for which is given above, but the champagne should bereplaced by Madeira.

Dish them in a timbale, set in a napkin folded to representan artichoke. But it would be very much more reasonableto serve “Truffes h la cendre” under this head, serving themunder a folded napkin, as for “Pommes de terre en robe dechambre” (potatoes in their skins).

TIMBALE de TRUFFES

Line a buttered timbale mould with ordinary patty paste.

Garnish its bottom and sides with slices of bacon, and fill

up the mould with raw, peeled truffles, seasoned with salt andpepper.

Add a glassful of Madeira, two tablespoonfuls of palechicken or veal glaze; cover with a slice of bacon, and close upthe timbale, in the usual way, with a layer of paste.

Gild with beaten eggs, and bake in a hot oven for fiftyminutes. When about to serve, turn out and dish on a napkin.

Farinaceous Products

GNOCHI AU GRATIN

Prepare a “pate k choux” after recipe No. 2374, from thefollowing ingredients:—one pint of milk, a pinch of salt, anda little nutmeg, four oz. of butter, two-thirds lb. of flour, andsix eggs. When the paste is ready, combine with it four oz.of grated Parmesan. Divide this paste into portions the size ofwalnuts; drop them into boiling, salted water, and poach them.

As soon as the gnochi rise to the surface of the water, andseem resilient to the touch, drain them on a piece of linen.

Coat the bottom of a gratin-dish with Mornay sauce; set thegnochi upon the latter; cover them with the same sauce;sprinkle with grated cheese and melted butter, and set thegratin to form in a moderate oven for from fifteen to twentyminutes.

GNOCHI à la ROMAINE

Scatter two-thirds lb. of semolina over a quart of boilingmilk. Season with salt, pepper, and nutmeg, and cook gentlyfor twenty minutes. Take the utensil off the fire; thicken thesemolina with the yolks of two eggs, and spread it on a moist-ened tray, in a layer one-half in. thick.

When it is quite cold stamp it out with a round cutter,two in. in diameter. Set the gnochi in shallow, buttered tim-bales; sprinkle with grated Gruy^re and Parmesan, and witha little melted butter, and set the gratin to form.

GNOCHI de POMMES de TERRE

Cook two lbs. of potatoes in the English way. Drain themas soon as they are cooked, and work the pur£e, while it is veryhot, with one and one-half oz. of butter, two small eggs, twoegg-yolks, one-third lb. of flour, salt, pepper, and nutmeg.Divide up this preparation into portions the size of walnuts; rollthem into balls; press upon them lightly with a fork to givethem a criss-cross pattern, and poach them in boiling water.

Drain them on a piece of linen; dish them in layers, sprink-

ling some grated cheese between each layer; sprinklesome grated cheese over the top surface; bedew liberally withmelted butter, and set the gratin to form in a hot oven.

NOQUES AU PARMESANPut into a previously-heated basin one-half lb. of vianiedbutter, and work the latter with salt, pepper, and nutmeg;adding to it, little by little, two eggs and two well-beaten egg-yolks, five oz. of flour, and the white of an egg, also beatento a stiff froth.

Divide up the preparation into portions the size of hazel-nuts; drop these portions into a saut^pan of boiling, saltedwater, and let them poach.

Drain the noques on a piece of linen; dish them in a tim-bale; sprinkle them copiously with grated cheese and withnut-brown butter.

MACARONI

Under this head are included all tubular pastes from Spag-hetti, the size of which is not larger than thick vermicelli, tocanneloni, the bore of which is one-half in. in diameter.

All these pastes are cooked in boiling water, salted to theextent of one-third oz. per quart. Macaroni, like other pastes ofa similar nature, should not be cooled.

The most one can do, if the cooking has to be stopped at agiven moment, is to pour a little cold water into the saucepanand then to take it off the fire.

MACARONI A d’lTALIENNECook the macaroni in boiling water; completely drain it; putit into a saut^pan, and toss it over the fire to dry.

Season it with salt, pepper and nutmeg; cohere it with fiveoz. of grated Gruyere and Parmesan, in equal quantities, andtwo oz. of butter, cut into small pieces, per lb. of macaroni.Saute the whole well to ensure the leason, and dish in a timbale.

MACARONI AU GRATINPrepare the macaroni after No. 2285, adding to it a littleBechamel sauce; and set it on a buttered gratin-dish, be-sprinkled with grated cheese. Sprinkle the surface of the pre-paration with grated cheese and raspings, mixed, and withmelted butter, and set the gratin to form in a fierce oven.

MACARONI AU JUSParboil the macaroni in salted water, keeping it somewhatfirm; drain it, cut it into short lengths, and simmer it in beef

x x

braising-liquor, until the macaroni has almost entirely absorbedthe latter.

Dish in a timbale, and sprinkle with a few tablespoonfulsof the same liquor.

MACARONI à la NANTUA

Having cooked, drained and dried the macaroni, cohere itwith crayfish cream, and mix therewith twenty-four crayfishes’tails per lb. of macaroni.

Dish in a timbale, and cover the macaroni with a julienne ofvery black truffles.

MACARONI à la NAPOLITAINE

Prepare a beef estouffade with red wine and tomatoes; cookit for from ten to twelve hours, that it may be reduced to apur£e.

Rub this estouffade through a sieve and put it aside.

Parboil some thick macaroni, keeping it somewhat firm;drain it; cut it into short lengths, and cohere it with butter.

Sprinkle the bottom of a timbale with grated cheese; coverwith a layer of estouffade pur£e; spread a layer of macaroniupon the latter, and proceed in the same order until the timbaleis full. Serve the preparation as it stands.

MACARONI aux TRUFFES BLANCHES

Prepare the macaroni as directed under No. 2285, and addto it six oz. of white Piedmont truffles (cut into thin shavings),per lb. of macaroni.

Leave the preparation covered for five minutes and dish in atimbale.

NOODLES (Nouilles)

These are generally bought ready-made. If one wish toprepare them oneself, the constituents of the paste are:—onelb. of flour, one-half oz. of salt, three whole eggs, and five egg-yolks. Moisten as for an ordinary paste, roll it out twice on aboard, and leave it to stand for one or two hours before cuttingit up.

All macaroni recipes may be applied to noodles.

For “Nouilles & l’Alsacienne,” it is usual, when the prepara-tion is ready in the timbale, to distribute over it a few rawnoodles sauted in butter and kept very crisp.

Kache

Kache is not a vegetable; but since this preparation hasappeared either as a constituent or an accompaniment of certain

Russian dishes which occur in this work, I am obliged to referto it.

KACHE de SEMOULE POUR COULIBIAC

Take some coarse, yellow semolina, and scatter it over threetimes its bulk of boiling consomm£. Cook it gently for twenty-five minutes; drain it on a sieve; spread it on a tray, and placeit in a moderate oven to dry. This done, rub it lightly througha coarse sieve with the view of separating the grains, and put itaside in the dry until wanted.

KACHE de SARRASIN POUR POT AGES

Moisten one lb. of concassed, buckwheat with enough tepidwater to make a stiff paste; add the necessary salt, and put thispaste in a large Charlotte-mould. Bake in a hot oven for twohours. Then remove the thick crust which has formed uponthe preparation, and transfer what remains, by means of a spoon,to a basin. Mix therewith two oz. of butter while it is stillhot.

Kache prepared in this way may be served in a special tim-bale. But it is more often spread in a thin layer on a butteredtray, and left to cool.

It is then cut into roundels one in. in diameter, and these arerolled in flour and coloured on both sides in very hot, clarifiedbutter.

POLENTA

In a quart of boiling water containing one-half oz. of salt,immerse two-thirds lb. of maize flour, stirring the while witha spoon, that the two may mix. Cook for twenty-five minutes;add two oz. of butter and two and one-half oz. of grated Par-mesan. If the Polenta be prepared for a vegetable or a gar-nish, it is spread in a thin layer on a moistened tray. Whencold, it is cut into roundels or lozenges, which are first brownedin butter, dished, and then sprinkled with grated cheese andnut-brown butter.

SOUFFLE PIEMONTAIS

Boil one pint of milk with one-fifth oz. of salt; sprinkle on ittwo oz. of maize flour; mix well; cover, and cook in a mildoven for twenty-five minutes.

Then transfer the paste to another saucepan; work it withone and one-half oz. of butter and as much grated Parmesan;mix therewith one egg, two egg-yolks, and the whites of threeeggs beaten to a stiff froth.

Dish in a buttered timbale; sprinkle with grated cheese, andcook like an ordinary souffle.

X X 2

676 GUIDE TO MODERN COOKERY

a—SOUFFLE AU PARMESAN

Mix one lb. of flour and two and one-half pints of milk ina saucepan. Add a little salt, pepper and nutmeg, and set thepreparation to boil, stirring it constantly the while.

As soon as the boil is reached, take the saucepan off thefire, and add one lb. of grated Parmesan, three oz. of butter,and ten egg-yolks. Rub the whole through tammy and thencombine with it the whites of ten eggs whisked to a stiff froth.

Mould in a silver timbale, lined with a band of butteredpaper, and bake in the oven for from twenty to twenty-fiveminutes.

RAVIOLI

Whatever be their garnish, ravioli are always prepared in thesame way. The stuffings given below represent the most usualforms of garnish.

STUFFING A

Mix one-half lb. of finely-chopped, cooked chicken-meat;five oz. of cooked and crushed brains; three oz. of pressedwhite cheese; three oz. of chopped, pressed and blanchedspinach; three oz. of parboiled green borage; a pinch of greensweet basil; five oz. of grated Parmesan; two eggs; two egg-yolks; salt, pepper and nutmeg.

STUFFING B

Mix two-thirds lb. of well-cooked, cold and finely-choppeddaube of beef; two-thirds lb. of parboiled, pressed, and choppedspinach; one oz. of chopped shallots; five oz. of a pur6e ofcooked brain; two whole eggs, salt, pepper and nutmeg.

STUFFING C

Toss one-half lb. of chickens’ livers in butter; add to ittwo chopped shallots, a pinch of parsley, and a little crushedgarlic. Finely pound the livers, and add successively one-half lb. of parboiled, cooled and fresh spinach; two anchovyfillets; three oz. of butter; three eggs, salt, pepper, nutmeg, anda pinch of sweet basil. Rub the whole through a sieve.

THE PREPARATION OF RAVIOLI

They may be made in various shapes as follows: —

(1) Roll a piece of noodle paste to a thin layer and stamp itout with a grooved cutter, two and one-half in. in diameter.Moisten the edges of each roundel of paste; garnish the centre

VEGETABLES AND FARINACEOUS PRODUCTS 677

of each with a ball of one of the above stuffings, the size of ahazel-nut, and fold in slipper-form.

(2) Roll the paste into a rectangle of four-in. sides; garnishwith stuffing, leaving a gap between the portions of the latter;moisten the edges of the paste, and close up by drawing thesetogether. Finally stamp out with a grooved, crescent-shapedfancy-cutter.

(3) Prepare a square layer of paste; garnish it with lines con-sisting of portions of paste; leave a space of two in. between thelines. Moisten; cover with a second layer of paste, of thesame dimensions as the first, and divide up, by means of theroulette, into squares of two-in. sides. Whatever be the shapeof the ravioli, plunge them into a saucepan of slightly saltedboiling water; poach them for from eight to ten minutes, anddrain them.

Set them on a buttered gratin-dish, sprinkled with gratedcheese; sprinkle them with good beef gravy; then again withgrated cheese, and set the gratin to form. Or, dish the ravioliin layers, sprinkling each layer with grated cheese and gravy.Complete with some grated cheese, and set the gratin to formin the usual way.

N.B.—The ravioli may also be served, merely sprinkled withgrated cheese and nut-brown butter.

Chapter XVII Savouries

Remaks upon Savouries

I have already expressed my opinion in regard to Savouries. I consider their use opposed to gastronomical principles, and that they have no raison d’être on a good menu. But, not wishing to seem didactic, I shall give, hereafter, a few savoury recipes, selected from among those which are gastronomically the best, and which custom has sanctified.

I resolved to make these recipes appear after the Vegetables and before the Ices, because I deem that Dessert alone is ad- missible after the Entremets and Ices.

There is much in common between Hors-d’œuvres and Savouries. Many of the former, the recipes for which I have given, may appear as Savouries, once their seasoning has been intensified. Among the latter class may be quoted the various Tartlets (№387, &c.); the Barquettes (№314); Frivolities (№350); Éclairs à la Karoly (№344); Allumettes aux Anchois (№300); City Toasts (№320), &c.

Allumettes

Prepare a ribbon of puff-paste three inches wide by one-fifth inch thick, leaving the length to come as it will. Spread on it some very reduced Béchamel sauce, combined with two tablespoonfuls of grated Gruyère cheese per one-half pint, and season with cayenne. Sprinkle the surface with grated Parmesan press the latter into the sauce by means of the flat; of a knife; cut into rectangles one inch wide; set these on a slightly-moistened tray, and bake them in a moderate oven for twelve minutes.

Beignets Soufflés with Cheese

Prepare some ordinary “pâte à choux” without sugar (№2375), and combine it, per lb., with five oz. of a Brunoise of Gruyère.

Divide up this paste into portions the size of hazel-nut, and fry them in fat like other Beignets soufflés.

Beurrecks à la Turque

Reduce the required amount of Béchamel sauce to a thick consistence; mix it with an equal quantity of Gruyère dice season with cayenne, and spread the preparation on a dish to cool.

Then divide it up into portions the size of fine walnuts; shape these like cigars, wrap each portion in a very thin layer of noodle paste; treat them a l’anglaise, and fry them at the last moment in very hot fat.

Choux au Fromage

By means of a piping-bag, form some “choux”, a little larger than the Saint-Honoré ones, from ordinary paste (see №2375). Gild them with beaten eggs; bake them in a moderate oven, and keep them dry. When cold, cut them at the top; garnish them with “Fondue au fromage” seasoned with cayenne, and complete with some Chantilly cream, combined with grated Parmesan; this should be laid on by means of a piping-bag, as in the case of “choux à la crème”.

Camembert Frit

Clear the cheese of its crust, and cut it into elongated lozenges. Sprinkle the latter with cayenne, treat them twice à l’anglaise, and fry them at the last moment in hot fat.

Canapés or Toast

These are nothing more than pieces of toast, i.e., slices of bread, trimmed according to fancy, grilled, buttered, and garnished in some way.

As the garnishes for toast are innumerable, I shall quote only a few typical examples.

Canapés Garnished with Scrambled Eggs.—Set the scrambled eggs in domes upon the Canapés; sprinkle with grated Parmesan, and set to glaze quickly.

Or arrange the scrambled eggs as above, and cover them with a lattice of anchovy fillets.

Canapés de Haddock.—Cook the haddock; rub it through a sieve; add a little butter and Bechamel sauce to the resulting purée, and set the latter in domes on the toast.

For Variety.—Sprinkle the purée with grated Parmesan, and set to glaze.

Or garnish the purée with oysters poached in a little Worcestershire sauce.

Or again: cover the pur´e with a lattice of anchovy fillets.

Canapés with Kippers or Bloaters.—Grill them and make a purée from them like the haddock.

Canapés with Halved or Filleted Anchovies.—In the case of fillets, set them to form a grill upon the toast; if the anchovies be halved, lay them lengthwise on the toast.

Canapés with Sardines in Oil.—Clear the fish of their skins and bones, and set the fillets on the canapés.

Canapés with Grilled Sprats.—Proceed as for sardines.

Canapés of Salmon.—Toast may be garnished with thin slices of smoked or fresh salmon, or with the latter prepared in a purée like the haddock.

Various Canapes.—Once the pieces of toast or canapes are grilled and buttered, they may be garnished with chopped smoked tongue or ham, cohered with a little butter and mustard, with grilled slices of mushrooms or tomatoes, &c.

A few of the preparations have names, while others are only distinguished by the nature of their garnish.

Canapés à la Cadogan

Take oval and slightly hollowed pieces of toast, fried in butter and garnished with spinach prepared with butter. Lay two oysters on the spinach of each piece of toast; cover with Mornay sauce, and glaze quickly.

Canapés des Gourmets

Prepare some very thin pieces of toast; fry them in butter, and garnish them with a cheese fondue. Pair them off, and sandwich a piece of grilled bacon between each pair.

Canapés Ivanhoe

Take some round, buttered pieces of toast, garnished with haddock purée, and set a very small, grilled mushroom on the purée of each piece of toast.

Canapés à l’Écossaise

Take some round, buttered pieces of toast, garnished with haddock purée, and glazed.

N.B.—I see no use in extending this list any further; the above directions should suffice to show the variety to which these preparations lend themselves.

Carcasse de Volaille (Chicken Carcasses)

Take in preference the carcasses of fowls cooked without colouration.

After having trimmed them, coat them with mustard and cayenne, and grill them.

Champignons sous Cloche

Trim the mushrooms; season them with salt and pepper, and garnish the hollow of ?ach with a piece of Maître-d’hôtel butter, the size of a hazel-nut, and one-half coffeespoonful of cream.

Set a mushroom on each piece of toast, which should be two inches in diameter and fried in butter. Dish them on an egg-tray, and cover them with a special, small, glass bell, four inches in diameter and two inches high, the rim of which must rest on the bottom of a dish, the diameter of which should be such as to fit the bell.

Put the dishes on the side of the stove, and cook in moderate heat for about twenty-five minutes.

Condés au Fromage

Prepare a ribbon from puff-paste trimmings, as in the case of №2299.

Spread thereon a thick layer of very reduced Béchamel sauce, flavoured with cayenne, and combined, when cold, with very small dice of Gruyère and Parmesan. Cut up and cook as for №2299.

Crème Frite au Fromage

Mix together four oz. of flour, two and one-half oz. of rice cream, three eggs, and two egg-yolks. Dilute with one pint of milk; season with salt, cayenne, and nutmeg; boil, and cook for five minutes over an open fire, stirring incessantly the while.

Add four oz. of grated Gruyère; spread this preparation on a buttered tray; leave it to cool, and then cut it into elongated lozenges. Roll the latter in beaten egg and bread-crumbs mixed with grated cheese, and fry them at the last moment. Dish them on a napkin.

Croquettes de Camembert

Dilute two oz. of flour and two oz. of rice cream with one- third pint of milk.

Add one lb. of cleaned camembert, cut into dice, five oz. of butter, salt, cayenne, and nutmeg.

Délices de Foie Gras

Take some fresh, well-seasoned foie gras, studded with truffles, and covered with slices of bacon, and poach it in a basin with good aspic jelly flavoured with dry champagne or Rhine wine. Leave to cool for twenty-four hours; clear the jelly of grease, first by means of a spoon, and then with boiling water.

Serve the preparation as it stands, very cold, and accompany it with grilled, crisp, and very hot slices of bread-crumb.

Diablotins

These are very small, poached Gnochi, sprinkled with grated cheese, flavoured with a very little cayenne, and set for their gratin to form at the last moment.

Fondants au Chester

Moisten one-half lb. of flour, an equal quantity of butter and grated cheese, a pinch of salt, and a very little cayenne, with a few tablespoonfuls of water.

Cut the paste into small galettes, two inches in diameter; gild them with beaten eggs; streak them with a fork, and bake them in a moderate oven.

When cold, pair the galettes off, and stick them together with a tablespoonful of fondant cream, prepared thus:—

Mix six egg-yolks with two-thirds pint of cream; season with salt and cayenne; leave to set on moderate fire, like an English custard, and, when the preparation is almost cold, finish it with five oz. of best butter and as much grated cheese.

Anges à Cheval

Wrap some fine oysters, each in a thin slice of bacon. Impale them on a skewer; season and grill them, and dish them on small pieces of toast.

Sprinkle with bread-crumbs and cayenne when about to serve.

Brochettes d’huîtres Lucifer

Poach some fine native oysters in their own liquor; clear them of their beards; dry them, and dip them in thin mustard. Impale them, six at a time, on skewers, and treat them a l’anglaise.

Fry them at the last moment, and dish them on a napkin.

Omelette à l’Écossaise

Take some fresh herring milts; salt them; sprinkle them with cayenne and chopped chives, parsley, and chervil; wrap each in a thin slice of smoked salmon, and poach them gently in butter.

Set them aslant in the centre of an “omelette aux fines herbes”; cover them well with the latter, and roll it up.

Omelette aux Fines Herbes

See №502.

Grilled Bones

Take the trimmed bones of a roast sirloin, and let there be still some meat upon them. Sprinkle them with cayenne; coat them with mustard, and grill them.

Paillettes au Parmesan

Prepare some puff-paste with two-thirds lb. of butter; roll it out ten times, dusting it and the table well the while with grated Parmesan and a little cayenne, that the paste may absorb as much as possible of these. Then roll it into square layers of four-inch sides and one-eighth inch thick; cut these up into ribbons one-eighth inch wide; set them on buttered trays; bake them in a very hot oven, and serve them on a napkin.

Pannequets à la Moscovite

Take some ordinary, unsugared Pannequets; cut them into rectangles three inches long by one and one-half inches wide.) Coat them with caviare, flavoured with cayenne; roll them into cigarettes, and serve them on crystal hors-d’œuvre dishes.

Pudding de Fromage au Pain

Set some thin slices of stale, buttered and cheese-sprinkled bread in a pie-dish. Having three-parts filled the dish with it, cover the slices with a preparation consisting of the yolks of four eggs mixed with one-quarter pint of broth—which quantities are suited to a pint dish.

Sprinkle copiously with grated cheese; bake in the oven, and glaze at the last moment.

Pannequets à la Moscovite

Take fresh sardines, if possible. Skin and bone them; coat them with mustard and cayenne; treat them à l’anglaise; fry them at the last moment, and dish them on small fried croutons, the shape of sardines.

N.B.—Fresh anchovies and smelts may be prepared in the same way.

Scotch Woodcock

Toast some large slices of bread, one-third inch thick, and cover them with a very thick English butter sauce, combined with plenty of capers and anchovy purée.

Sprinkle with grated Parmesan glaze quickly at the salamander; speedily cut up into small rectangles, and serve very hot.

Tartelettes Agnès

Line some grooved tartlet moulds with good paste, and garnish them with a preparation of Quiche with cheese, flavoured with cayenne. Cook them at the last moment, and, on taking them out of the oven, set a roundel of poached marrow rolled in pale melted meat glaze and chopped parsley on each tartlet.

Tartelettes à l’Ecossaise

Take some tartlet crusts, baked without colouration, and garnish them at the last moment with a haddock purée, cohered with Béchamel sauce.

Tartelettes de Haddock

Garnish some colourlessly-baked tartlet crusts with a salpicon of poached haddock, mixed with curry sauce. Sprinkle the surface of each with fine raspings, and dish them on a napkin.

Tartelettes à la Florentine

Garnish some colourlessly-baked tartlet crusts with Soufflé with Parmesan, combined with grated truffles and crayfishes’ tails cut into dice, and strongly seasoned with mignonette.

Bake in the oven for about three minutes.

Tartelettes Marquise

Line some tartlets with good paste garnish their bottom and; sides with a thread of gnochis preparation, laid by means of a piping-bag fitted with an even pipe, the orifice of which should be equal in diameter to macaroni.

Fill up the tartlets with Mornay sauce flavoured with cayenne; sprinkle with grated cheese, and bake in a fierce oven.

Tartelettes à la Raglan

Garnish the bottom of some colourlessly-baked tartlets with a smoked herring-milt purée. Cover the latter with haddock soufflé, shaped like a hive by means of a piping-bag fitted with a small, grooved pipe. Place in the oven for six minutes, and serve instantly.

Tartelettes à la Tosca

Garnish some tartlet crusts with crayfishes’ tails, prepared “à l’Américaine”. Cover with Soufflé with Parmesan, and place in the oven for three minutes.

Tartelettes à la Vendome

Line some tartlet moulds with good paste; prick the bottom of each, and garnish them with the following preparation.

For twelve tartlets:—One and one-half oz. of chopped shallots, heated in butter; three oz. of sauted and finely chopped cèpes; one and one-half oz. of raw marrow in dice; one small hard-boiled and chopped egg; one oz. of bread-crumbs, salt, cayenne, a few drops of lemon juice, and three tablespoonfuls of melted meat glaze. Set a large slice of marrow on each tartlet, and cook at the last moment.

Welsh Rabbit

This may be prepared in two ways, but always on square or rectangular pieces of buttered toast, one-third inch thick.

The simplest way is to cover the pieces of toast with a thick layer of grated Gloucester or Chester cheese, to sprinkle them with cayenne, and then to place them in the oven for the cheese to melt and thereby glaze their surfaces.
The original method consists in melting the dice or slices of cheese in a few tablespoonfuls of pale ale and a little English mustard.

As soon as the cheese has melted, it is poured over the pieces of buttered toast, quickly smoothed with the flat of a knife, and sprinkled with cayenne. The pieces may be cut up if required.

Sandwiches

Sandwiches are prepared in two ways, according to their purposes.

They generally consist of two slices of buttered bread, with mustard spread upon them, covering a slice of ham or tongue, &c. Sandwiches are usually rectangular, and they should measureaboutthreeinchesbyoneandone-halfinches. The kind served at ball buffets are much smaller, and therefore it is best to cut the sandwiched product (whatever this be) into dice, and to mix it with an equal weight of butter containing mustard.

When sandwiches have to be kept, they should be placed under a slight weight to prevent the bread from drying. Sand- wiches may also be made from thick, toasted slices of bread, cut laterally into two, and then garnished according to fancy.

Names of common sandwiches:

Ham Sandwich
Tongue Sandwich
Beef Sandwich
Pressed-beef Sandwich
Veal Sandwich
Chicken Sandwich
Foie-Gras Sandwich
Hard-boiled Egg Sandwich
Caviare Sandwich
Tomato Sandwich
Cucumber Sandwich
Watercress Sandwich
Mustard-and-cress Sandwich

Bookmaker Sandwiches

In his book, “La Cuisine Anglaise”, Mr Suzanne gives the following kind of sandwich, which deserves attention:—

This kind of sandwich, which is liked by racing people, is a most substantial affair, and it will be seen from the following recipe that a sandwich of the nature prescribed might, in an emergency, answer the purpose of a meal.

Take an English tin-loaf, and cut off its two end crusts, leaving on them about one-third inch of crumb. Butter these crusts. Meanwhile grill a thick steak, well seasoned with salt and pepper. When it is cooked, cool it; sprinkle it with grated horse-radish and mustard, and lay it between the two crusts. String the whole together as for a galantine, and wrap it in several sheets of blotting-paper. Then place the parcel under a letter-press, the screw of which should be gradually tightened, and leave the sandwich thus for one-half hour.

Chapter XX Entremets (Sweets)

Pastry, Confectionery, and Ices are so closely allied toCookery, and they are so surely its complements, that it isimpossible to omit them when dealing with Entremets, eventhough the latter be limited to the kind proper to the kitchen.

However, these subjects, which could supply matter forvoluminous works, are too complex for it to be possible to copethoroughly with them here.

I shall therefore confine myself to the expounding of theirfundamental principles and the essential operations relatingthereto, a knowledge of which is absolutely necessary for thesuccessful preparation of Kitchen Entremets and Ices. Thedirections given hereafter are certainly too inadequate to con-vert an ordinary cook into a pastry-cook, a confectioner, or a“glacier”; but they will at least admit of his carrying out acomplete dinner, if the necessity so to do should occur.

Elementary Preparations of Pastry which may be Applied

to Entremets

VARIOUS ALMOND PREPARATIONS

It is important that one should have skinned, splintered, and chopped almonds.

To Skin Almonds.—Throw them in a saucepan of boilingwater, place the utensil on the side of the fire without allowingthe boiling to continue, and let the almonds soak for sevenor eight minutes. As soon as the skin slips when pressingthem between one’s fingers, turn them out on to a strainer; coolthem in cold water, and skin them. This done, wash them incold water; drain them well; spread them on a very cleantray, and dry them in a mild oven.

Splintered Almonds.—Having skinned and washed thealmonds, split them in two, and cut each half into five orsix splinters. Dry the latter in the drying-box, and placethem in the front of the oven for a while to colour slightly.

They serve for nougat, and sometimes take the place ofpignolis.

Chopped Almonds.—Having skinned the almonds, slightlydry them and chop them with a knife; rub them through acanvas sieve, the coarseness of which should be in accordancewith that required for the chopped almonds.

Spread the latter on a tray covered with a sheet of paper, and dry them in the drying-box, stirring them from time totime the while.

Grilled Almonds.—These are either splintered or choppedalmonds set to bake on a tray in a moderate oven. Be sureto stir them frequently, that they may colour evenly, and with-draw them when they are of a nice golden shade.

Pralined Almonds.—Proceed as for grilled almonds, butsprinkle them frequently with icing sugar, which turns tocaramel under the influence of the heat of the oven, and swathesthe almonds in a pale-brown coat of sugar.

VARIOUS PREPARATIONS of FILBERTSAND HAZEL-NUTS

Filberts are a large kind of hazel-nut, generally coveredwith red skins.

After having cracked and suppressed the shells, set the fil-berts on a dish, and place them in the front of the oven untiltheir skins are slightly grilled. They need then only be rubbedbetween the fingers in order to clear them of their skins.Chopped filberts are prepared like chopped almonds, and shouldbe included in the permanent “mise en place” of the pastrycook.

VARIOUS BUTTERS

Softened Butter.—More particularly in winter, when it isvery hard, butter should be softened, i.e., thoroughly kneadedin a towel, to: —

1. Extract the butter-milk, which is always present in moreor less large quantities.

2. Make it sufficiently soft to mix with the various in-gredients of which the pastes are made up.

Pomaded Butter.—After having well softened it as above, put it in a bowl or basin, previously rinsed with hot waterand thoroughly wiped. Work the butter with a spatula or awooden spoon until it acquires the consistence of a pomade—a necessary condition for certain of its uses.

Clarified Butter.—In pastry, clarified butter is used moreespecially for the buttering of moulds. Put the butter to beclarified into a saucepan, and cook it over a very slow fire until

(1) the caseous substances liberated in the cooking process haveaccumulated and solidified on the bottom of the saucepan; (2) itappears limpid, of a golden colour, and exhales a slight, nuttysmell.

Strain it through muslin, and put it aside until required.

The Buttering and Glazing of Moulds

All moulds, large and small, should be buttered so as toensure the easy turning-out of cakes cooked in them. Clarified butter, owing to its purity, is the best for the purpose. It maybe applied with a brush, care being taken that all the insidesurfaces get uniformly covered with it. One unbuttered spotis sufficient to make a moulding stick, or to completely spoil acake.

For certain cakes, chopped or splintered almonds aresprinkled in the mould. For others, especially biscuits, themoulds are flour-dusted—that is to say, a veil of very dry flouror fecula is allowed to settle on the layer of butter, which, atthe turning out, appears like a glazed crust upon the cake.

HOW TO BEAT THE WHITES of EGGS

The best utensil for the purpose is a copper or nickel basinin which the whisk may act at all points owing to the sphericalshape of the receptacle. Tinned or enamelled utensils set upa kind of greasiness which does not allow of one’s bringing thewhites to the stiffness necessary for some purposes.

Begin whisking the whites gently, and draw them up withthe whisk until all their molecules have disaggregated and theybegin to stiffen. They may then be whisked until they aresufficiently stiff to be taken up bodily by the whisk.

Preventive Means.—To facilitate the beating of whites ofeggs, there may be added to them at the start a pinch eitherof salt or alum per ten whites. When, towards the close of theoperation, the whites begin to granulate, owing to any one ofthe various causes, add immediately one tablespoonful ofpowdered sugar per ten whites, and then whisk briskly, torestore them to their normal state.

Vegetable Colouring Matters

Every pastry-cook’s stock should include a series of vegetable colouring matters, comprising carmine, liquid spinach green, yellow, &c.amp;c.

When required, the blending of these colours yields theintermediate tones. The colours may be bought.

Y V

690 GUIDE TO MODERN COOKERY

The Cooking of Sugar

From the state of syrup to the most highly-concentratedstate in which it is used in pastry sugar passes through variousstages of cooking, which are:—The small thread (2150 F.) andthe large thread (2220 F.), the small ball (236°F.) and the largeball (248°F.), the small crack (285°F.) and the large crack(3150 E*)* When the last state is overreached, the sugar hasbecome caramel (360°F.).

Put the necessary quantity of loaf sugar in a small, coppersaucepan; moisten with enough water to melt it, and boil.Carefully remove the scum which forms, and which might causethe sugar to granulate.

As soon as the sugar begins to move stiffly in boiling, itis a sign that the water has almost entirely evaporated, and thatthe real cooking of the sugar has begun.

From this moment, with moistened fingers or a little pieceof moistened linen, take care to remove the crystallised sugarfrom the sides of the utensil, lest it makes the remaining portionturn.

The cooking of the sugar then progresses very rapidly, andthe states of its various stages, coming one upon the other inquick succession at intervals of a few minutes, may be ascer-tained as follows: —

It has reached the small-thread stage, when a drop of it heldbetween the thumb and the first finger forms small resistlessstrings when the thumb and finger are drawn apart.

It has reached the large-thread stage, when, proceeding inthe same way, the strings formed between the parted finger andthumb are more numerous and stronger.

From this moment recourse must be had to cold water inorder to ascertain the states of the sugar.

When a few minutes have elapsed after the test for the large-thread state, dip the end of the first finger, first into coldwater, then into the sugar, and plunge it again immediatelyinto the bowl of cold water, which should be ready at hand.The sugar taken from the finger forms a kind of soft ball, andit is this state which is called the small ball.

When, upon repeating the procedure, the sugar removedfrom the finger rolls into a firmer ball, the large-ball stage isreached.

After the cooking has continued for a few seconds longer, the sugar lying on the finger peels off in the form of a thin, flexible film, which sticks to the teeth. This is the small-crackstage. Tests should then be made in quick succession, until

the film taken from the end of the finger breaks “clean” inthe teeth, like glass. This is the large-crack state, the last ofthe cooking stages, and as soon as it has been reached theutensil should be taken off the fire, lest a few seconds moreturn the sugar to caramel.

To prevent the granulating of the sugar, a few drops oflemon juice may be added to it; or, better still, a tablespoonfulof glucose per lb.

GLACE à l’ANCIENNEPut the required amount of icing sugar in a small saucepan, the quantity used being in proportion to the object to be glazed.

If it be flavoured with vanilla, orange^ or lemon, dilute itwith a little water, keeping it somewhat stiff; add some vanilla-flavoured sugar or grated orange-rind, and stir it up well fora few minutes. Then make it lukewarm, so that it may runeasily and dry quickly, and pour it over the object to be treated.

For the above-mentioned flavours, an infusion of vanillaor orange-rind may be prepared, and this may serve in dilutingthe glaze. The flavours may also be used in the form ofessences, provided it be remembered that they are usually verystrong thus, and must be used with caution.

If liqueur glazes are in question, such as Kirsch, Rum, Anisette, or Marasquin, &c.amp;c., the glaze is diluted with the liqueurand made lukewarm as directed above.

GLACE au FONDANTPreparation of the “Fondant.”—Put some loaf sugar intoa small saucepan, the quantity being in accordance with theamount of “Fondant” required.

Moisten with just enough water to melt the sugar, and setto cook as directed under “The Cooking of Sugar.”

Stop the cooking precisely at 230°F. between the large-thread stage and the small-ball stage, and pour the sugar on amoderately-oiled marble slab. Let it half cool for a fewminutes; then, with a spatula, move it about well in all direc-tions, taking care that no portion of the sugar on the marbleis left untouched by the spatula, for any such portion wouldharden and form lumps in the Fondant.

After ten to fifteen minutes’ work with the spatula, the sugarshould have become a white, slightly granulated paste. Heapthe latter together, and scrape the marble slab with the bladeof a strong knife. Carefully knead this paste (№2357) withthe palm of the hand until it is very thin and smooth, whereuponthe Fondant is ready for use.

Y Y 2

It need now only be heaped in a receptacle, covered with adamp cloth, and kept somewhat dry.

To Glaze with “Fondant—Put the required amount of itinto a saucepan; work it over a slow fire for a while, in orderto soften it, and moisten it, little by little, with water whena dry flavour or an essence is used, or, otherwise, with theselected liqueur

Warm slightly in order to make the glaze very liquid andto ensure its speedy drying, and pour it, at one tilt, over theobject to be glazed.

With the help of some colour, the glaze is generally giventhe tint of the fruit which flavours it.

a—SUCRE EN GLACE (Icing Sugar)

This is sugar strained through a silken drum-sieve. Thesugar strained through this silk has the delicacy of starch.At times it is used instead of Fondant for the glazing ofcakes, but it is mostly used for white and caramel glazings.For this purpose the sugar is held in a tin box, covered witha lid pierced with small holes, called a sugar dredger.

To glaze white is to cover a cake, a fritter, or other objectwith a coat of icing sugar. This operation is effected by shak-ing the sugar dredger over the object to be glazed.

To glaze with caramel is to cover a Souffle, a souffled omelet, fruit fritters, a custard, Pannequets, or other objects with a coatof icing sugar. By placing the sugar-coated object in fierceheat, a few minutes suffice to melt the sugar, which is con-verted into a brilliant covering of caramel.

SUGAR GRAINS

These are used in pastry to border certain cakes, or to sur-round the sugared-paste bases on which cakes are set. For thispurpose the parts to which the sugar is expected to adheremust be besmeared with cooked apricot.

To make them, roughly pound some loaf sugar, and sift thelatter first through a coarse strainer, and then through a finerone, according to the size the sugar grains are required to be.The powder will, of course, fall and leave the grains clean.

COLOURED SUGAR GRAINS

To colour sugar grains, spread them on a piece of paper, and add a drop of liquid vegetable-colouring or a very littlecoloured paste per tablespoonful of sugar. The amount ofcolouring matter may either be lessened or increased, accord-ing to the strength the shade is required to be.

Rub the sugar in the hand to colour it evenly; dry it in a

moderately warm drying-box, and keep it in the dry in well-closed boxes.

VANILLA SUGAR

The vanilla sticks which have served in preparing infusions

still possess some flavour. Reserve them, therefore, for themaking of vanilla sugar.

After having gently dried them in the drying-box, finelypound them with twice their weight of loaf sugar; sift througha silken sieve, and again pound the bits remaining on the silkof the sieve until every particle goes through. Keep the pre-paration in a well-closed box in the dry.

CANDIED FRUIT

These are used in the decoration of certain cakes, and asthe constituent ingredients of others.

They comprise angelica, golden and green chinois, cherries, plums, red and white pears, &c.amp;c.

Candied fruit may be bought ready-prepared.

235*— APPLE JELLY for DECORATING

Quarter, peel, and core the apples (preferably russets), andthrow them, one by one, in a bowl of fresh water to preventtheir getting brown.

Then put them in a copper basin with one and one-half pintsof water per two lbs. of apples, and cook them gently withouttouching them.

This done, pour away their juice, and return it to the basintogether with two lbs. of sugar per quart. Boil; skim withgreat care, that the jelly may be clear, and cook over a fiercefire until the jelly has reached a stage which may be ascertainedthus:—(1) When on taking the skimmer out of the basin, thejelly adhering to it seems to mass itself towards the middleof the skimmer; or:—(2) When the jelly breaks up into largedrops, separated one from the other.

Then take the jelly off the fire; add some carmine to it, drop by drop, until it acquires a rosy hue; strain it againthrough a fine piece of linen, that it may be perfectly limpid, and finally pour it into tin receptacles to cool.

Put aside until wanted.

PRALIW

(1) If it be for the purpose of covering certain cakes, or forforming a glaze on a fruit entremet, prepare it thus:—Put thewhites of two eggs and three tablespoonfuls of icing sugar in asmall basin. Mix and stir briskly with a small, wooden spoon, until the paste becomes somewhat thick. Then, subject to the

purpose for which it is intended, add a more or less largequantity of chopped almonds, according as to whether the pralinbe required thick or slightly liquid for spreading. Cover itwith a piece of white paper, moistened with white of egg, thatit may remain moist if kept for some time.

(2) If it is to be added to a souffle preparation, to a souffledomelet, to a preparation of ice, or to a custard, it is a nougatpowder which is prepared as follows: —

Gently melt one lb. of powdered sugar in a small saucepan, taking care not to let it acquire a deeper shade than old gold.Mix twenty oz. of dried almonds with it; turn the whole outon to the corner of a slightly-oiled marble slab (or on an over-turned saucepan-lid), and leave to cool. When the nougat isquite cold, pound it and rub it through a sieve.

Pound and rub what remains in the sieve until the wholegoes through.

Put the powder in a well-closed box, and place the latter ina dry place.

CURRANTS and SULTANAS

Sultanas and currants should always be at hand, ready andcleaned. To clean them, first dredge them and then rub themin a towel, closed to form a sort of purse. Now, turn them intoa sieve or colander, which shake vigorously, that the flour andthe detached stems may be eliminated; then examine them, one by one, to make sure that no stems remain.

Currants should be examined with very particular care, assmall stones often get in among them.

Put the currants and the sultanas asidef each in a box or adrawer.

ESSENCES and FLAVOURINGS

The various essences used in pastry are bought ready-made.The flavourings Consist of those products treated by infusion, such as vanilla; of grated or infused products, such as lemonand orange rinds; and liqueurs in general.

Fruit juices only become flavours when a liqueur in keepingwith the fruit from which they were extracted has been addedto them.

GILDING PREPARATION

This consists of beaten eggs. Its purpose is to ensure thecolouration of certain cakes, whereon it is smeared by meansot a brush. In some cases this gilding may be combined witha little water, as, for instance, when the heat of the oven is too

69 5

fierce, and cakes are required of a light colour. In some cases, especially in that of small, dry cakes, it consists entirely ofegg-yolks diluted with a few drops of water.

The Pastes

ORDINARY SHORT PASTE

Sift one lb. of flour over the mixing-board; make a hollowin its midst, and put therein one-sixth oz. of salt, one-thirdpint of cold water, and one-half lb. of butter well softened—>especially in winter. Mix the flour gradually with the butter andthe water; mass the whole a moment or two, and knead it (seeNo. 2357) twice. Then roll it up in a ball; wrap it in a pieceof linen that its surface may not dry, and put it aside in thticool.

Remarks: A kneaded paste should be prepared either oneday, or at least a few hours, in advance, in order that it maylose that elasticity which it acquires from the kneading.

Pastes, after they have rested awhile, are much more easilytreated, and bake a much more definite and lighter colour, thanthose that are used as soon as they are prepared.

THE KNEADING of PASTES

The object of kneading paste is to combine the ingredientsof which it is composed thoroughly, and also to smooth it.Proceed as follows :—

When the paste is mixed, roll it into a mass; put it in frontof one; then press it away from one, little by little, between theboard and the palm of the hand. For the paste to be perfectlysmooth, it ought to be treated twice in this way.

FINE, SHORT or FLAWN PASTE (For Fruit Tarts)

Sift one lb. of flour on to the mixing-board, and hollow itout. Put in the hollow one-third oz. of salt, one and one-halfoz. of powdered sugar, an egg, one-fourth pint of cold water, and ten oz. of butter. First, thoroughly mix the butter, theegg, the water, and the seasoning, and then gradually combinethe flour with it.

Knead the paste; press it out twice; roll it into a ball, andwrap it up as before with the view of setting it aside in the coolto rest.

DRESSING PASTE (Pate a Pate)

Take one lb. of sifted flour, four oz. of butter, one egg, one-third oz. of salt, and one-fourth pint of water. Mix as already

directed; knead twice; roll up the paste, and set it in the cool torest. This paste should be kept somewhat firm.

DRESSING PASTE with LARD

Take one lb. of sifted flour, four oz. of lard, one-quarter pintof tepid water, one egg, one-third oz. of salt, and proceedexactly as in the case of №2359.

DUMPLING and PUDDING PASTES

Break up ten oz. of very dry beef suet, and carefully clearit of all little pieces of skin and connective tissue. Chop it upas finely as possible; sift one lb. of flour on to the mixing-board; hollow it out; and put into the hollow one-half oz. ofsalt, one and one-half oz. of sugar, one-third pint of water, andthe chopped suet. Mix up these various ingredients, and, bydegrees, combine the flour with them.

Mass the paste together, without kneading it, and put it asidein the cool until it is wanted.

DRY SUGARED PASTE for VARIOUS PURPOSES

Take one lb. of sifted flour, seven oz. of butter, five oz. ofpowdered sugar, three eggs, and one-half tablespoonful oforange-flower water.

Mix in the usual way, knead it twice; roll it into a ball, andkeep it wrapped up, in the cool, until required.

PASTE for SMALL GUMMED TEA-CAKES

Take one lb. of sifted flour, ten oz. of butter, ten oz. ofsugar, one egg, the yolks of four, and a tablespoonful of orange-flower water.

Mix up gradually; mass the paste together, and roll it outinto a thin layer, twice. Roll it up, and let it rest awhilein the cool before it is used.

GUMMING

In the case of certain small cakes, especially those served attea, it is usual to gum their surfaces in order to make themglossy. For this purpose a thin solution of gum arabic is used, and it is smeared over the cakes as they leave the oven, bymeans of a small brush.

Cakes may also be gummed with a syrup formed from milkand sugar, which mixture may be used instead of gum arabicwith advantage.

GALETTE paste

Hollow out one lb. of sifted flour and put in its midst one-third oz. of salt, two oz. of powdered sugar, one-quarter pint ofwater, and one-half lb. of softened butter.

Mix, taking care to include the flour only by degrees:

thoroughly knead, that the ingredients may be well combined, and mass the paste together without making it too elastic.Leave it to rest in the cool for at least an hour; then roll itout thrice, at intervals of eight minutes, for the reasons givenunder the directions for puff-paste.

PUFF-PASTE

(1) Sift one lb. of flour on to the mixing-board. Make ahollow in it, and put therein one-third oz. of table salt andabout one-half pint of cold water, and mix without kneading.Mass the paste together, and let it rest for twenty minutes, thatit may lose its elasticity, which will be all the more pronouncedfor its having been very much worked. It is to avoid thiselasticity, therefore, that the mixing of puff-paste should beeffected with the smallest amount of kneading possible.

(2) Spread the prepared paste on a flour-dusted board, in theshape of an even galette. Spread thereon one lb. of softenedbutter, without completely covering the paste; draw the edgesof the paste towards the centre, in such wise as to enclose thebutter completely, and to form a square thickness of paste.

(3) Leave to rest for a further ten minutes,, and then beginthe working of the paste; rolling it out to the length of one andone-half feet, and keeping it one in. thick. Fold this layer overthrice, and press upon it with the roller so as to join the super-posed layers. The whole of this operation constitutes one turn.

Begin another turn immediately, turning the paste the re-verse way, and folding it as before. Set it to rest in the cool foreight or ten minutes, and then effect two more turns.

Ten minutes after the two last turns (there should be six inall), the puff-paste is ready to be cut up and used.

Remarks relative to puff-paste: Good puff-paste should bebuttered to the extent of one lb. per one and one-half lbs., i.e., one lb. of butter for every one lb. of flour mixed with one-halfpint of water. The consistence of the paste and the buttershould be exactly the same, if they are to be evenly mixed; thebutter ought therefore to be softened—more particularly inwinter.

In preparing puff-paste, remember to put it in a cool placewhile it is resting; but never directly upon ice; for, though theice would not affect the paste, it might seriously affect the butter.

It would harden it to the extent of preventing its perfectmixture with the mass, and lumps would form. Puff-pasteshould be rolled out very regularly, with the view of thoroughlydistributing the butter throughout the preparation, and thusensuring its uniform rising.

Puff-paste should not be worked too speedily; for, if it be so

worked, it will be found to acquire an elasticity which not onlvmakes it difficult to cut up, but also tends to make it shrink inthe baking.

PUFF-PASTE TRIMMINGS or HALF PUFF-PASTE

These are very useful in pastry work, for tartlets, barquettes, croutons, &c.amp;c. When the puff-paste is cut up, the trimmingsshould therefore be rolled into a ball, and put aside in the cool.Nevertheless they must be used within the space of two days insummer and four days in winter.

ORDINARY BRIOCHE PASTE

(1) Sift one lb. of flour on to the board; take a quarter of it, make a hollow in it, and put therein one-quarter oz. of veryfresh, dry yeast. Mix the yeast and the flour with a little tepidwater, so as to obtain a soft paste which is the leaven. Rollthis paste into a ball; make twyo slits in its top, at right anglesto one another, and place it in a small basin.

Cover the latter, and put it in a somewhat warm place, thatthe leaven may be sure to ferment.

(2) Make a hollow in the remaining flour, and put into it one-quarter oz. of salt, and one and one-half oz. of sugar, togetherwith two tablespoonfuls of milk to melt it, one-third of thewhole amount of the butter to be used, namely, four oz., andfour eggs.

Begin by thoroughly mixing the butter, eggs and seasoning, and then combine the flour therewith, by degrees. When thepaste forms a compact mass, knead and pull it about with thehands, that it may be light. When, at the end of a few minutes, it has acquired a certain resilience, make a hole in the middleof it and add one egg. Mix the latter with the paste; work itafresh, and after an interval of two minutes add one more egg inthe same way. The total number of eggs for the quantitiesof other ingredients given above should be six.

(3) Add the remaining butter (eight oz.) to the paste; theformer being manied and even softened, just sufficiently to makeit of the same consistence as the paste.

Spread it on the latter, and mix the two; kneading smallportions at a time, and combining those portions so as to mixthe two elements completely.

At this stage, overturn the paste and spread the leaven(which should now be equal to twice its original bulk) upon it.

Mix it well as in the case of the butter, without working thepaste.

Finally, put the paste into a basin; cover it, and place it ina temperate room.

For it to have the desired lightness, this paste should fer-ment for from ten to twelve hours. However, at the end of fiveor six hours, the process is arrested by the working of the paste;that is to say, by turning it out upon a flour-dusted board andbeating it with the palm of the hand.

It is then returned to the basin to ferment afresh, for fiveor six hours; and then it is once more beaten just before beingused.

MOUSSELINE BRIOCHE PASTE

Mousseline brioche paste is made from the ordinary kind, combined with a little butter and developed in the mould byfermentation before the baking process—which procedure makesit exceedingly light and delicate.

This paste is used in the preparation of certain timbales forfruit sweets, and it is prepared as follows :—

Take the required amount of ordinary brioche paste, andadd to it, per lb. of paste, two oz. of best butter, softened tothe consistence of an ointment, that it may thoroughly mixwith the paste. Roll the paste into a ball, and put it in aliberally-buttered mould, only filling two-thirds of the latterwith it. The remaining third of the mould gets filled by therising of the paste. Place the mould in a temperate room, untilthe paste has risen to the edges of the mould; besmear the sur-face of the paste with a brush dipped in melted butter, and bakein a moderate oven.

ORDINARY BRIOCHE PASTE (For Rissoles, SmallPatties k la Dauphine, and Various other Preparations)

Quantities: one lb. of flour, seven oz. of butter, four fair-sized eggs, salt, a pinch of powdered sugar; one-third oz. ofvery dry, fresh yeast, and a little tepid milk.

(1) Make the leaven with a quarter of the flour, the yeastand the lukewarm milk, and set it to ferment while the pasteis being prepared.

(2) Prepare the paste as already directed, and keep it fer-menting as before for ten hours, taking care to arrest the processonce.

The work is the same as in the preceding case, in everyparticular, except in regard to the amount of butter, which inthis instance is only half as much; in regard to the amountof sugar, which should only be just sufficient to ensure thecolouring of the paste; and finally in regard to its firmness, which should admit of the paste being worked with a rolling-pin.

SAVARIN PASTE

Quantities: One lb. of flour; twelve oz. of butter; one-halfoz. of very dry, fresh yeast; eight eggs; about one-third pint ofmilk; one-half oz. of salt, and one oz. of sugar.

Procedure: Savarin paste may be prepared in several ways;but the one given below is as simple and expeditious as couldbe desired.

Sift the flour into a basin (or a round wooden bowl, bettersuited to the work); hollow it out; add the yeast, and dissolvethe latter by means of tepid milk, stirring slightly with the tipof the finger.

Add the eggs; mix the whole; work the paste by hand fora few minutes; detach those portions of it which have adheredto the side of the utensil, and add them to the whole.

Distribute the softened butter in small quantities over thepaste. Cover, and place in a temperate room until the paste hasgrown to twice its original bulk. Then add salt; knead thepaste, that it may thoroughly absorb the butter, and pat itbriskly until it is sufficiently elastic to be taken up in one lump

At this stage add the sugar, and work the paste again thatthe former may thoroughly mix with it. The sugar should onlybe added at the close of the operation; for, since it impairs thecohesiveness of the paste, it would render the latter much moredifficult to work were it added at the start.

THE USES of THIS PASTE

If it be for Savarins with syrup, it is customary to sprinklethe previously-buttered moulds with slightly-grilled, choppedor splintered almonds. Take the paste in small quantities at atime, and line the moulds with it to the extent of one-third oftheir height.

The remaining two-thirds of each mould become coveredwhen the paste rises owing to fermentation.

Proceed in the same way for Savarins which are to be keptdry, for fruit crusts or other uses; but then the sprinkling ofthe moulds with almond may be omitted.

PATE A BABA

Quantities: One lb. of flour; one-half lb. of butter; seveneggs; two-thirds oz. of yeast; one-fifth pint of milk; one-thirdoz. of salt; two-thirds oz. of sugar; three oz. of currants andsultanas in equal quantities.

Procedure: Proceed exactly as for Savarin paste, and add thecurrants and sultanas at the last with the sugar. In moulding,

a few pipped Malaga raisins may be laid on the bottom of themoulds. As in the case of the Savarin, the paste should onlyfill one-third of the mould.

ORDINARY PATE A CHOUX

Quantities.—One pint of water; eight oz. of butter; one-thirdoz. of salt; one oz. of sugar; one lb. of sifted flour; sixteen fair-sized eggs, and a tablespoonful of orange-flower water.

Procedure.—Put the water, butter, salt, and sugar in a sauce-pan and boil. When the liquid boils and rises, take the saucepanoff the fire; add the flour, and mix. Return the saucepan to amoderate fire, and stir the paste until it ceases to stick to thespoon, and the butter begins to ooze slightly.

Take the saucepan off the fire; add the eggs, two at a time, taking care to mix each couple thoroughly with the paste beforeinserting the succeeding couple. When all the eggs have beenabsorbed, finish the paste with orange-flower water.

COMMON PATE A CHOUX (For Souffled Fritters,

Gnochi, Potatoes k la Dauphine)

Proceed as directed above, but reduce the quantity of butterto three oz., and the number of eggs to twelve; avoid dryingthis paste overmuch.

RAMEQUINS and GOUGERE PASTE

This is prepared exactly like ordinary “Pate k Choux,”except that: —

1. Milk takes the place of water.

2. The sugar and orange-flower water are omitted.

3. For the quantities given (№2373), eight oz. of freshGruy&re, cut into dice, are added to the paste, after all the eggshave been added to it.

PATE A GENOISE FINE

Put into a copper basin one lb. of powdered sugar andsixteen eggs. Mix the two; place the basin upon hot cindersor on the hob, and whisk its contents until they reach the“ribbon” stage (see remarks below). Then add the selectedaroma (vanilla sugar, orange rind, or liqueur, in the proportionof one tablespoonful of vanilla sugar or orange rind, and oneliqueur-glass of liqueur, to the quantities given above), twelveoz. of sifted flour, and eight oz. of melted butter, the latter beingcarefully poured into the paste without allowing it to bubble.Mix these ingredients with the paste, raising the latter by meansof a spatula that it may not get heavy.

Bake it in buttered and dredged moulds.

Remarks.—A preparation of Biscuit or Gtnoise reaches the

“ribbon” stage when it becomes thick, draws out in ribbon-form, and takes some time to level itself again when a spoon ispulled out of it. This state of the paste is also indicative of itslightness.

ORDINARY GENOISE PASTE for CUTTING UP

Quantities.—One lb. of sugar, twelve eggs, thirteen oz. offlour, eight oz. of butter, and the quantity of flavouring thoughtsufficient.

Proceed exactly as in the preceding recipe, in everythingpertaining to the working of the paste.

This paste is baked in buttered and dredged cases, in whichit is spread in layers one and one-quarter inches thick, that itmay rise to about one and three-quarter inches thick, whilebaking.

LADY’S-FINGER BISCUIT PASTE

Stir one lb. of sugar and sixteen egg-yolks in a basin untilthe preparation has whitened slightly and has reached theribbon stage. Now add a tablespoonful of orange-flower water;mix therewith twelve oz. of sifted flour, followed by sixteenegg-whites, whisked to a stiff froth. Take care to effect themixture by raising and cutting the preparation with the spatula, that the former may be quite light.

To Shape the Biscuits.—Put the paste, little by little, intoa canvas piping-bag, fitted with a pipe of one-half inch bore.Close the bag; lay the biscuits on sheets of strong paper;sprinkle them with powdered sugar, and rid them of any super-fluous sugar by holding the sheets end upwards.

Jerk a few drops of water upon the biscuits by means ofa moistened brush in order to assist the beading of the sugar, and remember that a very moderate oven is the best for theeffecting of this beading.

SAVOY-BISCUIT PASTE

Stir one lb. of sugar and fourteen egg-yolks in a basin untilthe preparation reaches the ribbon stage. Flavour with vanillasugar; add six oz. of very dry, sifted flour mixed with six oz.of fecula, and finally mix therewith the fourteen egg-whites, which should be in a very stiff froth.

Carefully set the preparation in buttered and fecula-dredgedmoulds, filling the latter only two-thirds full, and leaving theremaining third to be covered by the rising of the paste whilebaking.

Bake in a regular, moderate oven.

PATE A BISCUIT MANQUEStir one lb. of sugar with eighteen egg-yolks in a basinuntil the preparation is white and light. Add three table-spoonfuls of rum, thirteen oz. of sifted flour, and ten oz. ofmelted butter, carefully poured away. Mix, raising it withthe spatula in so doing.

Set the preparation in special buttered and dredged moulds, filling the latter only two-thirds full with it. Bake in amoderate oven.

PUNCH BISCUIT PASTEStir one lb. of sugar, twelve egg-yolks, and three eggs in abasin, until the whole becomes frothy. Aromatise with a baretablespoonful of orange sugar, the same amount of lemonsugar, and three tablespoonfuls of best rum, and addtwelve oz. of sifted flour, ten oz. of melted butter, and thewhites of eight eggs whisked to a stiff froth. Mix wffth theusual precautions, that the paste may not be heavy.

Bake the preparation in buttered moulds, in cases or inrings, according to the purpose it is intended for. Use amoderate oven.

ORDINARY MERINGUEWhisk the whites of eight eggs until they are as stiff as it ispossible to make them. Sprinkle them with one lb. of pow-dered sugar, and mix them with the latter carefully, that theymay retain all their lightness.

MERINGUE à l’lTALIENNECook one lb. of sugar to the large-ball stage, and meanwhilewhisk the whites of eight eggs to a stiff froth, so as to havethem ready simultaneously with the sugar.

Pour the cooked sugar into the egg-whites, slowly and with-out a pause, and mix up briskly with the whisk.

MERINGUE à l’lTALIENNE (another recipe)Mix one lb. of very best powdered sugar and the whites ofeight eggs in an untinned copper basin. Place the utensil onhot cinders or on the side of the stove, that the preparation maybe lukewarm while in progress.

Whisk the meringue until it is sufficiently consistent to spanthe members of the whisk. If it is not to be used at once, transfer the paste to a small basin; cover it with a round pieceof paper, and set it in the cool.

ALMOND PASTEInstead of the antiquated and difficult method of makingalmond pastes in the mortar, a crushing machine is now used

which not only yields a much smoother paste, but also greatlysimplifies the work. Almond paste, which consists of almonds, sugar, and egg-whites, in quantities varying in accordance withthe purpose of the paste, is now sold ready-made. It has onlyto be finished with a little sugar, white of egg, and otherthings, subject to the use to which it is to be put.

MELTING ALMOND PASTE (For Stuffing andImitating Fruit)

Pass eight oz. of dry, skinned almonds through the crusherPlace them in the mortar, together with the selected aromaticessence; either a tablespoonful of vanilla sugar or a smallglassful of liqueur; and add to them, little by little, working thewhile with the pestle, one lb. of sugar cooked to the small-crack stage.

With this generic recipe, the melting paste may be variedat will by an increase or decrease in the quantity of sugar.

PISTACHIOS

These should belong to the pastry-cook’s stock, but, as arule, they are only prepared just before being served. To skinthem, proceed as in the case of almonds.

PISTACHIO PASTE for INFUSION

As soon as the pistachios are skinned, washed, and dried, crush them in the mortar to a very smooth paste, which set inboiled milk, to infuse.

As the colour of pistachios is weak, it is strengthened inpreparations containing them with a few drops of vegetablegreen, while its aroma is thrown into relief with a trifle ofvanilla.

MELTING PISTACHIO PASTE

Put seven oz. of pistachios and two oz. of almonds throughthe crusher; both should have been just skinned. Put thepaste into the mortar; add to it two tablespoonfuls of syrup, strongly flavoured with vanilla, followed by eight oz. of sugar, cooked to the small-crack stage, and added to the paste littleby little.

Transfer the paste to a marble slab, and finish it by com-bining three tablespoonfuls of icing sugar with it.

The Preparation and Cooking of Various Pastry Crusts

used in Cookery

VOL-au-VENT CRUST

Prepare the puff-paste as directed under №2366. Makethe layer of paste of an even thickness of four-fifths inch; set

70 5

thereon an overturned plate or a saucepan-lid, the size of whichshould be that intended for the Vol-au-vent, and cut the pasteobliquely, following round the edges of the lid or plate with asmall knife. Turn the layer of paste over, and set it on aslightly moistened round baking sheet; groove it all round;gild it, and describe a circle on top of it with the point of aknife, one and one-quarter inches awray from the edge, to formthe cover of the Vol-au-vent. Streak this cover criss-cross-fashion; also streak the body of the Vol-au-vent with the pointof a small knife, and bake it in a rather hot oven.

Upon withdrawing the Vol-au-vent from the oven, removeits cover, and clear it of the soft crumb which will be found onits inside.

BOUCHEE or SMALL-PATTY CRUSTSBouchdes are really small Vol-au-vents. Roll out the paste, making it a good one-third inch thick. Cut this layer with agrooved round cutter three inches in diameter; set the roundelsof stamped-out paste on a moistened tray; gild, and make acircular incision in each of them, one-half inch from their edges, either with the point of a small knife or wdth an even, roundcutter dipped in hot water.

Bake in a hot oven, and clear the insides of the bouchdes oftheir crumb on taking them out of the oven. “MignonnesBouchdes,” which are used as a garnish, are stamped out witha round cutter two inches in diameter, and are slightly thickerthan ordinary bouchdes.

SMALL HOT PATTIESRoll out the puff-paste to a thickness of one-sixth inch, andstamp it out with an even round cutter three inches in diameter.With the trimmings resulting from this operation, rolled some-what more thinly, make an equal quantity of roundels, and laythem on a tray. Slightly moisten the edges of these roundelswith a brush; garnish their centres w7ith some forcemeat, rolledto the size of a hazel-nut; cover the forcemeat wdth the roundelsstamped out from the first; press upon these with the back ofa round cutter two inches in diameter; gild them, and bakethem in a hot oven for twelve or fourteen minutes.

CROfJTES et croustadesFor tartlet crusts, which are put to various uses, take eithereven or grooved, large or small moulds, subject Lo the require-ments.

Roll out a piece of short paste to a thickness of one-fifth inch;stamp it out with a grooved round cutter of a size in proportionto the moulds used; line the buttered moulds with these roundels

z z

706 GUIDE TO MODERN COOKERY

of paste; pierce the paste on the bottom of each with the pointof a small knife; line with good-quality paper; fill up withlentils, split peas, or rice, and bake in a moderate oven. Whenthe paste is baked, withdraw the dry vegetable used and thepaper, and place the crusts in the drying-box, that they maybe quite dry; or gild them inside, and set them in the front ofthe oven for a few minutes.

TIMBALE CRUST

Butter a Charlotte-mould, and decorate its sides with somesort of design made from noodle-paste trimmings to which alittle powdered sugar has been added. Shape a piece of shortpaste (of a size in proportion to the mould) like a ball; roll itout to a disc; sprinkle it with flour, and fold it in two. Drawthe ends gently towards the centre, so as to form a kind ofskullcap, and take care to not crease the paste. Make thisskullcap of an even thickness of one-third inch, and place it inthe mould.

Press it well upon the bottom and sides of the mould, thatit may acquire the shape of the latter; line the mould insidewith good buttered paper; fill up with lentils or split peas, letting them project in a dome above the edges of the paste, andcover with a round sheet of paper.

Prepare a round layer of paste, one-fifth inch thick, a littlelarger diametrally than the timbale one. Slightly moisten theinside edges of the timbale; cover it with the prepared disc ofpaste, and seal it well down to the edges of the timbale, pressingit between the fingers in such wise as to form a crest reachingone-half inch beyond the brim of the mould all round.

Pinch this crest with paste-pincers inside and out.

With a round or oval grooved fancy-cutter stamp out someimitation leaves from a very thin layer of paste, and imitatethe veins of the leaves with the back of a knife; or stampout some triangles of paste; shape them like leaves, and setthese (slightly overlapping one another) upon the dome of thetimbale in superposed rows.

Finish with three roundels of paste, stamped out with agrooved round cutter of a different size from the first, and makea hole in the centre of each roundel with a round, even fancy-cutter. Gild and bake in a moderate oven. When the outsideof the timbale is well browned, detach and remove the coverformed by the leaves. Withdraw the split peas and the paper;gild the timbale inside, and leave it to dry in the front of theoven or in the drying-box.

-FLAWN CRUST

With short or any other kind of paste prepare a layer one-sixth inch thick, the diameter of which should be one-fourth aslong again as that of the flawn-ring used. Raise this layer, andplace it upon the previously-buttered flawn-ring, pressing it withthe fingers, that it may assume the shape of the mould. Thenroll the pin across the ring, in order that the overlapping pastemay be cut away; press the thickness of paste that has beenformed between the fingers in such a way as to make it projectabove the edges of the flawm-ring, and form a regular crest.Pinch this crest with the pastry pincers, and set the flawn-ringon a small round baking sheet.

Prick it with the point of a small knife; line its bottom andsides with slightly-buttered, good paper; fill the ring with drylentils or split peas, and bake in a moderately hot oven forabout twenty-five minutes.

Then remove the lentils and paper, as also the ring, andreturn the flawn to the oven for a few minutes to brown, if itis not already sufficiently coloured.

If the paste be required very dry, place the flawn in thedrying-box for a little while, or gild it inside, and set it in thefront of the oven for a few minutes.

THE LINING and COVERING of RAISED

and DRESSED PIES

The moulds for Raised Pies are oval or round. If they areround, make a layer of patty paste, one-half inch thick, in pro-portion to the size of the mould.

Sprinkle this paste with flour, fold it in two, and shape itlike a skullcap, after the manner described under “TimbaleCrust.” It is only necessary to press this skullcap of pasteinto the buttered mould in order to give it the shape of thelatter. If the mould is oval, proceed in the same way, givingthe skullcap an oval shape.

When the raised pie is filled, first cover the garnish witha somewhat thin, round, or oval layer of paste, in accordancewith the shape of the mould, and seal it well down upon themoistened edges. Then cut away the superfluous paste of thecrest, so as to make the latter even and neat, and pinch it out-side and in. Raised pies are covered in two ways—eitherwith a layer of puff-paste, or with leaves of paste stampedout with a round cutter or a knife, the veins being imitatedwith the back of a knife.

In the first case, prepare a layer of puff-paste one-third inchthick, equal in size to the inside of the patty. Drop this layer

z z 2

of paste upon the cover of the pie, after having slightly moist-ened it; gild and streak it, and make a slit in the top for theescape of steam.

In the second case, prepare the paste leaves as directed above, and lay them on the pie (slightly overlapping one another) insuperposed rows, starting from the bottom. On the top of thepie set three or four indented roundels of paste, graduated insize, and stuck one upon the other, each roundel having a holein its centre for the escape of steam.

Gild and set the pie in the oven.

The baking of raised pies made with raw forcemeat is effectedin a moderately-heated oven. Bear in mind that the larger thepie is, the more moderate should be the oven.

VARIOUS CUSTARDSHot Custards2397—CREME ANGLAISE

This custard allows of various methods of preparation whichare subject to the purpose for which it is intended. It is thechief sauce for entremets, and whether it be poached in a deepdish or in a mould, it constitutes one of the oldest and best-known entremets. This last kind of custard will be examinedhereafter. At present I shall only deal with the varietyused either as a sauce or an accompaniment, cold or hot. Itis extremely difficult to prescribe fixed quantities for thiscustard, for the former depend a great deal upon the consumers’tastes, and, whereas some like a thick custard, others go to theextreme of wishing it just liquid enough to be drunk like anyother beverage.

The quantities given below are suited to a custard of mediumconsistence, but if a thicker custard were desired, the numberof egg-yolks would have to be proportionately increased, andvice-versa.

The quantity of sugar also varies, subject to the consumers’tastes, and, as the amount used (except in the case of unreason-able excess) does not affect the consistence of the custard, itmay be graduated from three to ten or twelve oz. per quart, astaste may dictate. Six oz. of sugar per quart of milk constitutesa happy medium.

English custard admits of all the aromatic essences used forentremets, but the one which suits it best is vanilla. When thislast-named flavour or that of filberts, almond pralin, or coffeeis used, if is well to put the required quantity to infuse for

twenty minutes in the boiling milk, after the latter has beenmeasured off. Chocolate is first melted and then graduallyadded to the custard before it is cooked. Other aromatic essencesor liqueurs are added to the custard after it has been strained.English custard admits of two methods of preparation: —Recipe A.—Put twelve raw egg-yolks and three-quarters lb.of powdered sugar in a bowl. Mix the sugar a little with theyolks, and stir the latter briskly with a spatula until they haveentirely absorbed the sugar, and the resulting paste is whiteand has reached the ribbon stage. Then pour one quart ofboiling milk into the paste, little by little, mixing the wholethe while with a whisk. Then put the preparation on the fire, stirring it with a spatula, and cook it until it approaches theboil and properly coats the withdrawn spoon. Take care notto let it boil, for this would turn the preparation. In anycase, when the sauce is intended for hot sweets, by adding atablespoonful of arrowroot, it may be prevented from turning.

When the custard is cooked, as already explained, strain it, either through a strainer, into a bain-marie, if it is to be servedhot, or through a sieve into a large, enamelled basin, whereit should be frequently stirred to be kept smooth while cooling.

Custard prepared in this way forms the base of all ice-creams, of which I shall speak later on. It may serve as anadjunct to all cold or hot sweets which allow of a sauce. When, while it is still lukewarm, it is combined with its weight of bestbutter, it constitutes the delicious butter cream, which is therichest and most delicate of the pastry-cook’s confections.

Finally, if eight melted gelatine leaves per quart of cooledmilk be added to it, and it be mixed with twice its volume ofwhipped cream, it represents the preparation for “CreamBavarois” and “Russian Charlottes.”

Recipe B.—Melt six oz. of sugar in one quart of milk; boil, and pour the mixture, little by little, over twelve egg-yolks, whisking the latter briskly the while. When this custard is tobe moulded, or is intended for a Cabinet Pudding, or some othersimilar preparation, which must be ultimately poached, strainit as soon as it is mixed, without cooking it.

If, on the other hand, it be intended for an accompaniment, or for the preparation of butter creams or ices, cook it as directedin Recipe A.

DISHED ENGLISH CUSTARD (To Accompany

Cold or Hot Stewed Fruit)For this purpose English custard is made from only ten egg-yolks per quart of milk. Serve it in shallow silver or porcelain

7io

dishes; sprinkle its surface copiously with icing sugar, andcriss-cross it with a red-hot iron.

FRANQIPAN CREAM

As in the case of English custard, Frangipan custard variesin the quantities of its ingredients in accordance with its pur-pose and the taste of its consumers. The recipe given below isan average one, which the reader will be able to modify, inregard to consistence, by increasing or decreasing the amount offlour.

Mix one-half lb. of powdered sugar, two oz. of flour, twowhole eggs, and the yolks of five in a basin. Pour one pint ofboiling milk over this paste, stirring it briskly the while; adda grain of salt and the selected aromatic essence, and set thesaucepan on the fire, that the Frangipan may cook. Do notcease stirring this cream while it is cooking, for it easilyburns.

Let it boil a few minutes; pour it into a bowl, and combinethree oz. of fresh butter and two tablespoonfuls of dry, crushedmacaroons with it. When the whole is well mixed, smooththe surface of the custard with a well-buttered spoon, so that nocrust may form while the cooling progresses.

FRANQIPAN for FRIED CREAM

Proceed as above, but so apportion the quantities as toobtain a very firm cream. The quantities should be asfollows :—Six oz. of flour, six oz. of sugar, ten egg-yolks, fourwhole eggs, one quart of milk, and one oz. of butter.

When this cream is cooked, spread it in a layer one inchthick on a buttered tray or on a marble slab; carefully butterits surface, and let it cool before using it.

Cold Custards

PASTRY CREAM

Mix one lb. of powdered sugar with four oz. of flour andtwelve egg-yolks, and dilute with one quart of boiling milk.Cook this cream, stirring it continually the while; and, as soonas it boils, add to it a few drops of orange-flower water andfour gelatine leaves, softened in cold water. Boil the creama few minutes; take it off the fire, and, while stirring it briskly, carefully combine with it twelve egg-whites, beaten to a stifffroth.

N.B.—Some operators call this St. Honors cream (for, asa matter of fact, it serves chiefly in the garnishing of sweetsbearing that name), and give the name of Pastry cream to the

same preparation minus the egg-whites and the gelatine. Iprefer to abide by the principle given above, and to considerthe cream without whisked egg-whites merely as a Frangipan, with which it has many points in common.

Pastry cream may be flavoured according to fancy. Theaddition of the gelatine is not necessary when the cream is tobe served immediately, or when it only has a moment or twoto wait. But it is indispensable to prevent the decompositionof the preparation, especially in hot weather, if it have to waitat all.

WHIPPED or CHANTILLY CREAM

Nothing could be simpler or more exquisite than this pre-paration, which is obtained by whipping the best cream (keptfresh for twenty-four hours in ice) over ice. The cream speedilyincreases in volume and becomes frothy. The operation shouldthen be stopped, lest the cream turn to butter, and there shouldbe immediately added to the former four oz. of powdered sugar(part of which should be the vanilla kind) per quart, and thenthe preparation should be placed in the cool until required.

N.B.—The addition of a little dissolved or powdered traga-canth gum to the cream allows of a more frothy cream beingobtained, but the result is neither as fresh nor as perfect intaste when it is not combined with a sweet or ice preparation.

Various Preparations for Entremets

PREPARATIONS for PANCAKES and PANNEQUETS

Preparation A.—Put into a basin one lb. of sifted flour, six oz.of powdered sugar, and a pinch of table-salt. Dilute with teneggs and one quart of milk, added by degrees. Flavour with oneheaped tablespoonful of orange, lemon or vanilla sugar, whichshould form part of the total weight of sugar prescribed; or withone-eighth pint of some liqueur such as brandy, kirsch, rum, &c.amp;c., which should form part of the total moistening.

Preparation B.—Dilute one lb. of flour, three and one-half oz.of powdered sugar and a pinch of salt, with nine eggs and a half-pint of cream. Add one-eighth pint of brandy, two and a half-oz. of melted butter and one and a half-pints of milk. Pass thewhole through a fine strainer, and finish it with one-eighth pint oforgeat syrup (or almond milk) and three oz. of finely-crushedmacaroons.

Preparation C.—Dilute one lb. of flour, three and a half oz. ofpowdered sugar and a pinch of table salt in nine eggs. Stir the

mixture well; add to it a half-pint of raw cream and one pint ofmilk. Finish with a half-pint of whipped cream, and flavour asfancy may suggest.

Preparation D.—Dilute one lb. of flour, three and a half oz. ofpowdered sugar and a pinch of salt, in five eggs and the yolks ofthree. Add one and three-quarter pints of milk and five egg-whites whisked to a stiff froth.

Flavour according to fancy.

RICE PREPARATION for ENTREMETS

Wash one lb. of Carolina or Patna rice; cover it with plenty ofcold water; boil, and drain it the moment it has boiled. Wash itonce more in lukewarm water; drain it, and set it to cook withtwo pints of boiled milk, two-thirds lb. of sugar, a pinch of saltand three oz. of butter.

Flavour with a stick of vanilla or a few strips of orange orlemon rind, strung together with cotton. When the liquor beginsto boil, cover the saucepan; place it in the oven, and let it cookgently for twenty or twenty-five minutes, without once touchingthe rice the while.

On withdrawing it from the oven, thicken it with the yolks ofsixteen eggs, which should be mixed with it by means of a forkin such wise as not to break the rice grains, which ought toremain whole.

N.B.—In some cases, the milk and the sugar may be re-placed (for the cooking process) by an equal amount of syrup at120 (Saccharometer).

SOUFFLE PREPARATIONS

Souffle preparations are of two kinds :—

(1) Those prepared with cream, which if necessary may servefor all souffles; (2) those with a fruit-pur£e base, which allow ofa more pronounced flavour for fruit souffles than if these wereprepared with cream.

Cream-souffle Preparation for Four People.—Boil one-sixth pintof milk with one oz. of sugar; add a tablespoonful of flourdiluted in a little cold milk; cook for two minutes, and finish, away from the fire, with a piece of butter the size of a walnut, andtwo egg-yolks with three whites whisked to a stiff froth.

Souffle Preparation for a Big Party.—Thoroughly mix half-lb.of flour, half-lb. of sugar, four eggs and the yolks of three, in asaucepan. Dilute with one quart of boiling milk; add a stick ofvanilla; boil, and cook for two minutes, stirring incessantlythe while.

Finish, away from the fire, with four oz. of butter, five egg-yolks, and twelve whites, whisked to a very stiff froth.

Souffli Preparation with a Fruit Base.—Take one lb. of sugarcooked to the small-crack stage; add thereto one lb. of the pulpor puree of the fruit under treatment, and ten egg-whites, beatento a stiff froth.

Proceed thus: Having cooked the sugar to the extent statedabove, add to it the fruit pulp. If the latter reduces the sugara stage or two, cook it afresh in order to return it to the small-crack stage; and, when this is reached, pour it over the whites.

Dishing and Cooking of Souffles.—Whatever the souffles mayconsist of, dish them in a timbale, or in a special false-bottomeddish, buttered and sugared inside. Cook in a somewhat moderateoven, that the heat may reach the centre of the souffle by degrees.

Two minutes before withdrawing the souffle from the oven, sprinkle it with icing sugar, which, when it becomes caramelupon the surface of the souffld, constitutes the glazing.

The decoration of souffles is optional, and, in any case, shouldnot be overdone.

Hot Sauces for Entremets

ENGLISH SAUCE

See the Custard recipe (№2397).

CHOCOLATE SAUCE

Dissolve half-lb. of grated chocolate in two-thirds pint of water.Add a tablespoonful of vanilla sugar; cook gently for twenty-fiveminutes, and complete at the last moment with three table-spoonfuls of cream and a piece of best butter, the size of awalnut.

SABAYON

Mix one lb. of powdered sugar with twelve egg-yolks, in abasin, until the mixture has whitened slightly. Dilute with onequart of dry, white wine; pour the whole in a narrow bain-marie, which should be placed in a receptacle containing boiling water, and whisk it until it is four times its former size, and is firmand frothy.

N.B.—Sabayon may also be made with milk instead of whitewine, and it may be flavoured according to fancy.

FRUIT SAUCE

Apricots, red-currants, greengages and mirabelle plums are thebest fruits for sweet sauces. Other fruits, such as peaches, William

7 H GUIDE TO MODERN COOKERY

pears, apples, &c.amp;c., may also be used in the form of light purgesor cullises.

APRICOT SAUCE

Rub some very ripe or stewed apricots through a sieve, and thinthe pur£e with the required quantity of syrup at 28° (Saccharom.).Boil, skimming carefully the while; take off the fire when thesauce veneers the withdrawn spoon, and flavour according to fancy.

If this sauce is to be used with crusts, a little best butter maybe added to it.

RED-CURRANT SAUCE

Melt some red-currant jelly and flavour it with kirsch.

This sauce may be slightly thickened with arrowroot.

SAUCE ORANGE

Rub some orange marmalade through a sieve; add theretoone-third of its bulk of apricot sauce, and flavour with Curasao.

HAZEL-NUT SAUCE

Flavour some English custard with an infusion of grilled hazel-nuts, and add two tablespoonfuls of moulded filbert pralin perquart of custard.

GREENGAGE or MIRABELLE SAUCE

Proceed as for apricot sauce and flavour with kirsch.

CHERRY SAUCE

Take the syrup of some stewed cherries, add an equal quantityof red-currant jelly, and flavour with kirsch.

RASPBERRY SAUCE

Take the required quantity of melted raspberry jelly; thickenit slightly with arrowroot, and flavour with kirsch.

STRAWBERRY SAUCEProceed as for №2416.

THICKENED SYRUPS

These accompaniments of sweets, which are commonly used inGermany, have this in their favour, that they are economical; butthey should be used in moderation. To make them, take somesyrup at 15° thickened with arrowroot, coloured accordingto the purpose for which it is required, and flavoured with someliqueur or essence at the last moment.

It is with this kind of sauce that flawns and all other sorts oftartlets are coated in northern countries.

HOT SWEETSFritters

The numerous fritter recipes for sweets may all be grouped intofive leading classes, viz.:—

(1) Fruit fritters.

(2) Custard fritters.

(3) Viennese fritters.

(4) Souffl^d fritters.

(5) Sundry other fritters which are more or less like the fourformer ones without entirely resembling them.

Class 1. FRESH FRUIT and FLOWER FRITTERS

Subject to the treatment undergone by them, fruits for frittersare of two kinds: firm fruits, such as apples and pears, and aqueousfruits, such as strawberries, &c.amp;c.

420—FRITTERS of FRUIT with FIRM PULPS

Ex. APRICOT FRITTERS

Select some apricots that are not over-ripe; cut them in two ;sprinkle them with sugar, and set them to macerate for an hourin kirsch, brandy, or rum, subject to the consumers’ tastes. A fewminutes before serving, dry the halved apricots, dip them in batter(№234), and fry them in hot fat. Drain them on a napkin; setthe fritters on a tray; cover them with icing sugar, and glaze themin a hot oven or at the salamander. Dish them on a napkin, andserve them at once.

N.B.—Proceed in precisely the same way for Apple, Pear, Peach, or Banana fritters.

AQUEOUS-FRUIT FRITTERSEx. STRAWBERRY FRITTERS

Select some large, somewhat firm strawberries; sugar themcopiously; sprinkle them with kirsch, and let them macerate onice for thirty minutes.

It is most essential that the strawberries be well sugared beforemacerating, because the heat of the fat sours them while the frittersare being fried, and they consequently become tart.

A few minutes before serving, drain the strawberries, dip themin batter (№234), and plunge them into very hot fat. Drain them, dish them on lace paper, and sprinkle them with icing sugar, bymeans of a dredger.

N.B.—The procedure is the same for Raspberry, Red-currant, Cherry, Orange, and Tangerine fritters. For the last-named, it isbetter to quarter them and peel, them raw, than to slice them.

FLOWER FRITTERS. Ex. ACACIA-FLOWER FRITTERS

Select some blown acacia flowers; besprinkle them with sugarand liqueur brandy, and leave them to macerate for thirtyminutes.

Dip them in batter (№234); plunge them into plenty of hotfat; drain them; sprinkle them with best sugar and dish themon a napkin.

N.B.—Proceed as above for Elder-flower, Lily, and Vegetable-marrow-flower fritters; but in the case of the last two, thequartered corollae, alone, are used.

CUSTARD FRITTERS or FRIED CREAM

Custard fritters may be prepared in the three following totallydifferent ways.

1st Method.—Cut up preparation №2400 with a round, square, orlozenge-shaped fancy cutter, as taste may dictate. Treat the resultingpieces of custard twice d langlaise, using very fine and fresh bread-crumbs for the purpose. Press upon the bread-crumbs with theblade of a knife that they may adhere properly, and fry the piecesof cream in very hot fat. On taking the fritters out of the fatsprinkle them with icing sugar, and dish them on a napkin.

N.B.—Instead of treating these fritters d Panglaise, they maybedipped into batter and treated as directed in the case of Apricotfritters.

2nd Method.—Prepare a custard as for a “cr&me renvers^e”(№2639), using only whole eggs, that it may be firm; and poachit in a utensil of a shape which will facilitate the cutting-up of thepreparation. When the latter is quite cool, cut it up as fancy maysuggest; dip the pieces in batter (№234) and plunge them inplenty of hot fat. Drain them on a piece of linen; sprinkle themwith icing sugar; glaze them in a fierce oven, and dish them on anapkin.

3rd Method.—Prepare some common-shaped meringues, andkeep them very dry.

When they have cooled, open them slightly on top, and, throughthe hole in each, fill them either with a Bavarois preparation, withsome kind of ice-cream, or with a fruit salpicon thickened withstewed apricots or plums. Close the holes with the pieces thatwere cut out, and place the meringues in the refrigerator foran hour.

7*7

When about to serve them, quickly treat them d tanglaise; setthem (opened side uppermost) in a frying-basket, and dip them for afew seconds in smoking fat. Withdraw them as soon as their crustshave acquired a golden colour; sprinkle them with icing sugar ;dish them on a napkin, and serve them immediately.

VIENNESE FRITTERS

Quantities for the paste of Viennese fritters: one lb. of flour ;six oz. of butter; half oz. of yeast; five eggs; half oz. of salt;two-third oz. of sugar; and one-sixth pint of milk. This paste isprepared exactly like Brioche paste (№2368).

In any case, as it has to be worked with the rolling-pin, alwayskeep it a little firm.

HOT VIENNESE FRITTERS

Roll out a piece of the paste given above to a thickness ofone-fifth inch.

Spread upon it, at regular intervals, small quantities (about thesize of a large walnut) either of stewed fruit or jam. Moistenslightly; cover with a second layer of paste, of the same size andthickness as the former; press upon it with the back of a roundcutter, so as to ensure the joining of the two layers of paste, andthen stamp the whole out with an even cutter two and a half inchesin diameter.

Set the fritters on a tray covered with a flour-dusted piece oflinen; let the paste ferment for thirty minutes, and then fry themin plenty of hot fat. Drain them; sprinkle them with icing sugarand dish them on a napkin.

N.B.—These fritters may be accompanied by frothy sauces, flavoured with vanilla, lemon, orange, coffee, or kirsch, &c.amp;c., the typeof which is the Sabayon with cream.

COLD VIENNESE FRITTERS

Roll out a piece of the paste prescribed, which should be keptsomewhat soft, and stamp it out with a round cutter two and ahalf inches in diameter. Set half of these roundels of paste onbuttered sheets of paper, lying on trays; garnish them either withstewed fruit or jam; slightly moisten their edges; cover them withthe remaining roundels of paste, and let the paste ferment for thirtyminutes.

A few minutes before serving, grasp the ends of the sheets ofpaper; plunge the fritters into plenty of hot fat, and withdraw thesheets of paper as soon as the fritters fall from them.

?i8

Drain them as soon as they begin to colour; and plunge themimmediately into a light, hot syrup, flavoured as fancy may dictate.Withdraw them as soon as they are beginning to be saturated, andserve them cold.

N.B.—In the case of either of these two methods ot servingViennese fritters, the latter, which are served under the name of“fritters a la Dauphine,” may be garnished with fruit salpicons orcream preparations.

Souffled Fritters

ORDINARY SOUFFLED FRITTERS

Put one pint of water, three and a half oz. of butter, a pinch ofsalt and two pinches of sugar into a saucepan. Boil; take theutensil off the fire in order to add two-thirds lb. of sifted flour, andmix up the whole. Then dry this paste as directed for pate achoux (№2373); and finish it, away from the fire, with seven eggs, added one by one.

Flavour according to taste.

Take this paste in portions, the size of small walnuts; put theseportions in moderately hot fat, and gradually increase the heat ofthe latter, so as to ensure the rising of the paste.

When the fritters are quite dry outside, drain them; dish themon a napkin, and sprinkle them with icing sugar.

SOUFFLED FRITTERS “EN SURPRISE”

Prepare the fritters exactly like the preceding ones. Whentaking them out of the fat, open them slightly and garnish them, bymeans of the piping-bag, either with stewed fruit, jam, a veryfine, thickened salpicon of fruit, or some kind of cream, especiallyfrangipan or pastry cream.

Various Fritters

PINEAPPLE FRITTERS “à la FAVORITE”

Cut the pineapple into roundels, one-third inch thick; cut eachroundel in two; sprinkle the half-discs with sugar and kirsch, andlet them macerate for thirty minutes. Then dry them and dip theminto a very thick and almost cold frangipan cream, combined withchopped pistachios. Set the cream-coated roundels on a tray, andlet them cool completely.

A little while before serving, detach the roundels from thetray; dip them in somewhat thin batter, and fry them in plenty ofhot fat.

Drain them; sprinkle them with icing sugar; glaze them ina fierce oven, and dish them on a napkin.

FRITTERS “à la BOURGEOISE”

Cut a stale brioche crown into slices, one-third inch thick, and dipthese into fresh, sugared cream, flavoured according to fancy. Drainthem; dry them slightly; dip them into thin batter, and fry themin very hot fat.

Drain them; sprinkle them with sugar, and dish them on anapkin.

SYLVANA FRITTERS

Hollow out some small round brioches, preserving the crustsfor covers, and dip them in some thin, sugared and flavoured freshcream. Then garnish them with a small fruit salpicon with kirsch ;cover this with the reserved covers; dip them into thin batter, andfry them in plenty of hot fat.

Drain them; dish them on a napkin, and sprinkle them withicing sugar.

FRITTERS “à la GRAND’MERE”

Spread upon a moistened tray a layer half inch thick of veryreduced, stewed fruit. Cut it up according to fancy; dip the piecesin batter (№234), and fry them in plenty of hot fat.

On withdrawing the fritters from the fat, sprinkle them withicing sugar and set them to glaze in a fierce oven.

REGINA FRITTERS

Shape some lady’s-finger biscuits (preparation №2378) intolarge half-balls, one and a half inch in diameter; bake these in amoderate oven and cool them. Then hollow out these half-balls ;garnish them with apricot or some other jam; join them in couples, and dip them so as to thoroughly soak them in some fresh creamflavoured with maraschino.

Drain them; treat them d Fanglaise with very fine bread-crumbs, and fry them in plenty of hot fat.

Drain them; dish them on a napkin, and sprinkle them withicing sugar.

MINION FRITTERS

Proceed as above, but substitute for biscuit half-balls soft

macaroons, saturated with kirsch syrup. For the rest of theoperation, follow the procedure of №2433.

fritters a la suzon

Make a preparation of “rice for entremets,” and spread it ina thin layer upon a tray, to cool. Divide it up into discs three anda half inches in diameter; garnish the centre of these with a verystiff fruit salpicon; roll the discs into balls, so as to enclose thesalpicon; dip these balls into thin batter, and fry them in plenty ofhot fat.

Drain them; dish them on a napkin, and sprinkle them withicing sugar.

Charlottes

APPLE CHARLOTTE

Copiously butter a quart Charlotte-mould. Garnish its bottomwith heart-shaped croutons of bread-crumb, slightly overlapping oneanother; and garnish its sides with rectangles of bread of exactlythe same height as the mould, and also slightly overlapping oneanother. The croutons and the rectangles should be one-eighth inchthick, and ought to have been dipped in melted butter before takingtheir place in the mould.

Meanwhile, quartor twelve fine russet apples; peel, slice, andcook them in a sautepan with one oz. of butter, two tablespoonfulsof powdered sugar, and half the rind of a lemon and a littlecinnamon—both tied into a faggot.

When the apples are cooked, and reduced to a thick purée, remove the faggot of aromatics and add three tablespoonfuls ofstewed apricots.

Fill up the mould with this preparation, and remember to shapethe latter in a projecting dome above the mould; for it settles incooking.

Bake in a good, moderate oven for from thirty to thirty-fiveminutes.

CHARLOTTE de POMMES, EMILE QIRET

Prepare the Charlotte as directed above, but in a shallow mould.

When it is moulded on the dish, completely cover it with aneven coat, half inch thick, of very firm "pastry cream” (№2401), and take care not to spoil the shape of the Charlotte.

Sprinkle the cream copiously with icing sugar; then, with ared-hot iron, criss-cross the Charlotte regularly all round; pressingthe iron upon the sugar-sprinkled cream.

Surround the base of the Charlotte with a row of beads made

by means of the piping-bag, from the same cream as that alreadyused.

VARIOUS CHARLOTTES

Charlottes may be made with pears, peaches, apricots, &c.amp;c., afterthe same procedure as that directed under №2436. The mostimportant point to be remembered in their preparation is that thestewed fruit used should be very stiff; otherwise it so softensthe shell of bread that the Charlotte collapses as soon as it isturned out.

It is no less important that the mould should be as full aspossible of the preparation used; for, as already explained, thelatter settles in the cooking process.

CREME à la REGENCE

Saturate half a pound of “Biscuits a la Cuiller” with Maraschino-Kirsch, and then dip them into a quart of boiled milk. Rub themthrough a silk sieve, and add eight eggs, ten egg-yolks, two-thirdspound of powdered sugar and a small pinch of table salt. Pourthe whole into a shallow, Charlotte mould, and set to poach in abain-marie for about thirty-five minutes.

Let the mould rest for a few minutes; turn out its contents on adish and surround the base of the cream with a crown of stewedhalf-apricots, each garnished with a preserved cherry. Coat thewhole with an apricot syrup, flavoured with Kirsch and Maraschino.

CREME MERINGUEE

Prepare some “Creme a la R^gence” as above, and poach it ina buttered deep border-mould. Poach in a bain-marie; turn out ona dish, and garnish the middle of the border with Italian meringue(No 2383), combined with a salpicon of preserved fruit, maceratedin Kirsch.

Decorate the border by means of a piping-bag, fitted with agrooved pipe and filled with plain, Italian meringue, without thefruit; and set to brown in a moderate oven.

Serve an orange-flavoured, English custard separately.

VILLAGE CUSTARD

Saturate five ounces of dry biscuits with Kirsch and Anisette, and set them in a deep dish in layers, alternated with coatings ofstewed, seasonable fruit, such as pears, apples, &c.

Cover the whole with the following preparation: one-half poundof powdered sugar mixed with eight eggs and the yolks of four, and

3 A

diluted with one and three-quarter pints of milk. Poach in a bain-marie, in the oven.

CUSTARD PUDDING

Custard pudding is a form of the English custard mentionedunder №2397.

The difference between the two is that for the former wholeeggs are used instead of the yolks alone, and that it is preparedaccording to the second method only. The average quantities forthe preparation are :

Six eggs and six ounces of sugar per quart of milk. Thecustard is cooked in pie-dishes in a bain-marie, which should beplaced in the oven or in a steamer.

According as to whether the custard be required milky orthick, the number of eggs is either lessened or increased. Inregard to the sugar, the guide should be the consumers’ tastes. Ifnecessary, it may be suppressed altogether, and saccharine orglycerine may be used in its stead, as is customary for diabeticpatients.

Custard is generally flavoured with vanilla, but any other flavoursuited to sweets may be used with it

Pancakes. (See preparations №2403.,

CONVENT PANCAKES

Pour into a buttered and hot omelet-pan some preparation A , sprinkle thereon some William pears, cut into small dice; coverthe latter with some more preparation A; toss the pancake inorder to turn it; sprinkle it with powdered sugar, dish it on a napkinand serve it burning-hot.

GEORGETTE PANCAKES

Proceed as for Convent pancakes, but substitute for pear-dicesome very thin slices of pine-apple, macerated in Maraschino.

GIL^BLAS PANCAKES

Make the following preparation: work three ounces of bestbutter in a bowl until it acquires the consistence of a pomade. Mixtherewith three ounces of powdered sugar, three tablespoonfuls ofliqueur brandy, a piece of butter the size of a filbert, and a few dropsof lemon juice.

Make the pancakes with preparation C; spread the preparedbutter upon them; fold each pancake twice, and dish them on anapkin.

PANCAKES à la NORMANDE

Proceed as for Convent Pancakes, but for the pear dice substi-tute fine slices of apple, previously sauUd in butter.

PANCAKES à la PARISIENNE

These are made from preparation B, and are ungarnished.

PANCAKES à la PAYSANNE

Make these from preparation B (the orgeat syrup and themacaroons being suppressed), and flavour with orange-flower water.

PANCAKES à la RUSSE

Add to preparation C, a quarter of its volume of broken biscuitssaturated with kummel and liqueur brandy, and make the pancakesin the usual way.

SUZETTE PANCAKES

Make these from preparation A, flavoured with curagoa andtangerine juice. Coat them, like Gil-Blas pancakes, with softenedbutter, flavoured with curagoa and tangerine juice.

Croquettes.

CHESTNUT CROQUETTES

Peel the chestnuts after one of the ways directed (№2172), and cook them in a thin syrup, flavoured with vanilla. Reserveone small, whole chestnut for each croquette. Rub the remainderthrough a sieve; dry the pur£e over a fierce fire, and thicken itwith five egg-yolks and one and a half oz. of butter per lb. ofpuree. Let it cool.

Then divide the preparation up into portions the size of pigeons’eggs, and roll these portions into balls, with a chestnut in the centreof each.

Treat them d 1 anglaise with some very fine bread-crumbs; frythem in some very hot fat, and dish them on a napkin.

Serve a vanilla-flavoured apricot sauce, separately.

RICE CROQUETTES

Make a preparation as directed under №2404. Divide it upinto two-oz. portions, moulded to the shape of such fruit as pearsapples, apricots, &c.; treat these a Vanglaise, like the chestnutcroquettes, and fry them in the same way.

Serve an apricot sauce or a vanilla-flavoured Sabayonseparately.

3 A 2

VARIOUS CROQUETTES

Croquettes may also be made from tapioca, semolina, vermi-celli or fresh noodles, &c., in which case the procedure is that of theRice Croquettes.

The preparation may be combined with currants and sultanas, and the croquettes are served with any suitable sauce.

Crusts.

CROUTE aux FRUITS

Cut some slices one-fifth inch thick from a stale Savarin whichhas not been moistened with syrup, and allow two for each person.Set these slices on a tray; sprinkle them with icing sugar, andput them in the oven so as to dry and glaze them at the same time.Arrange them in a circle round a cushion of fried bread-crumbs, and between each lay a slice of pine-apple of exactly the same sizeas the slices.

Upon this crown of crusts, set some quartered apples and somestewed pears. The pears may be stewed in a pinkish syrup, which, by varying the colours, makes the croute more sightly.

Decorate with preserved cherries, lozenges of angelica, quarteredyellow and green chinois, &c. Fix a small, turned and white orpink pear on the top of the cushion, by means of a hatelet, andcoat with an apricot sauce, flavoured with Kirsch.

croCjte a la lyonnaise

Prepare the crusts as described above, and coat them with asmooth chestnut puree, flavoured with vanilla; then, cover themwith an apricot pur£e, cooked to the small-thread stage; sprinklewith finely-splintered and slightly-browned almonds, and dish in acircle.

Garnish the middle of the circle with chestnuts cooked in syrup, and pipped Malaga raisins, currants, and sultanas (washed andswelled in tepid water); the whole cohered with an apricot purdethinned with a few tablespoonsful of Malaga wine.

CROUTE au MADERE

Dish the glazed crusts in a circle as already described. Pourinto their midst a garnish consisting of equal parts of pipped, Malaga raisins, currants, and sultanas, swelled in tepid water andmoistened with a Madeira-flavoured, apricot syrup.

croCjte a la marechale

Cut from a stale mousseline brioche, some triangles of thesame thickness as the ordinary crusts. Coat them with trali»

(№2352), and then set them on a tray; sprinkle them withsugar glaze, and dry the pralin in a moderate oven.

Stick a fried-bread-crumb cushion, four inches high, on a dish, and surround it with a salpicon of pineapple, raisins, cherries, andsugared orange-rind, cohered with some stiff stewed apples, combined with a little apricot purde. Set the pralm-coatedtriangles upright alongside of the salpicon, and surround them witha border of half-pears, stewed in syrup, half their quantity beingwhite and the other pink.

On the top of the cushion, set a small pear, cooked in pinksyrup, which fix with a small hatelet, surround the border of half-pears with a thread of apricot pur<£e, flavoured slightly with vanilla, and serve a sauceboat of the same purde separately.

CROUTE à la NORMANDE

Prepare the crusts as indicated under №2454, coat them withvery stiffly stewed apples, and dish them in a circle.

Garnish their midst with stewed apples, prepared as for uCharlotte, and upon the apples set a pyramid of quartered, whiteand pink apples, cooked in syrup. Cover with reduced applesyrup, thickened with a little very smooth stewed apples flavouredwith Kirsch or old rum.

CROUTE à la PARISIENNE

Coat the crusts with pralin, as explained under №2457, anddish them in a circle. In their midst set some thin slices of pine-apple, the ends of which should rest upon the circle of crusts; inthe middle, pour a garnish of various fruits, cohered with anapricot pur£e, flavoured with Madeira, and coat the circle ofcrusts with apricot syrup flavoured with Madeira.

CROIJTE aux ABRICOTS au MARASQUIN

Cook some Savarin paste in buttered tartlet moulds. Whenthese tartlets are cooked, hollow them out at the top, taking care toleave a somewhat thick border all round.

Coat them inside with pralin (№2352), and dry them in amoderate oven. Then garnish the centre of the tartlets withfrangipan cream, combined with filbert pralin. Upon this creamset a stoned apricot poached in Maraschino.

Surround the apricot with small, candied half-cherries, alter-nated with lozenges of angelica. Serve an apricot sauce, flavouredwith Maraschino, separately.

CROUTE VICTORIA

Prepare a srsst after №2456, and garnish the centre with

candied cherries and glazed chestnuts. Serve an apricot sauce, flavoured with rum, separately.

OMELETS.

Sweet omelets may be divided into four distinct classes, whichare:—

1. Liqueur omelets. 3. Souffl^d omelets.

2. Jam omelets. 4. Surprise melets.

Omelets with Liqueur.

Example: OMELET with RUM

Season the omelet with sugar and a little salt, and cook it inthe usual way. Set it on a long dish, sprinkle it with sugar andheated rum, and set a light to it on bringing it to the table.

Jam Omelets.

Example: APRICOT OMELET

Season the omelet as above, and, when about to roll it up, garnish it inside with two tablespoonfuls of apricot jam per sixeggs. Set on a long dish; sprinkle with icing sugar, and eithercriss-cross the surface with a red-hot iron or glaze the omelet atthe salamander.

XMAS OMELET

Beat the eggs with salt and sugar and add, per six eggs: twotablespoonfuls of cream, a pinch of orange or lemon rind, and onetablespoonful of rum. When about to roll up the omelet, garnishit copiously with mincemeat, set it on a long dish; sprinkle itwith heated rum, and set it alight at the table.

Souffl£d Omelets.

Example: SOUFFLED OMELET with VANILLA

Mix eight oz. of sugar and eight egg-yolks in a basin, until themixture has whitened slightly, and draws yp in ribbons when thespatula is pulled out of it. Add ten egg-whites, beaten to a verystiff froth, and mix the two preparations gently; cutting andraising the whole with the spoon.

Set this preparation on a long, buttered and sugar-dusted dish, m the shape of an oval mound, and take care to put some of itaside in a piping-bag.

Smooth it all round with the blade of a knife; decorateaccording to fancy with the contents of the piping-bag, and cookin a good, moderate oven, for as long as the size of the omeletrequires.

Two minutes before withdrawing it from the oven, sprinkle itwith icing sugar, that the latter, when melted, may cover theomelet with a brilliant coat.

Flavour according to fancy, with vanilla, orange or lemon rind, rum, Kirsch, &c.amp;c.; but remember to add the selected flavour to thepreparation before the egg-whites are added to it.

Surprise Omelets.

Example: NORWEGIAN OMELET

Place an oval cushion one and one half in. thick of Gtnoiseupon a long dish, and let the cushion be as long as the desiredomelet. Upon this cushion set a pyramid of ice-cream with fruit.Cover the ice-cream with ordinary meringue (№2382); smoothit with a knife, making it of an even thickness of two-thirds of aninch in so doing; decorate it, by means of the piping-bag, withthe same meringue, and set in a very hot oven, that the meringuemay cook and colour quickly, without the heat reaching the iceinside.

SURPRISE OMELET MYLORD

Proceed as directed above; but garnish the cushion of Gtnoisewith coats of vanilla ice-cream, alternated with coats of stewedpears. Cover with meringue and cook in the same way.

CHINESE SURPRISE OMELET

The procedure is the same, but the vanilla ice-cream is re-placed by tangerine ice. On taking the omelet out of the oven, surround it with tangerines glazed with sugar, cooked to the large-crack stage.

SURPRISE OMELET with CHERRIES

Garnish the cushion of Gtnoise with red-currant ice, fla-voured with raspberries and mixed with equal quantities ofcherry ice and half-sugared cherries, macerated in Kirsch.

Finish it like the Norwegian Omelet.

On taking it out of the oven, surround the omelet withdrained cherries, preserved in brandy, and sprinkle it withheated Kirsch, to which set a light at the table.

SURPRISE OMELET MILADY: also calledMILADY PEACH

This is a surprise omelet, garnished with very firm rasp-berry ice, in which are incrusted a circle of fine peaches, poachedin vanilla.

The whole is then covered with Italian meringue, flavouredwith Maraschino, and laid in suchwise that those portions ofthe peaches which project from the glaze remain bare.

Decorate the surface of the omelet with the same meringue;sprinkle it with icing sugar, and set it to a glaze quickly.

SURPRISE OMELET “à la NAPOLITAINE”otherwise “BOMBE VESUVE”

Garnish the cushion of G^noise with coats of vanilla andstrawberry ice, alternated with layers of broken candied-chest-nut. Cover the whole with Italian meringue prepared withKirsch, which keep flat and somewhat thick towards the centre.On top, set a barquette of a size in proportion to the omelet, made by means of the piping-bag with ordinary meringue andbaked in the oven without colouration. Decorate with Italianmeringue, covering the barquette in so doing, and quickly brownthe omelet in the oven. When about to serve, garnish theomelet with Jubilee cherries (№2566), which set alight at thelast moment.

SURPRISE OMELET ELIZABETH

Garnish the cushion of Ginoise with vanilla ice and crystal-lised-violets.

Cover it with meringue; decorate its surface with crystallised-violets, and treat the omelet as in №2466.

When about to serve it, cover the omelet with a veil ofspun sugar.

SURPRISE OMELET “à l’ISLANDAISE”

Make the cushion of Genoise round instead of oval; set iton a round dish, and garnish it with some sort of ice, whichshould be shaped like a truncated cone. Cover with meringue;set a small case on the top, made from meringue, as explainedunder №2471, but round instead of oval; conceal all but itsinside with meringue, decorating the omelet in so doing, and setto browm quickly.

When about to serve, pour a glassful of heated rum into themeringue case and set it alight.

SYLPHS’ OMELET

Dip a freshly-cooked savarin into a syrup of maraschino, andstick it on a base of dry paste exactly equal in size.

In the centre of the savarin set a cushion of Gfaioisesufficiently thick to reach half-way up the former.

At the last moment, turn out upon this cushion an icedstrawberry mousse, made in an iced madeleine-mould, the diameterof which should be that of the bore of the savarin. Cover themoitsse with a coat of Italian meringue with kirsch, shaping it likea cone of which the base rests upon the top of the savarin.

By means of a piping-bag, fitted with a small pipe, quicklydecorate the cone, as also the savarin, with the same meringue ;colour it in the oven, and serve it instantly.

VARIOUS SURPRISE OMELETSWith the generic example given this kind of omelets may beindefinitely varied by changing the ice preparation inside.

The superficial appearance remains the same, but every changein the inside garnish should be made known in the title of the dish.

Pannequets.

PANNEQUETS with JAMPrepare some very thin pancakes; coat them with some kind ofjam, roll them up, trim them aslant at either end, and cut theminto two lozenges.

Place these lozenges on a tray, sprinkle them with icingsugar, set them to glaze in a fierce oven, and dish them on anapkin.

PANNEQUETS à la CREMECoat the pancakes with frangipan cream, and sprinkle thelatter with crushed macaroons. For the rest of the procedurefollow №2476.

PANNEQUETS MERINGUESCoat the pancakes with Italian meringue, flavoured with kirschand maraschino; roll them up, cut them into lozenges as above, and set them on a tray. Decorate them by means of the piping-bag with the same meringue; sprinkle them with icing sugar, andset them to colour quickly in the oven.

PUDDINGS

English puddings are almost innumerable; but many of themlie more within the pastrycook’s than the cook’s province, and theirenumeration here could not serve a very useful purpose. The namePudding is, moreover, applied to a whole host of preparations whichare really nothing more than custards—as, for example, “custardpudding.” If both of the foregoing kinds of puddings be passed over, puddings proper which belong to hot sweets may be dividedinto eight classes, of which I shall first give the generic recipes, from

which all pudding entremets given hereafter are derived. Theeight classes are :—

(1) Puddings with cream.

(2) Fruit puddings.

(3) English fruit puddings.

(4) Plum puddings.

(5) French and German bread puddings.

(6) English and French paste puddings.

(7) Rice puddings.

(8) Souffldd puddings.

Puddings allow of various accompanying sauces, which will begiven in each recipe. The majority of English puddings may beaccompanied by stewed fruit, Melba sauce, or whipped cream “k laChantilly."

Puddings with Cream.

ALMOND PUDDING

Make a preparation for souffl£d pudding (№2505), moistenedwith almond milk. Pour it into copiously-buttered moulds, sprinkled inside with splintered and grilled almonds.

Set to poach in the bain-marie. As an accompaniment serve asabayon prepared with white wine and flavoured with orgeat.

ENGLISH ALMOND PUDDING

Mix to the consistence of a pomade four oz. of butter andfive oz. of powdered sugar; add eight oz. of finely-choppedalmonds, a pinch of table salt, a half table-spoonful of orange-flower water, two eggs, two egg-yolks, and one-sixth pint of cream.Pour this preparation into a buttered pie-dish, and cook in a bain-marie in the oven.

N.B.—English puddings of what kind soever are served in thedishes or basins in which they have cooked.

BISCUIT PUDDING

Crush eight oz. of lady’s-finger biscuits in a saucepan, andmoisten them with one pint of boiling milk containing five oz. ofsugar. Stir the whole over the fire, and add five oz. of candiedfruit, cut into dice and mixed with currants (both products havingbeen macerated in kirsch), three egg-yolks, four oz. of meltedbutter, and the white of five eggs beaten to a stiff froth.

Set to poach in a bain-marie, in a low, even Charlotte mould, or in a pie-dish, and serve an apricot sauce at the same time.

CABINET PUDDING

Garnish a buttered cylinder-mould with lady’s-finger biscuitsor slices of buttered biscuit, saturated with some kind of liqueur;

73»

arranging them in alternate layers with a salpicon of candied fruitand currants, macerated in liqueur. Here and there spread a littleapricot jam.

Fill up the mould, little by little, with preparation №2639, flavoured according to fancy. Poach in a bain-marie.

Turn out the pudding at the last moment, and coat it withEnglish custard flavoured with vanilla.

FRUIT PUDDING

This pudding requires very careful treatment. The custardwhich serves as its base is the same as that of Cabinet Pudding, except that it is thickened by seven eggs and seven egg-yolks perquart of milk. This preparation is, moreover, combined with apurde of fruit suited to the pudding.

Procedure: Butter a mould; set it in a bain-marie, and pour afew table-spoonfuls of the above preparation into it. Let it set, andupon this set custard sprinkle a layer of suitable fruit, sliced. Thisfruit may be apricots, peaches, pears, &c. Cover the fruit with afresh coat of custard, but more copiously than in the first case; letthis custard set as before; cover it with fruit, and proceed in thesame order until the mould is full.

It is, in short, another form of aspic-jelly preparation, but hotinstead of cold. If the solidification of the layers of custard werenot ensured, the fruit would fall to the bottom of the mould insteadof remaining distributed between the layers of custard, and theresult would be the collapse of the pudding as soon as it wasturned out.

Continue the cooking in the bain-marie; let the preparationstand a few minutes before turning it out, and serve at the sametime a sauce made from the same fruit as that used for the pudding.

English Fruit Puddings.

APPLE PUDDING

Prepare a suet paste from one lb. of flour, ten oz. of finely-chopped suet, quarter of a pint of water and a pinch of salt.

Let the paste rest for an hour, and roll it out to a thickness ofone-third of an inch.

With this layer of paste, line a well-buttered dome-mould or largepudding-basin. Garnish with sliced apples mixed with powderedsugar and flavoured with a chopped piece of lemon peel.

Close the mould with a well-sealed-down layer of paste; wrapthe mould in a piece of linen, which should be firmly fastened withstring; plunge it into a saucepan containing boiling water, and in

the case of a quart pudding-basin or mould, let it cook for aboutthree hours.

N.B.—This pudding may be made with other fleshy fruit, as alsowith certain vegetables such as the pumpkin, &c.

PLUM PUDDING

Put into a basin one lb. of chopped suet; one lb. of bread-crumb; half lb. of flour; half lb. of peeled and chopped apples ;half lb. each of Malaga raisins, currants and sultanas; two oz. eachof candied orange, lemon and cedrat rinds, cut into small dice; twooz. of ginger; four oz. of chopped almonds; eight oz. of powderedsugar; the juice and the chopped rind of half an orange and halfa lemon; one-third oz. of mixed spices, containing a large quantityof cinnamon; three eggs; quarter of a pint of rum or brandy, andone-third of a pint of stout. The fruit should, if possible, havepreviously macerated in liqueur for a long time.

Thoroughly mix the whole.

Pour the preparation into white earthenware pudding-basins, with projecting rims; press it into them, and then wrap them in abuttered and flour-dusted cloth which tie into a knot on top.

Cook in boiling water or in steam for four hours.

When about to serve, sprinkle the puddings with heatedbrandy or rum, and set them alight, or accompany them, eitherwith a sabayon with rum, with Brandy Butter (as directed under“Gil-Blas pancakes” but without sugar), or with an Englishcustard thickened with arrowroot.

AMERICAN PUDDING

Put into a basin two and a half oz. of bread-crumb; three oz.of powdered sugar; three oz. of flour; two and a half oz. of marrowand an equal quantity of suet (both chopped); three oz. of candiedfruit cut into dice; one egg and three egg-yolks, a pinch of choppedorange or lemon zest; a little nutmeg and cinnamon, and aliqueur-glassful of brandy or rum.

Mix up the whole; pour the preparation into a buttered anddredged mould or basin, and cook in the bain-marie.

Serve a sabayon with rum at the same time.

MARROW PUDDING

Melt half a lb. of beef-marrow and two oz. of suet, in a bam- Imarie, and let it get tepid. Then work this grease in a basin withhalf a lb. of powdered sugar; three oz. of bread-crumbs, dipped inmilk and pressed; three whole eggs and eight egg-yolks; half a lb.of candied fruit, cut into dice; three oz. of sultanas and two oz. ofpipped, Malaga raisins.

Pour this preparation into an even, deep, buttered and dredgedborder-mould; and poach in the bain-marie.

Serve a sabayon with rum at the same time.

Bread Puddings.

ENGLISH BREAD PUDDING

Butter some thin slices of crumb of bread and distribute overthem some currants and sultanas, swelled in tepid water and welldrained. Set these slices in a pie-dish; cover with preparationNo. 2638, and poach in front of the oven.

FRENCH BREAD PUDDING

Soak two-thirds of a lb. of white bread-crumb in one and three-

quarter pints of boiled milk, flavoured with vanilla and containingeight oz. of sugar. Rub through a sieve and add: four whole eggs, six egg-yolks, and four egg-whites, beaten to a stiff froth.

Pour this preparation into a deep, buttered border-mould, dusted with bread-crumbs; and poach in bain-marie.

As an accompaniment, serve either an English custard, a vanilla-flavoured sabayon, or a fruit sauce.

GERMAN BREAD PUDDING

Soak two-thirds of a lb. of brown bread-crumb in one and

three quarter pints of Rhine wine, Moselle or beer, containing halfa lb. of moist sugar and a little cinnamon. Rub through a sieveand add four eggs, six egg-yolks, five oz. of melted butter, andthe whites of four eggs beaten to a froth. Poach in a bain-marie asin the preceding case. The adjunct to this pudding is invariably afruit syrup.

SCOTCH BREAD PUDDING

Proceed exactly as for №2490, but add five oz. of slicedseasonable fruit. Mould and poach in the same way, andserve a red-currant sauce flavoured with raspberries, as an accom-paniment.

Paste Puddings.

TAPIOCA

Sprinkle eight oz. of tapioca into one and three-quarter pintsot boiling milk, containing four oz. of sugar, a pinch of salt andthree oz. of butter.

Cook in the oven for twenty minutes; transfer the preparationto another saucepan, and add to it six egg-yolks, two and a half oz.of butter, and the whites of four eggs beaten to a stiff froth.

Pour the whole into a well-buttered cylinder-mould, sprinkledwith tapioca, and poach in the bain-marie until the preparation

seems resilient to the touch. Let the pudding stand for seven oreight minutes before turning it out. Serve an English custard, a sabayon or a fruit sauce as accompaniment.

SAGO PUDDING

Proceed as above, but substitute sago for the tapioca, andsprinkle the inside of the mould with sago. The treatment andadjuncts are the same.

SEMOLINA PUDDING

Proceed as for №2493, but use semolina instead of tapioca, and sprinkle the mould with granulated semolina.

VERMICELLI PUDDING

Proceed as for №2493, but use vermicelli, and sprinklethe mould with bits of vermicelli, which should not be broken upovermuch.

FRESH-NOODLE PUDDING

Proceed in exactly the same way as for №2493.

ENGLISH TAPIOCA, SAGO, and SEMOLINAPUDDINGS, ETC.

Whatever be the paste used, it should be cooked in very slightly-sugared milk, flavoured according to fancy, and in the quantitiesgiven above. Thicken by means of two eggs per pint of thepreparation; pour the whole into a buttered pie-dish, and cook inthe oven in a bain-marie.

N.B.—All English puddings of this class are made in the sameway, and, as already stated, are served in the dish in which they havecooked.

BRAZILIAN PUDDING

Make the preparation for tapioca pudding and pour it into amould, clothed with sugar cooked to the caramel stage.

Poach in a bain-marie and serve plain.

CHEVREUSE PUDDING

This is semolina pudding served with a Sabayon, flavoured withkirsch.

RICE PUDDING

Prepare the rice as directed under №2404, and mix with it(per lb. of raw rice) the whites of fifteen eggs beaten to a stiff froth.Mould in buttered moulds sprinkled with raspings.

The cooking and the adjuncts are the same as for Nos. 2493,2494, &c.

ENGLISH RICE PUDDING

The quantities for this pudding are: six cz. of rice, one quartof milk (flavoured according to fancy), two oz. of sugar and threeoz. of butter. The grains of rice should be kept somewhat firm, but the whole should be rather liquid. Thicken with three eggs ;cook the preparation in the oven, in a pie-dish; and on taking thepudding out of the oven sprinkle its surface with icing sugar.

RICE and CHOCOLATE PUDDING

Add two oz. of chocolate to every lb. of the preparation of rice, made after №2404, and combine therewith the whites of three eggsbeaten to a fairly stiff froth; pour the preparation into a butteredpie-dish, and cook in the oven.

Serve some chocolate custard (combined with its bulk of whiskedcream) separately. *

N.B.—This sweet may be served hot or cold.

Souffl^d Puddings.

SAXON PUDDING

Work four oz. of butter to a pomade in a basin. Add four oz.of powdered sugar and four oz. of sifted flour, and dilute withtwo-thirds pint of boiled milk.

Boil this preparation, stirring it the while; and dry it over afierce fire as in the case of a panada for a “Pate a choux.”

Take off the fire; thicken with five egg-yolks; and then care-fully mix with it the five whites beaten to a stiff froth. Pour intowell-buttered moulds, and poach in a bain-marie.

As an accompaniment serve an English custard or a Sabayon, flavoured according to fancy.

ALMOND SOUFFLED PUDDING

Make a preparation as for №2504, but use almond milkinstead of cow’s milk. Pour the preparation into buttered moulds, sprinkled with splintered and grilled almonds, and poach in a bain-marie.

As an accompaniment serve a white-wine Sabayon flavouredwith orgeat.

SOUFFLED PUDDING, DENISE

Finely pound four oz. of freshly-washed and peeled almonds, and add thereto, from time to time, a few drops of fresh water.When the almonds form a smooth paste, add the necessary quantityof water to them to produce one pint of milk. Strain throughmuslin and slightly twist the latter in order to express all thecontained liquid.

With this almond milk, dilute three oz. of flour and three oz.of rice cream, mixed in a saucepan, and take care that no lumpsform. Strain the whole through a strainer, and add five oz. of sugar, three oz. of butter and a little salt.

Set the saucepan on the fire; boil, stirring the while, and thenstir briskly with a spatula until the preparation acquires'The con-sistence of a thick paste and falls from the spatula without leavingany adhering portions. Pour this paste into a basin and combinetherewith: first, little by little, two oz. of fresh butter; then, eightegg-yolks, two ounces of finely-pounded almonds moistened witha tablespoon ful of kirsch and as much maraschino, and the whitesof five eggs beaten to a stiff froth.

This pudding is cooked in a bain-marie in one of the followingways :

(1) In a buttered pie dish. In this case, on taking the puddingout of the bain-marie, sprinkle its surface with icing sugar, andcriss-cross it with a red-hot iron.

(2) In a shallow, buttered and dredged, Charlotte-mould.

(3) In fairly shallow, buttered dome-moulds, lined inside withroundels one inch in diameter, stamped (by means of a fancy-cutter)out of a layer of Genoise or a layer of “lady’s-finger-biscuit”preparation, about one-third of an inch thick.

In the two last cases, the pudding is coated with an apricotsauce, mixed with almond milk, and a sauceboat of the same sauceis served separately.

LEMON SOUFFLED PUDDING

Make the preparation for №2504, and flavour it with a pieceof lemon rind. The treatment is the same.

Serve an English custard, flavoured with lemon separately.

ORANGE, CURA^OA, ANISETTE, ANDBENEDICTINE PUDDINGS, ETC.

For all these puddings the procedure is the same as for №2504, and only the flavour changes.

Accompany each with an English custard, flavoured like theparticular pudding.

INDIAN SOUFFLED PUDDING

Take some souffled-pudding preparation and add to it twooz. of powdered ginger, and five oz. of candied ginger, cut intodice. Proceed in the same way as for №2504.

As an accompaniment, serve an English custard flavoured withginger.

CHESTNUT SOUFFLED PUDDING

Cook two lbs. of peeled chestnuts in a light, vanilla-flavouredsyrup.

Rub them through a sieve, add five oz. of powdered sugar andthree oz. of butter to the pur£e, and dry it over a fierce fire.Thicken it with eight egg-yolks and finish it with the whites of sixeggs, beaten to a stiff froth.

Poach in buttered moulds in a bain-marie.

As an accompaniment, serve, either an English custard, or avanilla-flavoured apricot syrup.

MOUSSELINE PUDDING

Work four oz. of butter and four oz. of powdered sugar to apomade, and add the yolks of ten eggs, one by one; meanwhilestirring the preparation.

Set the latter on a moderate fire until it veneers the withdrawnspoon; then immediately add the whites of seven eggs beatento a stiff froth.

Pour the whole into a deep, buttered border-mould, which onlyhalf fill, in view of the subsequent expansion of the preparationwhile cooking.

Poach in a bain-marie for about thirty minutes, and let thepudding stand for ten minutes before turning it out.

As an accompaniment serve a light Sabayon or a fruit sauce.

SOUFFLED PUDDING à la REGENCE

Make a souffled-pudding preparation flavoured with vanilla, and poach it in a bain-marie, in a mould clothed with sugar cookedto the caramel stage. Serve an English custard, prepared withcaramel, separately.

SOUFFLED PUDDING à la REINE

Take some vanilla-flavoured, soufflM-^ndd'mg preparation.Take a mould with a central tube; butter it, and besprinkle itwith chopped pistachios and crushed macaroons. Set the pre-paration in the mould in layers, alternated by coats of choppedpistachios and crushed macaroons; and poach in a bain-marie.

As an accompaniment serve an English custard combinedwith pralin.

SOUFFLED PUDDING à la ROYALE

Line the bottom and sides of a buttered Charlotte-mould withthin slices of biscuit spread with jam and rolled up. Garnish themould with a souffled-pudding preparation, and poach in a bain-marie.

Serve an apricot sauce flavoured with Marsala, separately.

3 B

SOUFFLED PUDDING SANS-SOUCI

Copiously butter a mould, and sprinkle its bottom and sideswith well-washed currants. Garnish with a souffled-pudding pre-paration, combined per two lbs. with one lb. of peeled apples, cutinto dice and cooked in butter.

Poach in a bain-marie.

SOUFFLED PUDDING à la VESUVIENNE

Make a souffl^d-puddlng preparation, and add to it for thequantities given in the original recipe one and a half oz. of tomatojam and the same quantity of pipped Malaga raisins. Poach in abain-marie in a mould with a central tube.

When the pudding is turned out, surround it with apricotsauce, and pour in the middle some heated rum, which light whenserving.

ROLY-POLY PUDDING

Proceed as for №2361: prepare a firm paste from one lb.of flour, nine oz. of chopped suet, one and a half oz. of sugar, apinch of salt, and one-sixth pint of water. Let this paste rest forone hour before using it.

Roll it out to the shape of a rectangle one-fifth of an inchthick; spread a layer of jam upon it, and roll it up like aSwiss roll.

Wrap it in a buttered and dredged cloth, and cook it inboiling water or in steam for one and a half hours.

When about to serve, cut the roll into roundels half an inch thick, and dish them in a crown. As an accompaniment serve a fruitsauce.

RISSOLES

The preparation of rissoles for sweets is the same as that forrissoles served as hors-d’oeuvres, except that the former aregarnished with marmalade or jam, with a fruit salpicon or with stewedfruit, with plain or pralined creams, &c.

The best paste for the purpose is derived from puff-pastetrimmings.

The shape of rissoles varies very much. They may be shapedlike half-moons, purses, small, round or oval patties, &c.

Rissoles for entremets are also frequently made from ordinarybrioche paste, and constitute a variety of Viennese fritters. Inthis case they are invariably mentioned on the menu as “k laDauphine.”

SOUFFLES

Although souffles are generally served unaccompanied, somestewed, seasonable fruit, or a macedoine of fresh fruit, may, never-theless, be served with them. This, of course, only applies tosoufflis with a fruit base.

I have already given the formulae for so7ifflJs {№2405); I neednow, therefore, only give the peculiarities of each particularsouffle.

FRUIT SOUFFLE IN A CROUSTADE

Line a round, shallow, well-buttered, croustade-mould with avery thin layer of sugared paste. Spread some vanilla-flavouted, stewed apples on the bottom, and upon it lay a garnish of variousseasonable fresh stewed fruits—quartered if large. The mouldought now to be half-filled.

Fill it up with a vanilla-flavoured souffle preparation, and cook itin a moderate oven for about twenty-five minutes.

On withdrawing it from the oven, carefully turn it out on a dish ;pour a few tablespoonfuls of heated rum into the latter, and set alight to it when serving.

ALMOND SOUFFLE

Make a preparation of souffle with cream, but use almond milkinstead of cow’s milk, add one and a half oz. of slightly-grilled, chopped almonds, per half pint of almond milk. Dish and cook inthe usual way.

SOUFFLE with FRESH ALMONDS

Proceed exactly as above, but use fresh splintered almondsinstead of grilled, chopped ones.

SOUFFLE with FILBERT

Make the souffle preparation from milk in which two oz. of filbertpralin per one-sixth pint have previously been infused.

Dish and cook the souffle in the usual way.

souffl£ a la camargo

Make a souffle preparation of tangerines, and another of filbertsas above. Dish the two preparations in layers, alternated by“lady’s-finger biscuits,” saturated with Curasao liqueur.

PAULETTE SOUFFLETake vanilla-flavoured, souffle preparation, thickened somewhatmore than the ordinary kind, and add to it five tablespoonfulsof strawberry pur£e. Serve some well-cooled strawberries, coatedwith raspberry purde, separately.

CHERRY SOUFFLE

Prepare a souffle with Kirsch, accompany it with some stewedstoned cherries, covered with a raspberry purde.

STRAWBERRY SOUFFL&

This is a souffle with Kirsch, accompanied by iced strawberriesmacerated in orange juice.

POMEGRANATE SOUFFLE “à l’ORIENTALE”

Make a souffle preparation, slightly flavoured with vanilla. Dishit in layers in a timbale, alternated by “lady’s-finger biscuits”saturated with Grenadine and Kirsch. On withdrawing the soufflefrom the oven, cover it with a veil of spun sugar, and sprinklethe latter with small sweets, flavoured with Grenadine, in imitationof pomegranate seeds.

JAVA SOUFFLE

Make the soufftt preparation, but use tea instead of milk, andadd thereto one and a half oz. of chopped pistachios per one-sixthpint of the tea.

LERINA SOUFFLE

Take some ordinary souffle preparation, flavoured with Larinaliqueur, which is a kind of Chartreuse, made in the Lerins islands.

SOUFFLE with LIQUEUR

This souffle may be made, either from the souffle with creampreparation or from that with fruit, given in the note.

The souffles made from cream are flavoured with such liqueursas rum, Curasao, anisette, vanilla, &c.

Those made from fruit are flavoured with Kirsch, Kiimmel, &c.

LUCULLUS SOUFFLE

Set a savarin, saturated with Kirsch-flavoured syrup, upon adish, and surround it with a band of paper, tied on with string, inorder to prevent the souffle from drying during the cookingprocess.

Make a souffU preparation with a fruit base, set it in the centreof the savarin, and cook it in the usual way.

HILDA SOUFFLE

This is a lemon souffll, accompanied by fine strawberries, wellcooled and coated with a purée of fresh raspberries

SOUFFLE “à la D’ORLEANS”

Take some cream souffU-preparation, combined with pieces ofJeanne-d’Arc biscuits (a kind of Rheims biscuit), saturated withpeach liqueur and Kirsch, and one oz. each of half-sugared cherriesand angelica, cut into dice.

74i

SOUFFLg PALMYRE

Take some vanilla-flavoured souffle preparation. Set it in atimbale, in layers alternated by lady’s-finger biscuits saturated withanisette and Kirsch. Cook in the usual way.

SOUFFLE PRALINE

Take some vanilla-flavoured souffle preparation; add to it twoounces of almond pralin which should have previously infused inmilk. When the souffle is dished, sprinkle its surface with grilledchopped almonds, or crushed, burnt almonds.

ROTHSCHILD SOUFFLE

Take some cream ^^/-preparation, combined with threeounces of candied fruit, cut into dice and macerated in Dantzigbrandy, containing plenty of gold spangles.

When the souffle is almost cooked, set on it a border of finestrawberries (in season), or half-sugared, preserved cherries.

It should be remembered, however, that the correct proceduredemands the use of strawberries in full season.

SOUFFLE à la ROYALE

Take some vanilla-flavoured j<?w$?/-preparation. Dish it in atimbale in alternate layers with lady’s-finger biscuits, saturatedwith Kirsch; and distribute thereon such fruits as pine-apple, cherries, angelica and grapes—all cut into dice, and previouslymacerated in Kirsch.

VANILLA SOUFFLE

Take some cream .^^/-preparation, made from milk in whicha stick of vanilla has been previously infused.

VIOLET SOUFFLE

Take some vanilla-flavoured souffle preparation, combined withcrushed crystallised violets. When the souffle is dished, set on ita crown of large crystallised violets, and cook in the usual way.

SUBRICS

Into one pint of vanilla-flavoured boiled milk, containing threeand a half oz. of sugar, drop four oz. of semolina. Add one and ahalf oz. of butter and a grain of salt; mix thoroughly, and gentlycook in the oven under cover for twenty-five minutes.

Thicken with six egg-yolks, and spread the preparation in layerstwo-thirds of an inch thick over a buttered tray. Pass a piece ofbutter over the surface to prevent its drying, and leave to cool.

Then cut up this preparation into rings three inches in diameter.

Heat some clarified butter in a frying-pan; set the ringsin it; brown them on both sides, and dish them in a circle.

Garnish the centre of each ring with a tablespoonful of red-currantjelly, or very firm quince jelly.

Timbales.

TIMBALE à la D’AREMBERG

Line a buttered Charlotte mould with some fairly firm Briochepaste. Garnish the mould with quartered pears, cooked in vanilla-flavoured syrup, kept rather firm and alternated by apricot jam.

Close the timbale with a layer of the same paste, well sealeddown round the slightly-moistened edges, and cut a slit in themiddle for the escape of steam. Cook in a good moderate ovenfor about forty minutes.

On taking the timbale out of the oven, turn it out on a dish, and accompany it with a maraschino-flavoured apricot sauce.

BOURDALOUE TIMBALE

Prepare a dry paste, combined with four ounces of finely-chopped almonds per one lb. of flour.

With this paste line a buttered timbale mould, and garnish itwith various stewed fruits, alternated by layers of frangipan cream.Cover with a layer of the same paste, and bake in a good moderateoven.

When the timbale is turned out, coat it with a vanilla-flavouredapricot syrup.

MARIE-LOUISE TIMBALE

Take a stale G/noise cooked in a deep Charlotte mould; pressthe blade of a knife into it and cut it all round, leaving a base.

Remove the inside crumb in one piece which should resemble alarge cork in shape. Cut this crumb into slices half-inch thick;coat each slice with Italian meringue, and, upon the latter, distri-bute a salpicon of peaches, cherries and pine-apple.

Coat the outside of the timbale with the same meringue, anddecorate it; put the slices back inside, and set them one upon theother. Owing to the inserted garnish these slices naturally projectabove the sides of the timbale; surround them therefore with aborder of poached peaches, separated by a bit of meringue.

Put the timbale in a mild oven to colour the meringue, andserve a Kirsch-flavoured peach sauce at the same time.

MONTMORENCY TIMBALE

Cook a brioche in a mould of the required size. When it isquite cold, remove all the crumb from its inside, leaving a thicknessof three-quarters of an inch on the bottom and sides. Coat allround, by means of a brush, with apricot jam cooked to the small-

thread, stage, and decorate with pieces of puff-paste in the shapeof crescents, lozenges, roundels, &c., colourlessly baked in amoderate oven. When about to serve, pour in a garnish of stonedcherries, cooked in a thin syrup, thickened with raspberry-flavouredred-currant jelly.

TIMBALE à la PARISIENNE

Cook a brioche in a Charlotte-mould, and, when it is quitecold, remove the crumb from its inside as above. Coat the outsidewith apricot jam, and decorate with candied fruit. When about toserve, pour into it a garnish consisting of peeled and quarteredpears, apples, peaches and apricots, cooked in vanilla-flavouredsyrup; pine-apple cut into large dice, lozenges of angelica; half-almonds; and raisins, swelled in tepid water. Cohere thisgarnish with a Kirsch-flavoured apricot pur£e.

timbale a la favart

Cook a brioche in a Richelieu-mould, and hollow it out anddecorate it as above. The garnish of this timbale consists of onlywhole or halved fruit, and vanilla-flavoured chestnuts; and theseare cohered with Kirsch-flavoured apricot syrup, combined withone quart of a pur<£e of chestnut remains.

Pour the garnish into the timbale just before serving.

Hot Fruit Entremets.

APRICOTS (Abricots)

Whether fresh or preserved, apricots used for sweets shouldalways be peeled. When preserved apricots are used, it is well tocook them again before using them, for sometimes they are inclinedto be too firm.

APRICOTS à la BOURDALOUE

Prepare a flawn-crust, and bake it without colouration. Garnishits bottom with a layer of thin frangipan cream, combined withcrushed macaroons. Upon this cream set some half-apricots, poached in vanilla-flavoured syrup, and cover them with a layer ofthe same cream.

Sprinkle the surface with crushed macaroons and melted butterand glaze quickly.

N.B.—The above is the usual procedure, but fruit “k laBourdaloue” may also be prepared in the following ways: (1) Setthe fruit in a shallow timbale, between two layers of cream, the upperone of which should be covered with gratin; (2) set the fruit in aborder of rice or semolina, with the same coat of gratin upon the

cream; (3) set the fruit in a border of Genoise, combined withapricots.

APRICOTS à la COLBERT

Poach some fine half-apricots in syrup, keeping them somewhatfirm.

Drain them; dry them, and garnish their hollows with “rice forentremets” (№2404) in suchwise as to reconstruct the fruit.Treat them d Fanglaise, with very fine bread-crumbs; fry justbefore dishing, and drain. Stick a small stalk of angelica intoeach apricot, in imitation of the stems, and dish them on anapkin.

Serve a Kirsch-flavoured apricot sauce separately.

APRICOTS à la CONDE

On a round dish prepare a border of vanilla-flavoured, sweetrice, either by means of a knife, or by means of an even, buttered, border-mould.

Upon this border set some apricots poached in syrup; decoratewith candied fruit, and coat with a Kirsch-flavoured apricot syrup.

APRICOTS à la CONDE (2nd Method)

Set a crown of small Gtnoise roundels on a dish; on each roundelset a fine poached half-apricot (convex side undermost), and seta half-sugared cherry in the hollow of each half-apricot. In themiddle of the crown arrange a pyramid of rice croquettes, the sizeand shape of apricots.

Serve a Kirsch-flavoured apricot sauce separately.

APRICOTS à la CUSSY

Garnish the flat side of some macaroons with a layer of smoothfruit salpicon, cohered with an apricot purée; set a fine poachedhalf-apricot on each macaroon, coat with Italian meringue; dish inthe form of a crown, and place the dish in a moderate oven for afew minutes to dry, but not to colour, the meringue.

Serve a Kirsch-flavoured apricot sauce separately.

ABRICOTS GRATINES

Spread an even layer, one inch thick, of stiff stewed apples orstewed semolina (prepared like rice for entremets) on a dish. Setthereon some fine half-apricots poached in syrup; entirely coverthe latter with a somewhat thin preparation of “Pralin a Cond£,”sprinkle with icing sugar, and set the dish in the oven to slightlycolour the pralin.

ABRICOTS MERINGUES

Spread a layer of vanilla-flavoured sweet rice on a dish, andset some poached half-apricots thereon. Cover with ordinarymeringue; shaping the latter like a dome or a Charlotte; decoratewith the same meringue; sprinkle with icing sugar, and placethe dish in the oven in order to slightly cook the meringue.

On withdrawing the dish from the oven, garnish the decorativeportions alternately with apricot and red-currant jam.

ABRICOTS MERINGUES (Another Method)

Prepare a colourlessly-baked deep flawn-crust. Garnish thebottom either with a layer of frangipan cream or with vanilla-flavoured semolina, or sweet rice. Set on this some poachedhalf-apricots; cover with meringue, smooth the latter on top andall round with the blade of a knife, and decorate with meringue bymeans of a piping-bag fitted with a small even pipe. For the restof the procedure follow the preceding recipe.

APRICOTS à la SULTANE

Prepare a GJnoise, cooked in a somewhat deep border-mould, and stick it by means of some apricot, cooked to the small-thread.stage, to a base of dry paste of the same size. Coat it all roundwith ordinary meringue; decorate it with a piping-bag fitted witha small even pipe, and brown it in a moderate oven.

Then garnish the inside of the border with a preparation ofvanilla-flavoured rice, combined with a little frangipan cream andsome splintered pistachios; taking care to keep the preparationsufficiently stiff to be able to shape it like a dome. Upon the riceset some fine half-apricots, poached in vanilla-flavoured syrup, andsprinkle these with chopped pistachios.

As an accompaniment serve a syrup prepared with almond milk, and finished with a piece of butter as big as a hazel-nut.

Pine-apple (Ananas).

PINE-APPLE à la FAVORITE

See №2429.

PINE-APPLE à la CONDE

Macerate in sugar and Kirsch some half-slices of pine-apple.Dish them in a circle upon a border of rice, prepared as directedunder №2551; decorate with half-sugared cherries and lozengesof angelica, and coat with a Kirsch-flavoured apricot syrup.

PINE-APPLE à la CREOLE

Cook a pine-apple in a Kirsch-flavoured syrup; cut it verticallyin two, and cut each half into vertical, thin and regular slices.

746 GUIDE TO MODERN COOKERY

Line a dome-mould with these slices, and fill it up withvanilla-flavoured rice; leaving a hollow in the middle. Garnishthis hollow with the pine-apple parings, cut into dice, and custardapples and bananas, likewise cut into dice and cooked in syrup.

Turn out upon a round dish; decorate the top with largeleaves of angelica, and surround the base with bananas poached inKirsch-flavoured syrup.

Serve a Kirsch-flavoured apricot syrup separately.

Bananas (Bananes).

BANANAS à la BOURDALOUE

Peel the bananas and poach them gently in a vanilla-flavouredsyrup. For the rest of the operation, proceed as directed underNo. 2549.

BANANAS à la CONDE

Poach the bananas in vanilla-flavoured syrup, and then treatthem as directed under №2551.

BANANAS MERINGUEES

Poach the bananas in vanilla-flavoured syrup, and then treatthem as directed under the apricot recipes (Nos. 2555 and 2556);leaving them either whole or cutting them into roundels.

BANANAS à la NORWEGIENNE

Cut a slice of the peel from each banana, and remove the pulpfrom their insides. Fill the emptied peels, three parts full, withbanana ice, and quickly cover the latter by means of a piping-bagfitted with a small grooved pipe, with an Italian meringue flavouredwith rum.

Lay the prepared bananas on a dish; set the latter on a traycontaining broken ice, and place the tray in a sufficiently hot ovento ensure the speedy browning of the meringue.

SOUFFLED BANANAS

Cut off a quarter of each banana, and withdraw the pulp fromtheir insides without bursting the peel. Rub this pulp through asieve; add it to a cream .^^/-preparation; finish the latter withthe necessary quantity of egg-whites, and fill the emptied peelswith it.

Set the filled peels in a star on a dish, and put the latter in theoven for six minutes.

Cherries (Cerises).

JUBILEE CHERRIES

Stone some fine cherries; poach them in syrup, and set them insmall silver timbales. Reduce the syrup and thicken it with alittle arrowroot, diluted with cold water; allowing one table-spoonfulof arrowroot per half-pint of syrup. Cover the cherries with thethickened syrup; pour a coffee-spoonful of heated Kirsch into eachtimbale, and set a light to each when serving.

CHERRIES à la VALERIA

Prepare some tartlet crusts for sugared paste. Garnish thebottom of each with red-currant ice, combined with cream, andcover the latter with vanilla-flavoured, Italian meringue, laid on bymeans of a piping-bag. Upon this meringue set the stonedcherries, poached in sugared Bordeaux wine, and arrange thetartlets on a dish.

Lay the dish on a tray containing broken ice, and set the trayin the oven in order to dry the meringue. On withdrawing thedish from the oven, quickly coat the cherries with red-currantsyrup; sprinkle the latter with chopped pistachios, and dish thetartlets on a napkin.

ME RING UED CHERRY FLAWN

Line a buttered flawn-ring with fine paste: prick the bottom ;garnish with stoned cherries after the manner of an ordinary flawn, and fill up with custard (№2397). Cook in the usual way.

On taking the flawn out of the oven, remove the ring, and finishthe former like an ordinary meringue-coated flawn.

N.B.—All fruits used in the preparation of ordinary flawnsmay be similarly prepared for meringue-coated flawns. Only suchfruits as strawberries and grapes, which are not cooked with thecrust, are unsuited to this kind of preparation.

NECTARINES

Nectarines may be prepared after all the recipes given forpeaches. I shall not, therefore, give any recipes which are proper tothem. See peaches.

Oranges and Tangerines (Oranges et Mandarines).

ORANGES à la NORWEGIENNE

Cut a slice of peel from the top of each of the oranges, andempty them by means of a spoon. Three-parts fill the emptiedpeels with orange or tangerine ice, in accordance with the fruit

74B

under treatment, and cover the ice with Italian meringue, by meansof a piping-bag.

Set the dish containing the garnished peels on a tray coveredwith broken ice, and quickly colour the meringue at thesalamander.

TANGERINES à la PALIKARE

Cut the tangerines at the top and remove the sections withoutbursting the peel. Skin the sections raw. Fill the peels with ricefor entremets, containing a little saffron; mould some of the samerice in a little dome-mould, and set it upon a carved cushion.

Cover this dome with the tangerine sections; coat the latterwith some apricot syrup; and, all round, arrange the rice-garnishedpeels, opened side undermost.

ORANGE or TANGERINE SOUFFLE RIGHI

Without splitting them, empty the orange or tangerine peels.Half-fill them with orange or tangerine ice, according to thefruit under treatment, and cover the ice with orange- or tangerine-flavoured j<?«j^/-preparation. Place the dish containing the garnishedpeels upon a tray covered with broken ice; set in the oven that thesouffle may cook quickly, and allow two minutes for tangerines andfour minutes for oranges.

Peaches (Peches).

P^CHES à la BOURDALOUE

Poach the 'peaches (cut into two) in some vanilla-flavouredsyrup, and then proceed exactly as for №2549.

PE1CHES à la CONDE

Nos. 2551 and 2552 maybe applied in every respect to peaches.

PEiCHES à la CUSSY

Proceed exactly as for №2553.

p£ches flambees

These may be prepared in two ways as follows :—

(1) Poach the peaches whole in a Kirsch-flavoured syrup, andset them each in a small timbale. Thicken the syrup slightly witharrowroot, and pour it over the peaches. Add some heated Kirsch, and set it alight when serving.

(2) Poach the peaches as above, and set them on a fresh-straw-berry purde. Sprinkle the whole with heated Kirsch, and set italight at the last moment.

p£ches gratinees

Proceed exactly as for №2554.

PECHES MERINGUES

Prepare a colourlessly-baked, flawn crust; garnish the bottomof it with frangipan cream prepared with pralin, and upon thiscream set whole or halved, poached peaches. Cover with meringueand finish as explained under №2555.

PECHES MAINTENON

Take some biscuit, baked in a dome-mould and completelycooled. Cut it transversely into slices, and coat each of the latterwith frangipan cream, combined with a salpicon of candied fruit andchopped, grilled almonds.

Join the slices together in suchwise as to reconstruct the biscuit, and cover the latter with Italian meringue. Decorate by means ofthe piping-bag, and dry in the oven.

Surround the biscuit with a border of fine half-peaches poachedin a vanilla-flavoured syrup.

PECHES à la VANILLE

Poach the halved or whole peaches in a vanilla-flavoured syrup, and set them in a timbale. Cover them to within half theirheight with the syrup used in poaching, thickened with arrowrootslightly tinted with pink, and combined with vanilla cream.

Pears (Poires).

POIRES à la BOURDALOUE

If the pears be of medium size, halve them; if they are large, quarter them. Carefully trim the sections. Cook the pears in avanilla-flavoured syrup, and for the rest of the operation followNo. 2549.

The remarks appended to №2549 apply equally to pears andto all fruit prepared according to the particular recipe referred to.

POIRES à la CONDE

Very small pears turned with great care are admirably suited tothis entremet. If they are of medium size, halve them. Cookthem in vanilla-flavoured syrup, and dish them on a border of riceas directed under №2551.

POIRES à l’IMPERATRICE

Quarter and properly trim the pears, and cook them in vanilla-flavoured syrup. Dish them in a shallow timbale between twolayers of vanilla-flavoured rice for entremets, combined with a littlefrangipan cream.

Sprinkle the upper layer with crushed macaroons and meltedbutter, and set the gratin to form.

POIRES à la PARISIENNE

Bake a GJtioise base in a flawn-ring, and, when it is almost cold, saturate it with Kirsch-flavoured syrup.

In the middle of this base set a little dome of vanilla-flavouredrice, and surround it with pears, cooked in syrup and set upright.Border them with a thread of ordinary meringue, squeezed from apiping-bag, fitted with a fair-sized, grooved pipe; by the samemeans make a fine rosette of meringue on top of the dome, andbake this meringue in a mild oven.

On taking the dish out of the oven, glaze the pears with a brushdipped in rather stiff apricot-syrup, and surround them with aborder of half-sugared cherries.

POIRES à la SULTANE

Halve or quarter the pears; trim them well, and cook them ina vanilla-flavoured syrup.

For the rest of the operation follow №2557.

POIRES à la REGENCE

Turn the pears; cook them whole in a vanilla-flavoured syrup, and let them cool in the syrup. When they are cold cut them intwo lengthwise, slightly hollow out the inside of each half; garnishthe hollow with rice for entremets, combined with a quarter of itsweight of frangipan cream and a fine salpicon of candied fruit, macerated in Kirsch.

Join the two halves of each pear, and treat them & Panglaisewith very fine bread-crumbs.

Fry them at the last moment, and, on taking them out of thefat, stick an angelica stalk into each. Dish them on a napkin, andserve a Kirsch-flavoured apricot sauce separately.

TIMBALE de POIRES à la VALENCIENNES

Two-thirds garnish a buttered Charlotte-mould with Savarin

paste. Let the paste rise by fermentation; bake it, and let it cool.

Remove the top which acts as a cover, and put it aside; thenremove all the crumb from the inside, leaving only the outsidecrust, and smear the latter with apricot syrup. Decorate withalternate bands of sugar grains and chopped, very green pistachios.

Treat the cover with apricot syrup and decorate it in thesame way. Quarter some “Duchesse,” “Beurr£,” “Doyenn£” orother creamy pears; peel them; cut them into somewhat thickslices, and cook them in butter after the manner of Pommes aCharlotte. When the pears are well cooked, mix with them aquarter of their weight of apricot jam, and flavour with vanillaliqueur.

Serve the timbale with this preparation; put its cover on, andset it on a warm dish.

Serve a Kirsch-flavoured apricot sauce separately.

Apples (Pommes).

APPLE FRITTERS

Take some russet apples, which are the best for the purpose, and make a hole through their centres with a tube three-quartersof an inch in diameter, to remove the core and the pips. Peelthem and cut them into roundels one-third of an inch thick, andmacerate them for twenty minutes in powdered sugar and brandyor rum.

A few minutes before serving, dry them slightly; dip theroundels into thin batter, and plunge them into plenty of hot fat.Drain them, set them on a tray, sprinkle them with icing sugar, glaze them quickly, and dish them on a napkin.

APPLES with BUTTER

Core some gray Calville or russet apples by means of the tube-cutter; peel them and parboil them for two minutes in boilingwater, containing a little lemon juice. Then set them in a butteredsaut6pan; add a few tablespoonfuls of vanilla-flavoured syrup, and cook them under cover in the oven. Dish them on little, round, brioche croiitons, glazed in the oven, and fill the hollow withbutter worked with an equal weight of powdered sugar, and mixedwith a little brandy.

Cover the apples with their own syrup, slightly thickened withapricot purde.

POMMES à la BONNE-FEMME

Core some russet apples with the tube-cutter, and slightly cutthem all round.

Dish them, fill the hollow of each with butter and powderedsugar mixed; pour a little water into the dish, and gently cook theapples in the oven.

Serve these apples as they stand.

POMMES à la BOURDALOUE

Quarter, peel and trim the apples, and cook them in vanilla-flavoured syrup, keeping them somewhat firm. Proceed for therest of the operation as directed under №2549.

POMMES EN CHARLOTTE

See №2436.

POMMES à la CHATELAINE

Take some medium-sized apples, and prepare them like thoseof №2590. Set them on a buttered dish; fill the hollow ineach with a salpicon of half-sugared cherries, cohered with apricotpur6e; cover with thin, frangipan cream; sprinkle with crushedbiscuits and macaroons and melted butter, and set the gratin toform in a fierce oven.

POMMES à la CHEVREUSE

On a dish, set a cushion of a preparation for semolinacroquettes. All round arrange a close border of quartered applescooked in vanilla-flavoured syrup; garnish the centre with asalpicon of candied fruit and raisins, cohered with an apricot puree, and cover with a thin coat of semolina.

Cover the whole with ordinary meringue, shaped like a dome ;sprinkle some chopped pistachios upon the latter; dredge withicing sugar, and set to brown in a mild oven.

On taking the dish out of the oven deck the top of the domewith a rosette of elongated angelica lozenges; place a small apple, cooked in pink syrup, in the middle of the rosette, and surroundthe base of the entremet with a circle of alternated white andpink, quartered apples.

POMMES à la CONDE2

Poach some fine, peeled and trimmed apples in vanilla-flavouredsyrup. Dish them on a border of rice, decorated with cherries andangelica, as explained under №2551.

POMMES GRATINEES

Set the quartered apples, poached in vanilla-flavoured syrup, upon a base of minced apples prepared as for a Charlotte andkept somewhat stiff. Cover with fairly thin pralin k Condd;sprinkle with icing sugar, and place the dish in a mild oven, thatthe pralin may dry and colour slightly.

POMMES MERINGUEES

Set the quartered apples, poached in vanilla-flavoured syrup, upon a base of rice for croquettes, or of a mince as for a Charlotte.Cover with ordinary meringue, and smooth the latter, givingit the shape of a dome or a Charlotte; decorate with the samemeringue; sprinkle with icing sugar, and bake and brown in amild oven.

POMMES à la MOSCOVITE

Take some well-shaped apples, uniform in size; trim to within

two-thirds of their height, and withdraw the pulp from their insidesin suchwise as to make them resemble a kind of cases.

Poach these cases in a thin syrup, keeping the pulp somewhatfirm; drain them well, and set them on a dish.

Garnish them, one-third full, with a purde made from the with-drawn pulp, and fill them up with a Kiimmel-flavoured, apple-soufflt preparation.

Cook in a mild oven for twenty minutes.

POMMES à la PARISIENNE

Proceed exactly as for №2584.

POMMES à la PORTUQA1SE

Make cases of the apples as under №2598, and poach themin the same way, keeping them somewhat firm.

Garnish them with stiff frangipan cream, combined with gratedorange rind, crushed macaroons, and currants and sultanas (bothwashed and swelled in a Cura^oa-flavoured, lukewarm syrup).

Dish these garnished apples on a base of semolina-croquettepreparation, and set them in the oven for ten minutes. On takingthem out of the oven, coat their surface with melted red-currantjelly, combined with a fine julienne of well-parboiled orangc-zest.

RABOTTE de POMMES OU DOUILLON NORMAN

Prepare the apples like those “k la Bonne-femme,” and encloseeach in a layer of fine, short paste. Cover each rabotte with anindented roundel of the same paste; gild; streak, and bake in a hotoven for fifteen minutes.

POMMES IRfeNE

Select some nice apples; peel them, and cook them In syrup, keeping them somewhat firm. When they are cold, carefully with-draw their pulp, that they may form a sort of cases.

Rub the pulp through a sieve, sugar it with vanilla sugar, andspread a layer of it on the bottom of each apple. Fill up theapple-cases with vanilla ice, combined with a purée of cookedplums; the proportions being one-third of the latter to one of theformer.

Cover this ice with Kirsch-flavoured Italian meringue; set thelatter to colour quickly, and serve instantly.

FLAN de POMMES CHAUD NINON

Prepare a colourlessly-baked flawn crust. Garnish it withapples stewed as for a Charlotte, and shape these in the form ofa dome. Upon these stewed apples set pink and white quarteredapples, alternating the latter regularly; and, by means of a brush

3 c

■

754 GUIDE TO MODERN COOKERY

delicately coat these quarters of apple with some reduced whitesyrup.

FLAN de POMMES à la BATELIERE

Line a flawn-ring with some short paste, and garnish it withapples, stewed as for a Charlotte.

Cover the apples with a dome of somewhat creamy rice forentremets, combined with the whites of four eggs (beaten to a stifffroth) per lb. of cooked rice.

Bake the flawn in the usual way, and, on taking it out of theoven, sprinkle it copiously with icing sugar, and glaze with ared-hot iron.

Various Hot Entremets.

MINCE PIES

Constituents.—One lb. of chopped suet; one and one-third lbs.of cold, cooked fillet of beef, cut into very small dice; one lb.of pipped raisins; one lb. of currants and an equal quantity ofsultanas; one lb. of candied rinds; half lb. of peeled and choppedraw apples; the chopped zest and the juice of an orange; two-thirds oz. of allspice; one-sixth pint of brandy; and the samemeasure of Madeira and rum.

Thoroughly mix the whole; pour it into an earthenware jar;cover the latter, and let the preparation macerate for a month.

Preparation.—Line some deep, buttered tartlet moulds withordinary short paste; garnish them with the above preparation ;cover with a thin layer of puff-paste, having a hole in its centre;seal down this layer, gild, and bake in a hot oven.

CELESTINE OMELET

Make an omelet from two eggs, and garnish it either withcream, stewed fruit or jam. Make a somewhat larger omelet, andstuff it with a different garnish from the one already used; enclosethe first omelet in the second, and roll the latter up in the usualway. Sprinkle with icing sugar, and glaze in the oven or witha red-hot iron.

EGOS à la RELIGIEUSE

Bake a somewhat deep flawn-crust without colouration, andhave it of a size in proportion to the number of eggs it has tocontain. Coat it inside with a layer of pralin, and dry the latterwell in a mild oven.

Meanwhile poach the required number of fresh eggs in boilingmilk, sugared to the extent of a quarter lb. per quart, and keepthem somewhat soft Drain them, and set them in the crust.

Between each egg place a small slice of pine-apple, cut to theshape of a cock’s comb. Thicken the poaching-milk with fiveeggs and six egg-yolks per quart; pass it through a strainer: pourthe preparation over the eggs, and put the flawn in a mild oven, that the cream may be poached and slightly coloured.

PAIN PERDU or GILDED CRUST

Cut some slices one-half inch thick from a brioche or a stale loafand dip them in cold sugared and vanilla-flavoured milk. Drain theslices; dip them in some slightly-sugared beaten eggs, and placethem in a frying-pan containing some very hot clarified butter.Brown them on both sides; drain them; sprinkle them withvanilla sugar, and dish them on a napkin.

FRUIT SUPREME à la GABRIELLE

Prepare (1) a border of apples, stewed as for a Charlotte, thickened with eggs, and poached in a buttered and ornamentedborder mould.

(2) A macedoine of fruit, the quantity of which should be inproportion to the capacity of the mould and consisting ofquartered pears, cooked in syrup; pine-apple, cut into largelozenges; half-sugared cherries; angelica, stamped into leaf-shapesby means of the fancy-cutter; and currants and sultanas, swelledin syrup. Set all these fruits in a sautdpan.

To every pint of the pear-syrup add one lb. of sugar, and cookthe mixture to the small-ball stage. This done, reduce it byadding one-sixth pint of very thick almond milk; pour this overthe fruit, and simmer very gently for ten minutes. Turn out theborder of apples, poached in a bain-marie, upon a dish, andsurround it with a border of candied cherries. Complete themacedoine away from the fire with a little very best butter; pourit into the border, and sprinkle on it some peeled and finely-splintered almonds.

SCHALETH à la JUIVE

Line a greased iron saucepan, or a large mould for “PommesAnna,” with a thin layer of ordinary noodle paste, and fill it upwith the following preparation :—For a utensil large enough to holdone and a half quarts:—one and three quarter lbs. of stiffly stewedrusset apples; one and a quarter lbs. in all of pipped Malagaraisins, currants, and sultanas (swelled in tepid water) in equalquantities; the finely chopped half-zests of an orange and a lemon;a mite of grated nutmeg; four oz. powdered sugar; four wholeeggs and the yolks of six; and a quarter of a pint of Malaga wine.Mix the whole well, in advance.

Cover with a layer of noodle paste; seal the latter well down

C 2

round the edges; gild,, and make a slit in the top for the escape ofsteam. Bake it in a moderate oven for fifty minutes, and let itrest ten minutes before turning it out.

ENGLISH TARTS

These tarts are made in deep pie or pastry-dishes. Whateverbe the fruit used, clean it, peel it, or core it, according to its nature.Some fruits are sliced while others are merely quartered or leftwhole.

Set them in the dish, to within half inch of its brim ;sprinkle them with moist or powdered sugar, and (in the case offruit with firm pulps like apples) with a few tablespoonfuls ofwater.

This addition of water is optional and, in any case, may be dis-pensed with for aqueous fruits. First cover the edges of the dish, which should be moistened slightly, with a strip of short paste, aninch wide. Then cover the dish with a layer of puff-paste, whichseal down well to the strip of paste, already in position andslightly moistened for the purpose. With a brush moisten thelayer of paste constituting the cover of the tart; sprinkle it withsugar, and set the tart to bake in a moderate oven.

All English tarts are made in this way, and all fruits may beused with them even when, as in the case of gooseberries, they aregreen.

Accompany these tarts by a sauceboat of raw-cream or by acustard pudding (№2406).

Cold Sweets

SAUCES and ACCOMPANIMENTS of COLD SWEETS

Cold sweets allow of the following sauces :—

(1) English Custard (2397), flavoured according to fancy.

(2) Syrups of apricot, of mirabelle plums, of greengages, of red-currant, &c.amp;c., the particular flavour of which should always be intensi-fied by the addition of a liqueur in keeping with the fruit forming thebase of the syrup. Kirsch and Maraschino are admirably suited tothis purpose.

(3) Purges of fresh fruit, such as strawberries, raspberries, red-currants, &c., combined with a little powdered sugar, and used plainor mixed with a little whipped cream.

(4) Chantilly Cream, flavoured as fancy may suggest.

Finally, certain entremets allow of the following sauce:—

CHERRY SAUCE

Gently melt one lb. of raspberry-flavoured red-currant jelly.Pour it into a cold basin, and add to it an equal quantity offreshly-prepared cherry juice, the juice of two blood-oranges, a littlepowdered ginger, and a few drops of carmine; the latter with theview of giving the preparation a sufficiently strong and distinctivecolour. Finally add a quarter of a lb. of half-sugared cherries, softened in a tepid, Kirsch-flavoured syrup.

Bavarois.

These are of two kinds :—

(1) Bavarois with cream, and (2) Bavarois with fruit.

CREAM BAVAROIS

Preparation: Work one lb. of castor sugar with fourteen egg-yolks in a saucepan, dilute with a pint and a half of boiled milk, inwhich a stick of vanilla has previously been infused, and two-thirdsof an oz. of gelatine dipped in cold water.

Put the preparation on a mild fire until it properly veneers thewithdrawn spoon, and do not let it boil. Pass it through thestrainer into an enamelled basin; let it cool, stirring it from timeto time; and, when it begins to thicken, add one and a halfpints of whipped cream, three oz. of powdered sugar, and two-thirdsoz. of vanilla sugar.

BAVAROIS aux FRUITS

Constituents.—One pint of fruit pur£e, diluted with one pint ofsyrup at 30° (saccharom.). Add the juice of three lemons, one oz. ofdissolved gelatine, strained through linen, and one pint of whippedcream. The preparation for fruit Bavarois may be combined withfruit of the same nature as that used for the pur£e; and this fruitmay be added raw in the case of strawberries, raspberries, red-currants, &c., and poached in the case of pulpy fruits, such as pears, peaches, apricots, &c.

THE MOULDING and DISHING of BAVAROIS

Bavarois are generally moulded in fancy moulds fitted witha central tube, slightly greased with sweet almond oil. Whenthey are greased they are incrusted in broken ice after the prepara-tion has been covered with a round sheet of white paper.

When about to serve, the mould is quickly plunged into tepidwater, wiped, and turned out upon a dish, which mayor may not becovered with a folded napkin.

Instead of oiling the moulds they may be covered with a thincoat of sugar cooked to the caramel stage, which besides making

the Bavarois sightly, also gives it an excellent taste. Another veryadvisable method is that of serving the Bavarois in a deep silvertimbale or dish, surrounded with ice. In this case, the entremet nothaving -to be turned out, the preparation does not need to be socohesive, and is therefore much more delicate.

When the Bavarois is served after this last method it is some-times accompanied by stewed fruit or a Macedoine of fresh fruit;though, in reality, these fruit adjuncts are better suited to coldpuddings, which, in some points, are not unlike Bavarois.

Finally, when the Bavarois is moulded, it may be decorated, just before being served, with Chantilly cream laid on by means ofa piping-bag fitted with a grooved pipe.

BAVAROIS CLERMONT

Take some vanilla-flavoured Bavarois preparation combinedwith three oz. of candied chestnut purée and three oz. of candiedchestnuts, broken into small pieces, per pint of the preparation.

Having turned out the Bavarois, surround it with a crown of finecandied chestnuts.

BAVAROIS DIPLOMATE

Clothe a timbale mould with a layer of vanilla-flavoured Bavaroispreparation. Fill it with chocolate and strawberry Bavarois pre-parations, spread in alternate and regular layers.

BAVAROIS MY QUEEN

Clothe a Bavarois mould with a preparation of slightly-sugaredraw cream, combined with dissolved gelatine. Then fill up themould with a Bavarois preparation, made from strawberry purdeand combined with large strawberries, macerated in Kirsch. Whenthe entremet is turned out surround it with a border of large straw-berries, also macerated in sugar and Kirsch.

BAVAROIS à la RELIGIEUSE

Clothe a mould with some chocolate dissolved in a syrup con-taining a somewhat large proportion of gelatine. Garnish theinside of the mould with a vanilla-flavoured Bavarois preparation, made from plain instead of whipped cream.

BAVAROIS RUBANNE

This kind of Bavarois is made from differently-coloured anddifferently-flavoured preparations, spread in alternate layers in themould.

It is therefore governed by no hard and fast rules, and everykind of Bavarois preparation may be used.

VARIOUS CREAM BAVAROIS

Almond, anisette, filbert, coffee, chocolate, Kirsch, fresh walnut,

orange, and violet Bavarois, &c.amp;c., may be prepared after №2614;the flavour alone undergoing any change.

VARIOUS FRUIT BAVAROIS

After the generic recipe, Bavarois may be prepared from pine-apple, apricots, strawberries, raspberries, melon, &c.

BLANC-MANGE

Blanc-mange is scarcely ever served nowadays, and this is apity; seeing that, when it is well prepared, it is one of the bestentremets that can be set before a diner. Blanc-mange, as it isprepared in England, is quite different from that generally served ;but it is nevertheless an excellent and very wholesome entremet, and that is why I have given its recipe below.

As a matter of fact, in order to justify its name, blanc-mange ought always to be beautifully white; but, for a longtime since, the compound word has lost its original meaning.The adjective and noun composing it have fused one with theother to form a single generic title, which may now be applied withequal propriety to both coloured and white preparations; and theverbal error is so old, dating as it does from pre-Careme times, thatit would be futile to try and correct it.

FRENCH BLANC-MANGE

Preparation.—Skin one lb. of sweet almonds and four or fivebitter almonds, and soak them well in fresh water that they may bequite white.

Pound them as finely as possible; adding to them the while (inspoonfuls at a time) one pint of water. Strain the whole through astrong towel, twisting the latter tightly; melt one lb. of loaf-sugarin the resulting milk (about one and half pints); add a bare oz.of gelatine dissolved in tepid syrup; strain the whole throughmuslin, and flavour according to taste.

Moulding-.—Mould the blanc-mange in oiled moulds fitted withcentre-tubes as for Bavarois. Incrust them in ice that theircontents may set, and proceed for the turning-out as alreadydirected.

N.B.—For the preparation of almond milk, modern Cookery hassubstituted for the procedure given above, which is antiquated, another which consists in pounding the almonds with only a fewtable-spoonfuls of water and some very thin cream.

BLANC-MANQE with FRUIT and LIQUEURS

All fruits, reduced to purges, may serve in the preparation ofblanc-manges, and the apportionment of the ingredients shouldbe as follows :—the puree of the selected fruit and the preparationgiven above (including the same amount of gelatine) should bemixed in equal quantities.

These blanc-manges take the name of the fruit with which theyare prepared, i.e.: strawberries, raspberries, apricots, peaches, &c.They may also be prepared with liqueurs, which should be in theproportion of one liqueur glassful to one quart of the preparation.The best liqueurs for the purpose are Kirsch, Maraschino andRum.

Blanc-manges are also made from chocolate and coffee, althoughthe flavour of the latter does not blend so well with that of almondsas do the other products.

BLANC-MANQES “RUBANNES”

Prepare these as directed under №2621, spreading the differ-ently flavoured and coloured blanc-mange preparations in alternateeven and regular layers.

N.B.—Blanc-mange preparations may also be dished in silvertimbales, in good china cases, or in deep dishes. By this means, to the great improvement of the preparation, the gelatine may bereduced to a minimum quantity, just enough to ensure the settingof the blanc-mange and no more. And the thing is quite possibleinasmuch as there is no question of turning out the entremet.

In his book “The Parisian Cook,” Careme recommends theaddition to the Blanc-mange of a quarter of its volume of veryfresh, good cream; and the advice, coming as it does from such anauthoritative source, is worth following.

ENGLISH BLANC-MANGE

Boil one quart of milk, containing four oz. ot sugar, and pour itover a quarter of a lb. of corn-flour diluted with half a pint of coldmilk; stirring briskly the while.

Smooth the preparation with the whisk, and cook it over anopen fire for a few minutes, without ceasing to stir.

On taking it off the fire, flavour it according to taste; and pourit, very hot, into moulds previously moistened with syrup, that themouldings may turn out glossy and smooth.

Let the contents of the moulds set; turn them out, and servethem very cold either plain or with an accompaniment of stewedfruit.

Charlottes.

CHARLOTTE à l’ARLEQUINE

Line the bottom of a Charlotte mould with a round piece ofpaper, and garnish the sides with upright pieces of GJnoise, glazedwhite, pink and pale-green; alternating the colours and pressingthe uprights snugly one against the other. Meanwhile, take somestrawberry, chocolate, pistachio and apricot Bavarois preparations, and let them set in flawn-rings, lying on pieces of oiled paper.

Cut the Bavarois preparations into large dice, and mix themwith an ordinary, and somewhat liquid, cream Bavarois preparation.Pour the whole into the mould, and leave to cool. When about toserve, turn out the Charlotte; remove the piece of paper andreplace it by a thin Ghioise top, glazed with “fondant” anddecorated with candied fruit.

CHARLOTTE CARMEN

Line the Charlotte with gaufrettes, and garnish it with the fol-lowing preparation :—eight oz. of stewed tomatoes; four oz. ofstewed red-capsicums, a pinch of powdered ginger, three oz. ofcandied ginger cut into dice, the juice of three lemons, half a pintof hot syrup at 320 (saccharom.), and five dissolved gelatine leaves.

Mix up the whole, and, when the preparation begins to thicken, add to it one and three-quarter pints of whisked cream.

CHARLOTTE à la CHANTILLY

Prepare the Charlotte with gaufrettes, stuck directly upon around base of cby paste, either with apricot jam cooked to thesmall-thread stage or with sugar cooked to the small-crack stage.As a help, a Charlotte mould may be used for this operation; itmay be laid on the dry-paste base and removed when thqgaufrettesare all stuck.

Garnish with whisked, sugared and vanilla-flavoured creambuilt up in pyramid-form, and decorate its surface, by means of aspoon, with the same cream, slightly tinted with pink.

BAQUET ET PANIER à la CHANTILLY

A “Baquet” (bucket) is made with lady’s-finger biscuits, welltrimmed and stuck upon a base of dry paste with sugar cooked tothe large-crack stage.

In the middle, and on either side of the baquet, set a biscuit, somewhat higher than the rest, with a hole in its top end, cut bymeans of a small round cutter; and surround the baquet with smallthreads of chocolate-flavoured almond paste, in imitation of ironhoops.

The “Panier” (basket) is made in the same way, but with bis-cuits all of the same size, and without the imitation iron-hoops.On the base and by means of sugar cooked to the large-crack stage, fix a handle of pulled sugar, decked with sugar flowers.

The baquet and the panier are garnished with the same creamas the Chantilly Charlotte, and are finished in the same way, witha decoration of pink-tinted cream.

CHARLOTTE MONTREUIL

Line the bottom and sides of the mould with lady’s-fingerbiscuits. Garnish with a Bavaroise preparation consisting of onepint of peach purée per quart of English custard, and the usualquantity of whisked cream.

Add some very ripe, sliced and sugared peaches, on putting thepreparation into the mould.

OPERA CHARLOTTE

Line a mould with Huntley and Palmer’s sugar wafers andgarnish it with a vanilla-flavoured Bavarois preparation, combinedwith one-quarter of its bulk of a smooth purée of candied chestnuts, and a salpicon of candied fruit, macerated in Maraschino.

CHARLOTTE PLOMBlERE

Line the Charlotte with lady’s-finger biscuits or with gaufrettes.When about to serve, garnish it with a Plombiere ice (№2795)and turn it out upon a napkin.

CHARLOTTE RENAISSANCE

Line the bottom of the mould with a round piece of white paper, and the sides with rectangles of GJnoise, glazed white and pink.Set the glazed sides of the rectangles against the mould.

Fill the mould, thus lined, with a vanilla-flavoured Bavaroispreparation, combined with raw peeled and sliced apricots andpeaches, pine-apple cut into dice, and wild strawberries, all thesefruits having been previously macerated in Kirsch. Let thepreparation set in the cool or on ice.

When the Charlotte is turned out, remove the round piece ofpaper, and in its place lay a slice of pine-apple, cut from the thickestpart of the fruit and decorated with candied fruit.

CHARLOTTE RUSSE

Make a rosette on the bottom of the mould with some heart-shaped lady’s-finger biscuits, and line the sides with the samebiscuits trimmed, set upright and close together.

This Charlotte maybe garnished with a vanilla-, pralin-, coffee-, orange- or chocolate-flavoured cream Bavarois preparation; or a

Bavarois preparation made from a pur£e of such fruits as apricots, pine-apple, bananas, peaches, strawberries, &c.

The flavour or product which determines the character of theCharlotte should always be referred to on the menu, thus:Charlotte Russe d F Orange or Charlotte Russe aux Praises, &c.

CREAMS

Cold creams, served as entremets, belong to two very distinctclasses:

(1) Cooked Creams, which are, in short, but a variety of custard.

(2) The Creams derived from natural, fresh cream, whipped andsugared, the generic type of which is Chantilly cream.

Cooked Creams are prepared either in special little pots, insmall silver or porcelain bowls, or in moulds. Those prepared inmoulds are turned out when they are quite cold, and are called“Cremes renvers^es” to distinguish them from the first two kindswhich are always served in the utensil in which they have cooked.

For all that, the term “Creme renvers^e” has grown somewhatobsolete, and the modern expression for this kind of custards is“Cr&me moul6e.”

Crime au Caramel represents a perfect type of this class.

The custards served in their cooking-receptacles are moredelicate than the others, because their preparation does not demandsuch a large quantity of eggs; but they are only served in thehome, like English custard. For a stylish luncheon or dinner, moulded custards-(Fr. crimes mouses) are best.

CREME à la VAN1LLE, MOULEE

Boil one quart of milk containing one-half lb. of sugar; add astick of vanilla, and let the latter infuse for twenty minutes. Pour thismilk, little by little, over three eggs and eight yolks, previouslywhisked in a basin, and whisk briskly the while. Pass the wholethrough a fine sieve; let it rest for a moment or two; thencompletely remove all the froth lying on its surface, and pour thepreparation into buttered moulds or into vases specially made forthis purpose. Set to poach in a bain-marie, in a moderate oven, keeping lids on the utensils.

Not for one moment must the water in the bain-marie boilwhile the poaching is in progress; for the air contained by thepreparation would then become over-heated, and the resultwould be an infinity of small holes throughout the depth of thecustard, which would greatly mar its appearance.

As a matter of fact, the custard should poach, that is to say,

coagulate, as the result of the surrounding water being kept at aconstant temperature of 185°F. As soon as it is poached, let thecustard cool.

When it is poached in the utensils in which it is served, one eggand eight yolks per quart of milk will be found sufficient. Theutensils should be carefully wiped and dished on a napkin.

If the custard is to be turned out, carefully overturn the mouldupon a dish, and pull it off a few minutes later. Moulded andpotted custards admit of all the flavourings proper to entremets ;but those which suit them best are vanilla, almond milk, almondand filbert pralin, coffee, chocolate, &c. Unless used in the formof very concentrated essences, fruit flavours are less suited to them.

CREME au caramel

Clothe the bottom and sides of a mould with sugar cooked to thegolden-caramel stage, and fill it up with a vanilla-flavoured, moulded-custard preparation. Poach and turn it out as directed.

CREME à la VIENNOISE, MOULEE

This is a custard with caramel, but instead of clothing the mouldwith the latter, it is dissolved in the hot milk. The custard shouldbe treated exactly like the vanilla-flavoured kind.

CREME à la FLORENTINE

Make a preparation of pralin-ft.avoured custard with carameland poach it.

When it is quite cold, turn it out on a dish; decorate it withKirsch-flavoured Chantilly cream, and sprinkle its surface withchopped pistachios.

CREME à l’OPERA

Poach, in an ornamented border-mould, a preparation of pralin-flavoured custard. When it is turned out, garnish its midst with adome of Chantilly cream, aromatised with pralined violets. Uponthe border set a crown of fine strawberries, macerated in a Kirsch-flavoured syrup, and cover with a veil of sugar cooked to thelarge-crack stage.

Cold Creams with a Wiiisked-Cream Base.

CREME à la CHANTILLY

Take some fresh and somewhat thick cream, and whisk it untilit is sufficiently stiff to span the members of the whisk. Addto it eight oz. of powdered sugar per quart of cream, and flavourwith vanilla or fruit essence

Whatever be the purpose of this cream, it should, if possible, be prepared only at the last moment.

CREME aux FRUITS à la CHANTILLY

The constituents for this preparation are a purde of the selectedfruit and Chantilly cream, in the proportion of one-third of theformer to two-thirds of the latter.

The quantities of sugar and kind of flavour vary according tothe nature of the fruit.

It is served either as an entremet garnish, or alone in a bowl, with a decoration of the same cream, laid by means of a piping-bag fitted with a small even or grooved pipe. Send some lady’s-finger biscuits separately.

CREME CAPRICE

Take some Chantilly cream, and add to it one-quarter of itsbulk of roughly broken-up meringues. Put the preparation in aniced Madeleine-mould, lined with white paper; seal up thoroughly;string tightly, and keep the utensil in ice for two hours.

Turn out when about to serve; remove the paper; anddecorate, by means of a piping-bag fitted with a grooved pipe, with Chantilly cream, tinted pink with strawberry and raspberryjuice.

BRISE DU PRINTEMPS

Take some violet-flavoured, slightly-iced Chantilly cream, andset in small dessert-dishes, by means of a spoon.

' 2648—NUEES ROSES

Take some Chantilly cream, aromatised with vanilla-flavouredstrawberry pur£e, and dish it in small dessert-dishes, by meansof a spoon.

FLAMRI

Boil one pint of white wine and as much water, and sprinklein it eight oz. of small semolina. Cook gently for twenty-fiveminutes. Then add to the preparation two-thirds lb. of powderedsugar, a pinch of table-salt, two eggs, and the whites of six, beatento a stiff froth.

Pour it into moulds with buttered sides; set these to poach inthe bain-marie, and leave them to cool. Turn out, and coat with apur£e of raw fruit, such as strawberries, red-currants, cherries, &c., reasonably sugared.

JELLIES

From the standpoint of their preparation, jellies are of twokinds: (1) wine-or liqueur-flavoured jellies; (2) fruit jellies. Buttheir base is the same in all cases, i.e., gelatine dissolved in acertain quantity of water.

The gelatine should be extracted from calf’s foot, by boilingthe latter; but, although this is the best that can be obtained, themeans of obtaining it are the most complicated. The gelatinebought ready-made may also be used in the quantities givenbelow.

CALF’S-FOOT JELLY

Take some fine soaked and blanched calves’ feet, and set them*to cook in one and three-quarters pints of water apiece. Skim asthoroughly as possible; cover, and then cook very gently for sevenhours. This done, strain the cooking-liquor and clear it of allgrease; test its strength, after having cooled a little of it on ice;rectify it if necessary with sufficient filtered water, and once moretest it by means of ice.

Per quart of calf’s-foot jelly, add eight oz. of sugar, a mite ofqinnamon, half the rind of an orange and lemon, and all theirjuice.

For the clarification, proceed as directed hereafter.

JELLY with A GELATINE BASE

Dissolve one oz. of strong gelatine in a quart of water. Addone-half lb. of sugar, one-sixth oz. of coriander, and the zest andjuice of half a lemon and of a whole orange; boil, and then letthe preparation stand for ten minutes away from the fire.

Whisk one and a half egg-whites in a very clean saucepan, together with a port wine-glassful of white wine, and pour thecleared syrup, little by little, over the egg-whites, whisking brisklythe while. Set the saucepan on the fire, and continue whiskinguntil the boil is reached; then move the utensil to a cornerof the stove, and keep the jelly only just simmering for one-quarterof an hour.

At the end of that time the clarification is completed; strainthe jelly through a woollen bag, placed over a very clean bowl, and, if the jelly is turbid after the first time of straining, strain itagain and again until it becomes quite clear. Let it almost coolbefore adding any flavour.

The Flavouring.—Whether the jelly be prepared from calves’feet or from gelatine, the above preparation is naught else than acohered syrup, to which the addition of some flavour lends thecharacter of a jelly. The complementary ingredients for jellies areliqueurs, good wines, and the juice of fruit; and the quantity of waterprescribed should be so reduced as to allow for the ultimateaddition of the liquid flavouring.

Thus, every jelly of which the flavour is a liqueur ought to beprepared with only nine-tenths of a quart of water; and the

remaining one-tenth of the measure is subsequently added in theform of Kirsch, Maraschino, Rum, or Anisette, &c.

A jelly flavoured with a good wine, such as Champagne, Madeira, Sherry, Marsala, &c., should contain only seven-tenthsof a quart of water and three-tenths of a quart of the selectedwine.

In the case of fruit jellies, the procedure differs in accordancewith the kind of fruit used.

For red-fruit jellies, prepared from strawberries, raspberries, red-currants, cherries, and cranberries, these fruits, which shouldbe very ripe, are rubbed through a sieve, and combined with one-tenth to three-tenths of a quart of water per lb., according as towhether the fruit be more or less juicy.

This done, filter the resulting juice, and add it to the jelly in theproportion of one part of the former to two parts of the latter.The jelly should therefore be twice as strong as for the previouspreparation, in order that it may remain sufficiently consistent inspite of the added juice.

When the fruit is too juicy, rub it through a sieve; let thejuice ferment for a few hours, and only filter the clear juice whichresults from the fermentation.

Aqueous-fruit jellies, prepared from grapes, oranges, lemons, and tangerines, are made in the same way. The filtering of thesefruit juices is easily done, and, except for the grapes, they need notbe set to ferments

When these fruits are not quite ripe, their juices may be addedto the jelly even before the clarification—a procedure which helpsto modify their acidity. The apportionment of the fruit juicesto the jelly is practically the same as that of the red-fruit juices.

Stone-fruit, such as apricots, peaches, nectarines, plums, &c., areoften used as jelly garnishes, but seldom serve as the flavouringbase of a jelly. Whenever they are treated in this way, they arefirst plunged in boiling water, that they may be peeled; they arethen poached and left to cool in the syrup which goes towardspreparing the jelly.

This jelly, after it has been clarified and three-parts cooled, should have a little Kirsch or Maraschino added to it, that itsfruit flavour may be intensified.

THE GARNISH and ACCOMPANIMENTS of JELLIES

As a rule, jellies are served plain. Sometimes, however, theyare garnished with variously-shaped, stewed fruits, symmetricallydistributed in the jelly, with their colours nicely contrasted.

A jelly prepared in this way is called a “Suddoise of fruit.”

QELEES RUBANNEES

These are differently-flavoured and differently-coloured jelliesmoulded in alternate layers, even and equally thick.

They are generally served without garnish.

JELLIES à la RUSSE

These are ordinary jellies which are whisked over ice until theybegin to set. They are then speedily moulded. By skilfullymixing two or three of these jellies, of different shades andflavours, at the moment of moulding, very effective “MarbledJellies” are obtained.

JELLIES à la MOSCOVITE

These are ordinary jellies, poured into tightly-closing moulds, the sealing of which is ensured by a thread of butter, laid roundthe edges of the lids. The moulds are then surrounded withbroken ice, mixed with five lb. of freezing salt and eight oz. ofsaltpetre per twenty-five lb. of ice.

The cold produced by the salted ice causes a frosted coat toform round the jelly, the effect of which is exceedingly pretty.But the moulds should be withdrawn from the ice as soon as thefrosted coat is formed and the jelly is set; for a longer sojourn inthe cold would transform the jelly into an uneatable block of ice.

N.B.—Modern methods have greatly simplified the dishing andserving of jellies. They are now dished in special silver bowls ordeep dishes, and they are not, as a rule, moulded. The bottom ofthese utensils is sometimes decked with stewed fruit or macedoinesof fruit which are covered with the jelly; and, as the latter isserved in the utensil itself, the quantity of gelatine may bereduced, and greater delicacy is the result.

PAINS de FRUITS

These “pains” are made in ordinary Charlotte moulds.

Clothe the mould with a fairly thick coat of jelly, in keepingwith the flavour of the fruit used, which may be apricots, straw-berries, red-currants, cherries, peaches, &c. Fill up the mouldwith a preparation, made as for a fruit Bavarois, but withoutcream.

The amount of gelatine used should therefore be reduced.

COLD PUDDINGS

Cold puddings have a great deal in common with Bavaroisand, more often than not, these two kinds of sweets have the samebase. Their distinguishing difference lies in the fact that Bavaroisare generally served without a garnish or sauce, whereas puddingsalways have either one or the other, and sometimes both.

The sauces for puddings are those given at the beginning ofthis chapter.

Their garnishes always consist of fruit, and the latter is eitherstewed and served separately, or it is candied and combined withthe pudding paste.

PUDDING à la BOHEMIENNE

Make some very small pancakes, and garnish them with asalpicon of candied fruits and currants swelled in tepid water, cohered with some fairly stiff, apple pur£e. Close up the pancakesto the shape of balls or rectangles, and set them in a butteredborder-mould. Fill up the mould with a moulded-custard pre-paration (№2639), containing a good proportion of whole eggs, and poach in a bain-marie.

Leave the whole to cool in the mould; turn out at the lastmoment, and coat the pudding with a sabayon, flavoured accordingto fancy.

PUDDING DIPLOMATE

Decorate the bottom of an oiled deep Bavarois-mould withpieces of candied fruit. Fill up the mould with alternate layersof vanilla-flavoured Bavarois preparation and “lady’s-finger-biscuits,” saturated with Kirsch. On each layer of biscuit sprinklesome currants and raisins swelled in tepid water, and here andthere set a tablespoonful of apricot jam.

Let the contents of the mould set in the cool or on ice, andturn out just before serving.

PUDDING DIPLOMATE aux FRUITS

Prepare the pudding as above, but spread a few extra layers offresh fruit in the mould, such as very ripe pears, peaches, apricots, &c., all peeled, cut into thin slices, and previously macerated withpowdered sugar and half a port wine-glassful of either Kirsch, Maraschino, or Anisette, &c.

When the pudding is turned out, surround its base with somevery cold stewed fruit the same as one of the kinds used insidethe pudding, or some stewed, mixed fruit.

PUDDING MALAKOFF

Prepare (1) a gelatinous English custard, combined with one pintof very fresh, raw cream per quart; (2) a stew of apples and pears, prepared as for an apple Charlotte; currants and sultanas, swelledin tepid syrup; fresh splintered almonds; candied orange rind, cut into dice; slices of stale biscuit, or lady’s-finger biscuits, saturated with liqueur. Oil a Charlotte mould, and pour into ita layer of cream half an inch thick. Upon this cream lay

3 D

770 GUIDE TO MODERN COOKERY

a thickness of biscuits, copiously coated with marmalade, andsprinkle with raisins, almonds and orange-rind dice.

Cover with a layer of cream; lay a second thickness of biscuits, and proceed thus in the same order with a Kirsch-flavoured coldsabayon.

PUDDING à la NESSELRODE

To an English custard, prepared after №2397, add eight oz.of a smooth, chestnut purde, and four oz. of currants and sultanas(swelled in tepid water), and candied orange-rind and cherries, cut into dice; these four products should be in almost equalquantities, and ought to have been previously macerated insweetened Madeira.

Add some Maraschino-flavoured, whipped cream to the pre-paration; apportioning it as for a Bavarois.

Garnish the bottom and sides of a Charlotte mould with whitepaper; pour the preparation into the mould; completely close thelatter, sealing the lid down with a thread of butter, and surroundthe utensil with plenty of salted ice. When about to serve, turnout on a napkin; remove the paper, and surround the base of thepudding with a crown of fine, candied chestnuts, or balls of choco-late-iced, candied chestnut purde.

N.B.—The English custard may be packed in the freezer, mixed with whipped cream when it is almost congealed, and thenplaced in a mould.

PUDDING à la RICHELIEU

Rub some stewed prunes through a fine sieve, and add to thepur£e equal quantities of very stiff, Kirsch-flavoured jelly and thereduced juice of the prunes. Let a layer three-quarters of an inchthick, of the preparation set on the bottom of a Charlotte mould.In the latter set a smaller mould (tinned outside), filled withbroken ice, and either fitted with handles that can rest on the brimof the first mould, or else sufficiently deep to be easily graspedand removed when necessary. The space between the sides of thetwo moulds should measure about three-quarters of an inch.

Fill up this space with what remains of the prune pur£e, thickened with jelly; leave the preparation to set; withdraw theice from the little mould; pour some tepid water into the latter, that it may be immediately detached from the surrounding, iced preparation.

Fill the space left by the withdrawn mould with some vanilla-flavoured Bavarois preparation; leave to set, and turn out at thelast moment on a napkin.

PUDDING or “CR6ME REINE DES FEES”

Prepare the whites of four eggs as for Italian meringue (№2383), and add to the sugar, while cooking, its bulk of quincejelly, and, at the last moment, one and a half ounces of candiedfruit, cut into dice, macerated in Kirsch and carefully drained. Setthe mervigue, in shapes resembling large buttons, on a sheet ofpaper.

Boil in a utensil large enough to take the sheet of paper, fourquarts of water, containing two and a half lb. of sugar and one-quarter pint of Kirsch. Slip the sheet of paper into this boilingsyrup; withdraw it as soon as it easily separates from the piecesof meringue; poach the latter; drain them on a piece of linenand let them cool.

Meanwhile, make two Bavarois preparations; one white andvanilla-flavoured, and the other pink and flavoured with Curagoa.In these preparations the quantity of whisked cream should betwice as much as for ordinary Bavarois, whereas the quantity ofgelatine should be reduced by half.

Set these preparations in even, alternate layers, in a slightly-oiled iced -Madeleine mould, distributing the meritigues betweeneach layer.

Cover the mould with a piece of paper and a lid, and keep itsurrounded by ice for two hours. When about to serve, turn itout on a napkin.

COLD FRUIT ENTREMETS.

Apricots (Abricots).

ABRICOTS à la PARISIENNE

Poach the halved apricots in vanilla-flavoured syrup. Cool themand drain them; and reconstruct the apricots by joining the halvestogether with a piece of vanilla ice-crcam, the size of a walnut, inthe centre.

Set these apricots upon some large overturned macaroons;cover with vanilla-flavoured Chantilly cream, shaped like a coneand sprinkle with fine filbert pralin.

ABRICOTS à la ROYALE

Take some fairly deep tartlet moulds, and set in them some fine(cold, half-apricots, poached in vanilla-flavoured syrup. Fill up thetartlet moulds with very limpid, Kirsch-flavoured jelly.

Prepare a shallow, GJnoise border, glazed with red-currant jelly, cooked to the small-thread stage, and sprinkle with choppedpistachios.

3 D 2

Turn out the tartlets of apricot jelly and place them in a crownover the border. Garnish the centre of the latter with choppedanisette-flavoured pink jelly.

Pine-apple (Ananas).

ANANAS GEORGETTE

Take a fine whole pine-apple, and hollow it out to within hallan inch of its outside all round and at the bottom. Put aside theslice cut from the top, on which is the bunch of leaves.

Fill the inside with a Bavarois preparation made from pine-apple pur£e, combined with the withdrawn pine-apple pulp, cutinto thin slices, and leave to set. Dish on a napkin, and return thetop slice to the pine-apple, that it may seem untouched.

ANANAS à la V1RGINIE

Proceed exactly as above, but replace the pine-apple Bavaroispreparation by a strawberry kind, combined, as before, with thepulp withdrawn from the inside of the pine-apple, cut into dice.

ANANAS à la NINON

Line the sides of a souffle timbale with vanilla ice-cream, layingit in an oblique strip from the edge of the utensil to the centre ofthe bottom of the timbale. Upon this layer of ice-cream settwo or three rows of thin pine-apple slices, in such a way as tomake the slices of the last row project beyond the edge of thetimbale.

In the centre of the mould build a pyramid of wild straw-berries; cover this with a raspberry puree, and sprinkle the latterwith chopped pistachios.

a—PINE-APPLE à la ROYALE

Take a fresh pine-apple and cut a slice from its top, contain-ing the bunch of leaves. Withdraw the pulp from the inside, and leave a thickness of about half an inch all round and on thebottom.

Fill it with a macedoine of fresh fruit macerated in Kirsch; setit in the middle of a crystal bowl; and surround the base witha crown of fine Montreuil peaches, poached in a vanilla-flavouredsyrup, alternated by large strawberries, macerated in 'Kirsch.

Return the bunch of leaves to its place upon the pine-apple.

Cherries (Cerises).

CERISES à la DUBARRY

Line a flawn-ring with good, short paste; set it on a smallround baking-sheet; prick the paste on the bottom to preventits blistering while baking, sprinkle with powdered sugar, andgarnish with fine, stoned cherries, pressed snugly one against theother.

Bake the flawn in the usual way and let it cool.

When it is quite cold cover the cherries with Chantilly cream, combined either with ordinary pr-alin or with crushed macaroons.

Smooth the surface of the cream, as also the sides of theflawn; cover it with macaroon powder, and then decorate bymeans of the piping-bag with white and pink Chantilly cream.

CERISES au CLARET

Select some fine cherries; cut off the ends of their stalks, andset them in a silver timbale. Pour sufficient sweetened Bordeauxwine (flavoured with a mite of cinnamon) over them, to just coverthem. Close the timbale, and keep it on the side of the fire for tenminutes, that the cherries may poach.

Let them cool in the syrup; drain the latter away; reduceit by a third, and add, in order to thicken it slightly, one table-spoonful of red-currant jelly per six tablespoonfuls of reducedsyrup.

Serve the cherries quite cold, and some lady’s-finger biscuitsseparately.

Strawberries (Fraises).

FRAISES à la CREOLE

Set some fine strawberries and an equal amount of pine-apple, cut into dice, to macerate in powdered sugar and Kirsch.

Arrange a close crown of pine-apple slices, also macerated inKirsch, upon a tazza. In the middle of the crown build a pyramidof the strawberries and pine-apple, and sprinkle with a Kirsch-flavoured syrup.

FRAISES FEMINA

Select some fine strawberries; sprinkle them with sugar andGrand-Marnier Curagao, and leave them to macerate on ice foran hour.

When about to serve, spread on the bottom of a bowl 01timbale a layer of orange-ice (which should be combined with themacerating liqueur) and set the strawberries thereon.

FRAISES MARGUERITE

Set some wild strawberries to macerate in sugar and Kirsch.Drain them; cohere them with an equal quantity of pomegranatesherbet; set them in a silver timbale, already surrounded with ice ;cover the strawberries with Maraschino-flavoured Chantilly cream, and decorate with the latter.

FRAISES MARQUISE

Set in a timbale surrounded with ice some Chantilly cream, combined with half its bulk of a purde of wild strawberries.Completely cover this cream with fine, fair-sized selected straw-berries (macerated with Kirsch), rolled at the last minute in semolinasugar.

FRAISES MELBA

Garnish the bottom of a timbale with vanilla ice-cream. Uponthis arrange a layer of choice strawberries, and cover the latter witha thick, slightly-sugared, fresh raspberry pur£e.

FRAISES NINA

Prepare the strawberries as directed under №2675, andcohere them with pine-apple sherbet. Dish them as before in atimbale, and cover them with some Chantilly cream, tinted pink bymeans of a red-capsicum purée flavoured with ginger.

FRAISES ROMANOFF

Macerate some fine strawberries with orange juice and Curasao.Set them in a timbale surrounded with ice, and cover them withChantilly cream, laid upon them by means of a piping-bag, fittedwith a large, grooved pipe.

FRAISES WILHELMINE

Macerate some fine, large strawberries with Kirsch, powderedsugar, and orange juice. Dish them in a timbale and serve avanilla-flavoured Chantilly cream separately.

FRAISES LERINA

Take a small black melon of Carmes; open it by cutting out abung-shaped piece containing the stalk, and remove all its seeds.Then cut out all the pulp, by means of a dessert-spoon, andsprinkle it with powdered sugar.

Macerate the required number of strawberries in Larinaliqueur.

Garnish the inside of the melon with these strawberries and thewithdrawn pulp; close the melon by replacing the bung cut out at

the start, and keep in a refrigerator for two hours, surroundedby ice.

Dish on a napkin at the last moment

FRAISES “REVE de BEBE”

Select a fair-sized, very ripe pine-apple, cut off a slice of it at thetop and withdraw all its pulp without bursting the rind.

Prepare a square cushion of GJnoise, about two inches thick ;slightly hollow it out towards its centre, that the emptied pine-apple may be set upright upon it; and stick the cushion upon adry-paste base, of the same size and shape as the former. Glazethe GJnoise cushion with pink fondant, decorate with “royale”glaze, and set a large strawberry at each corner.

Slice half of the withdrawn pine-apple pulp, and macerate itwith Kirsch, Maraschino and sugar. Pound the remaining pulpand press it in order to extract its juice.

Set to macerate with this pine-apple juice a sufficient quantityof strawberries to three-parts fill the pine-apple.

When about to serve, fill the emptied pine-apple with successiveand alternate layers ^f pine-apple with Kirsch and strawberries ;and, between each layer, spread a coat of vanilla-flavoured, Chantilly cream.

Close the pine-apple with the slice cut off at the start, and set itupright in the hollow of the cushion. Serve the preparation verycold.

FRAISES à la RITZ

Set some well-sugared and cooled strawberries in a timbale, and

cover them with the following preparation: rub half-pound of wildstrawberries through a sieve; add a little Melba sauce to thepurde, that it may acquire a pink tint; and then add the samequantity of very stiff vanilla-flavoured Chantilly cream.

Thoroughly cool these strawberries before serving them.

FRAISES CARDINAL

Set some fine, cooled strawberries in a timbale; coat them with

Melba sauce, or a purde of fresh raspberries, and sprinkle thelatter with splintered fresh almonds.

FRAISES ZELMA KUNTZ

Set some fine, cooled strawberries in a timbale. Cover themwith a raspberry purée, combined with an equal quantity ofChantilly cream.

Decorate, by means of the piping-bag, with Chantilly cream, and sprinkle with a powdered pralin of filberts.

Gooseberries (Groseilles vertes).

GOOSEBERRY FOOL

Poach one pound of green gooseberries in some thin syrup.When they are cooked, thoroughly drain them; rub them througha sieve, and collect the pur£e in a flat saucepan.

Work this pur£e on ice, and add the necessary amount of icingsugar to it.

The amount of the icing sugar varies according to the acidity ofthe fruit and the sweetness of the poaching-syrup.

Combine with the puree an equal quantity of very stiffly whippedcream; set the preparation in the shape of a dome in a timbale:decorate its surface, by means of a piping-bag, with Chantillycream, and serve very cold.

Tangerines (Mandarines).

MANDARINES ALMINA

Cut a slice of the rind from the stem-end of the tangerines bymeans of a round, even cutter, one inch in diameter. Then emptythem, and fill the rinds with a preparation of Bavarois with violets, combined with crumbled lady’s-finger biscuits, sprinkled withMaraschino. Close the tangerines with the slice cut off at thestart; let them set in a cool place, and, at the last moment, laythem on a dish covered with a folded napkin.

MANDARINES à la CREME

Empty the tangerines, and fill their peels with a somewhatthick tangerine Bavarois preparation, combined with a third of itsbulk of fresh, raw cream.

Place them in ice until they have to be served; dish them asdirected in the preceding recipe.

MANDARINES EN SURPRISE

Proceed as for the oranges, but for the orange ice sub-stitute tangerine jelly.

Oranges.

ORANGES au BLANC-MANGER

Cut the oranges and empty them as directed in the case oftangerines. Then fill them with French blanc-mange (№2625), and let it set. Close the oranges with the slices cut off at the start, and dish them on a napkin.

-GRANGES RUBANNEES

Garnish the empty orange-rinds with regular layers of vari-ously coloured and flavoured blanc-manges, or with alternated fruitjellies. When about to serve, quarter the oranges.

N.B.—These quartered oranges are sometimes used for thegarnishing of cold entremets.

ORANGES EN SURPRISE

Cut a lateral slice from each orange, representing about one-fourthof their height, and empty them. Garnish the peels with orange ice ;cover the latter with Italian meringue; set the garnished peelson broken ice, lying on a tray, and set them in a sufficiently hotoven, to quickly colour the meringue. On taking the oranges outof the oven, close each with the slices cut from them at the start, in which are stuck imitation leaves and stalks, made from pulledsugar. Dish them on a napkin.

ORANGES SOUFFLEES EN SURPRISE

Empty the oranges as above; garnish the rinds with an orangesoujffU preparation, and cook the latter.

On taking the oranges out of the oven, cover the soufftt withthe slices cut off at the start; dish the oranges on a napkin, andserve them instantly.

Peaches and Nectarines (Peches et Nectarines).

As nectarines may be prepared after the same recipes aspeaches, there is no need to give special recipes for the former.

PECHES AIGLON

After having peeled the peaches, poach them in a vanilla-flavoured syrup, and leave them to cool therein. Drain them, dish them upon a layer of vanilla ice-cream, spread in a false-bottomed silver timbale, the inner compartment of which containsbroken ice. Sprinkle crystallised violets over the peaches; setthe timbale on a block of ice, carved to represent an eagle, andcover the whole with a veil of spun sugar.

PECHES à l’AURORE

Poach the peeled peaches in a Kirsch-flavoured syrup, and letthem cool there. Drain them; dish them in a silver timbale, upon a layer of “iced mousse with strawberries,” and coat thewhole with a Curagoa-flavoured sab ay on.

PECHES ALEXANDRA

Poach the peaches in a vanilla-flavoured syrup and let themcompletely cool. Dish them in a timbale surrounded by ice

containing on its bottom a layer of vanilla ice-cream, covered witha strawberry purée. Sprinkle the peaches with white and redrose-petals, and veil the whole with spun sugar.

p£ches cardinal

Poach the peaches in vanilla-flavoured syrup, and, when theyare quite cold, dish them in a timbale. Cover them with a veryred, sweetened, raspberry purde, flavoured with Kirsch, andsprinkled with very white, splintered fresh almonds.

p£ches dame-blanche

Poach the peaches in vanilla-flavoured syrup. When they arecold, set them in a timbale upon a layer of vanilla ice-cream, covered with thin slices of pine-apple macerated in Maraschinoand Kirsch.

Between each peach, and in every crevice, put some balls ofChantilly cream, laid by means of a piping-bag, fitted with agrooved pipe.

PECHES MELBA

Poach the peaches in vanilla-flavoured syrup. Dish them in atimbale upon a layer of vanilla ice-cream, and coat them with araspberry purde.

PECHES PETIT-DUC

Prepare the peaches as under №2698, but use small heaps ofred-currant jelly instead of balls of cream.

PECHES à la SULTANE

Poach the peaches in vanilla-flavoured syrup, and let them cool.Dish them in a timbale upon a layer of pistachio ice, and coatthem with very cold, thickened syrup, flavoured with rose essence.

Veil the whole with spun sugar, and set the timbale upon ablock of ice.

PECHES au CHATEAU-LAFFITE

Scald the peaches; peel them, and cut them in two.

Poach them in sufficient Ch&teau-Laffite wine to cover them, and sugar the wine to the extent of ten oz. of sugar per bottle.

Leave them to cool in the syrup, and dish them in a silvertimbale.

Reduce the wine by three-quarters; thicken it with a littleraspberry-flavoured, red-currant jelly.

When this syrup is quite cold, sprinkle the peaches with it.

PECHES à l’IMPIs RATRICE

Cut the peaches in two; poach them in a vanilla-flavouredsyrup, and let them cool. Then drain and dry them; garnish thecut side of each of the half-peaches with enough vanilla ice-creamto give them the appearance of whole fruit. Coat the peach-sideof each with some stiff apricot sauce, and roll them in pralinedsplintered almonds.

Dish these peaches upon a cushion of GJnoise, saturated withKirsch and Maraschino, set upon a dry-paste base, and glazed withraspberry glaze.

Veil the whole with spun sugar.

PECHES ROSE-CHESRIPoach the peaches in vanilla-flavoured syrup, and let themcool. Dish them in a timbale; cover them with a purde of pine-apple with Clicquot, and serve very cold.

PECHES ROSE-POMPON

Scald and peel some fine peaches; poach them in vanilla-flavoured syrup, and let %them cool. Stone them without openingor breaking them overmuch, and in the place of the stone, putsome very firm vanilla ice-cream.

Set these reconstructed peaches in a silver timbale, upon alayer of raspberry ice; cover them with pralined Chantilly cream ;and before serving put them for thirty minutes in the refrigerator.

At the last moment, veil the timbale with pink, spun sugar.

Pears (Poires).

POIRES ALMA

Peel the pears and poach them in a syrup made from onequart of water, one-half pint of port wine, eight ounces of sugar, andthe blanched and chopped zest of an orange. Cool: dish themin a timbale; sprinkle them with powdered pralin, and serve aChantilly cream at the same time.

POIRES CARDINAL

Poach the pears in a vanilla-flavoured syrup, and then proceedas directed under №2697.

POIRES à la CARIGNAN

Evenly turn some very fine dessert pears, and cook them in avanilla-flavoured syrup; keeping them fairly firm. Drain them ona dish and let them cool. This done, trim them flat at their base, and empty them from underneath by means of a root spoon, afterhaving outlined the circumference of the opening with an evenround cutter.

Fill them with a preparation of “Bombe au chocolat pralin£”(see Bombe, No 2826).

Close them up with a little roundel of G/noise, stamped out bymeans of the same cutter as that used above.

Set the pears on a tray; coat them speedily with apricot jamcooked to the small-thread stage; glaze them with chocolatefondant, and keep them for three hours in a very cold refrigerator.Meanwhile, prepare as many small GJnoise squares as there arepears; and make them one-quarter inch wider than the diameter ofthe pears. Saturate these square bases with Anisette, and by meansof a little apricot jam cooked to the small-thread stage, stick eachof them on to very thin, dry-paste bases of the same size. Coatthese prepared bases with the same apricot jam, and garnish themall round, as also their uncovered corners, with pralined splinteredalmonds.

When about to serve, take the pears out of the refrigerator, setthem on these bases: stick into each a stalk and a leaf, made frompulled sugar; and dish on a napkin.

N.B.—Each pear should be cut vertically into two, three, or fourpieces, subject to its size.

POIRES FELICIA

Poach some quartered William pears in vanilla-flavoured syrupand let them cool. Cook also, in a pink syrup, some very smallhalved pears.

Dish the quarters in the middle of a border of Viennese cream(№2641) laid out upon a dish. Cover them with a pyramid ofvanilla-flavoured Chantilly cream, and sprinkle its surface withcrushed, red pralines.

Surround the cream border with the pink half-pears.

POIRES à la FLORENTINE

Fill an oiled border-mould with a semolina Bavarois prepara-tion, and let it set. Turn it out at the last moment, and garnishthe middle of the border with stewed pears, cohered by means of avanilla-flavoured apricot pur£e.

POIRES HEiLENE

Poach the pears in vanilla-flavoured syrup and let them cool.

When about to serve, dish them in a timbale upon a layer ofvanilla ice-cream, sprinkled with crystallised violets.

Serve a hot, chocolate sauce separately.

POIRES MARQUISE

Cook the pears in a vanilla-flavoured syrup, and drain themthaJ: they may cool. This done, coat them again and again with

some very stiff raspberry-flavoured red-currant jelly, and sprinklethem instantly with chopped, burnt almonds.

Set the pears on a “Diplomatic Pudding,” made in a manquemould, and turned out on a round dish. Surround the base of thepudding with a border of apple-jelly croutons, neatly cut totriangular shapes.

POIRES MARY-GARDEN

Cook the pears in syrup; cool them, and dish them on atimbale, upon a Melba sauce, combined with half-sugared cherries, softened in tepid water for a few minutes.

Decorate the pears with Chantilly cream.

POIRES MELBA

Poach the pears in a vanilla-flavoured syrup, and proceed asdirected under №2699.

POIRES PRALINEES

Stew the pears and let them cool. Set them in a timbale, andcoat with some Frangipan cream, thinned by means of a little rawcream.

Between each pear, set a well-moulded tablespoonful of Chan-tilly cream, and cover the whole with concassed-almond pralin.

Serve a cold or hot chocolate sauce at the same time.

POIRES à la RELIGIEUSE

Stew the pears in a vanilla-flavoured syrup; cool them, anddish them in a shallow porcelain timbale equal in depth to the lengthof the pears.

Cover them with a somewhat thin chocolate Bavarois pre-paration, and place the whole for two hours in the refrigeratorbefore serving.

POIRES au RHUM

Stew the pears and set them in a timbale.

Thicken the syrup with arrowroot, colour it faintly with pink ;flavour it with rum; pour it over the pears, and let them cool.

N.B.—These pears may also be served hot, after the samerecipe; except that the rum is poured over the pears, hot, at thelast moment, and set alight at the table.

POIRES à la REINE EMMA

Mould a Flamri preparation in an even border-mould, decor-ated with candied fruit. Set this to poach, and, when it is cold, turn it out on a round dish.

In the middle set a pyramid of quartered pears, stewed in avanilla-flavoured syrup; coat the quarters with Frangipan cream,

combined with a quarter of its bulk of crushed, dry macaroons, and with double its volume of very stiff Chantilly cream.

Decorate the top, by means of a piping-bag, with Chantillycream; and serve some Kirsch-flavoured apricot sauce separately.

Apples.

POMMES à la ROYALE

Peel some small apples, core them by means of a tube-cutter, and poach them in vanilla-flavoured syrup. When they are quitecold, coat them with red-currant jelly, and dish them in a circle, each upon a tartlet of blanc-mange. Garnish their midst withchopped Maraschino jelly.

Various Cold Sweets (Entremets).

BISCUIT à la REINE

Cook, in a manqud mould, a Savoy-biscuit preparation, and letit cool.

With a little apricot jam, cooked to the small-thread stage, stick this biscuit on a dry-paste base; saturate it with cold syrup, flavoured with Kiimmel, and by means of a piping-bag decorateit all round and on its edges with royale icing.

Turn out upon it a Bavarois with Maraschino, moulded in aRichelieu mould of proportionate size.

croCjte a la mexicaine

Cut some slices three inches long by one-third inch thickfrom a stale Genoise. Coat them with a Condd pralin, and drythem in a moderate oven.

Set these croutes in a crown on a round dish, and garnish theirmidst with a rocky pyramid of plombiere ice, projecting abovethem.

DIPLOMATE aux FRUITS

Prepare (1) a base of Genoise with fruit, glazed with apricotjam, cooked to the small-thread stage; (2) a Bavarois with fruits.

Turn out the latter upon the former, and surround the wholewith stewed fruit of the same kind as those used for the Bavarois.

ILE FLOTIANTE

Take a stale Savoy biscuit, and cut it into thin slices.

Saturate the latter with Kirsch and Maraschino, coat themwith apricot jam, and sprinkle the latter with currants andchopped almonds. Put the slices one upon the other, in suchwise

as to reconstruct the biscuit, and coat the latter with a layer ofsweetened and vanilla-flavoured Chantilly cream.

Sprinkle the cream with splintered pistachios and currants;set the whole on a tazza, and surround it with vanilla-flavouredEnglish custard, or raspberry syrup.

MILK JUNKET

Gently heat one quart of milk. When it has reached 95°F. takeit off the fire; add two and one-half oz. of sugar to it; flavour it asfancy may suggest; put into it six drops of russet-apple essence(or two pastils of russet-apple essence, dissolved in six drops ofwater); pour it into a timbale, and serve it very cold.

N.B.—This very delicate and simple entremet is little else, in-deed, than flavoured and sweetened milk, caused to set by thecombined agencies of heat and russet-apple essence.

MACEDOINE of COOLED FRUIT

Take some fresh fruit of the season, such as ripe Williampears and peaches, peeled and sliced apricots and bananas, andadd to it some small or large strawberries, raspberries, white-and red-currants; skinned, fresh almonds, &c.

Set these fruits in a timbale surrounded by ice, mixing themwell together; sprinkle them with a syrup at 30° (saccharom.), flavoured with Kirsch or Maraschino, and let them macerate foran hour or two; taking care to toss them from time to time.

EUGENIA: ITALIAN CREAM

Select some very ripe Eugenia; peel, slice, and set to maceratein a bowl, with Maraschino-flavoured syrup.

Set the fruit in a timbale, upon a layer of vanilla ice-cream ;decorate them on top with Chantilly cream, and sprinkle thelatter with crystallised violets.

MARQUISE ALICE

Prepare a /ra/z>z-flavoured Bavarois in a manque mould:garnish the inside with lady’s-finger biscuits, saturated withAnisette.

Turn it out on a dish, and completely cover it with an evencoat of very stiff, sweetened and vanilla-flavoured Chantillycream.

On top, lay some parallel lines of red-currant jelly, by meansof the piping-bag; and then cut these lines at right angles, withthe point of a small knife. Surround the base with small puff-paste triangles, coated with “Pralin a Condd" dried in the oven.

74

MELON à l’ORIENTALE

Take a melon that is just ripe; make a circular incision roundits stalk, and remove the resulting bung, Get rid of the seeds andwithdraw the pulp by means of a silver spoon. Cut the pulp intodice.

Copiously sprinkle the inside of the melon with icing-sugarand fill it up with wild strawberries and the pulp dice, spread inalternate layers, sprinkled with sugar. Complete with one-sixthpint of Kirsch; close the melon with the excised bung, seal the jointwith a thread of butter, and keep the melon in the cool for twohours.

Dish it on a napkin, and serve gaufrettes at the same time.

MELON FRAPPE

Select two very ripe, medium-sized melons, and, with the entirepulp of one of them, cleared of all the rind and seeds and rubbedthrough tammy, prepare a Granite after №2930.

Cut the other melon round the stalk and open it. Completelyremove the seeds; and, by means of a silver spoon, withdraw thepulp piecemeal, and set it to macerate on ice with a little sugar andone of the following wines or liqueurs: Port, Curagoa, Rum, Kirschor Maraschino.

Keep the emptied rind for thirty minutes in a refrigerator.

When about to serve, set the emptied melon on a small block offancifully carved ice, and fill it up with the Granitd and the maceratedpulp spread in alternate layers. When the melon is full, return theexcised bung to its place.

N.B.—This melon is served, by means of a spoon, upon icedplates, and it often takes the place of ices at the end of a dinner.

MELON EN SURPRISE

Empty the melon as above, and fill it with a macedoine of freshfruits, combined with the withdrawn pulp of the melon, cut into diceand cohered with a sugared and Kirsch-flavoured purde of wildstrawberries.

Close the melon and keep it in the refrigerator for two hours.

GARNISHED MERINGUES

Join the meringue shells together in couples, by means of somestiff sugared and flavoured Chantilly cream or with some sort of ice, and dish them on a napkin.

MONT-BLANC aux FRAISES

Add some small wild strawberries macerated in cold, vanilla-flavoured syrup and drained, to some very stiff Chantilly cream; theproportions being *four oz. of the former per quart of the latter.

Dish in the shape of a dome; surround the base with large straw-berries, rolled in beaten egg-whites and then in semolina sugar, anddecorate the surface with large and very red half-strawberries.

MONT=BLANC aux MARRONS

Cook some chestnuts in sweetened and vanilla-flavoured milkand rub them through a sieve, over an overturned, even border-mould; in order that the chestnut puree, falling in the form ofvermicelli, may garnish the mould naturally.

Fill up the mould with the pured that has fallen over the sidesof the mould; turn out the border on a dish, and in the midst setan irregular and jagged mound of sugared and vanilla-flavouredChantilly cream.

MONT-ROSE

Prepare a Charlotte, Plombiere in a shallow Madeleine ice-mould.

Having turned out the Charlotte on a dish, cover it on top withtablespoonfuls of Chantilly cream, combined with a puree of freshraspberries, and so shaped as to imitate a pyramidic rock.

(HUFS à la NEIGE

Mould some ordinary meringue, by means of a spoon, to repre-sent eggs; and drop the mouldings into a saut^pan containing someboiling sugared and vanilla-flavoured milk. Turn the meringues overin the milk, that they may poach evenly, and, as soon as they arefirm, drain them in a sieve.

Strain the milk through muslin; add six egg yolks, and with itprepare an English custard.

Set the egg-shaped meringues on a tazza and cover them withthe prepared custard, kept very cold.

MOULDED CEUFS à la NEIGE

Prepare the meringues and the English custard as above; butto the latter add five or six gelatine leaves soaked in cold water.Set the egg-shaped meringues in an oiled border-mould; cover themwith the very cold custard, which, however, should not have set;and let the preparation set in the cool, or surrounded by ice.

MOUSSELINES D’OEUFS rejane

By means of a piping-bag, fitted with an even pipe, lay someordinary meringues upon sheets of white paper, in shapes resemblinglarge macaroons.

Slip the sheets of paper into boiling, sugared and vanilla-flavoured milk, and withdraw the sheets of paper as soon as the

3 E

meringues sever from them. Complete the poaching of the meringues, and drain them.

Set these meringues, two by two, in silver or porcelain egg-dishes ;place a fine, poached half apricot in the middle of each, and coverthe whole with a few teaspoonfuls of English custard.

MOUSSELINE of EGGS, MIMI

This is a preparation of ordinary Italian meringue, poached in abain-marie, in a caramel-clothed mould. Let the contents get quitecold before turning out, and serve some stewed, fresh fruit and anEnglish custard separately.

RICE à l’IMPERATRICE

Make a vanilla-flavoured preparation of rice for entremets, using the quantities of milk and sugar already prescribed. Whenthe rice is cooked, and somewhat cold, add to it four oz. ot ajilptcon of candied fruit and four tablespoonfuls of apricot jam, perone-half lb. of raw rice. Then combine with it an equal quantity ofKirsch-flavoured Bavarois preparation, or one pint of thick Englishcustard and one pint of whipped cream.

Let a layer of red-currant jelly set upon the bottom of a Bavaroismould; then pour the above preparation into the latter and let thewhole set, either in the cool or surrounded by ice.

When about to serve, turn out on a napkin.

RICE à la MALTAISE

Prepare the rice with milk as above, but flavour it with orangerind, and omit the apricot jam and the candied fruit salpicon.Combine with it an equal quantity of orange Bavarois preparation;pour the whole into a dome-mould, and let it set on ice. Whenabout to serve, turn out upon a round dish, and cover it withalternate rows of orange-sections, skinned raw and macerated in asyrup flavoured with orange-rind.

SUEDOISE of FRUIT

As I mentioned in my remarks upon the preparation of jellies, a Su^doise of fruit is a jelly moulded in an aspic mould andgarnished with layers of stewed fruit, the colours and kindsof which should be contrasted as much as possible.

FRAISALIA TIMBALE

Prepare a timbale of Savarin paste in a Charlotte mould.

When it is baked and cooled, remove the crumb from its insideleaving a thickness of half an inch on its bottom and sides; smear itthinly with Kirsch-flavoured syrup, and return the timbale to themould.

ENTREMETS

Now garnish it with alternate layers of vanilla-flavoured, Bavarois preparation and wild strawberries, macerated in Kirsch.Let it set in the cool, or surround the mould with ice. Turn outthe timbale first upon a plate; overturn it on a dish, and upon itset a pyramid of vanilla-flavoured Chantilly cream. Stud the latterall over with small, very red strawberries, or garnish it with largehalf-strawberries.

Surround the timbale with fine dice of strawberry jelly.

TIVOLI aux FRAISES

Clothe an ornamented mould, fitted with a central tube, with athick coat of very clear, Kirsch-flavoured jelly. Fill the mouldwith a Bavarois preparation, combined with plenty of wild straw-berry puree, and let its contents set. Turn it out, when about toserve, and surround it with very clear, chopped, Kirsch-flavouredjelly.

Chapter XXI Ices

Ices, with their accompanying “petits fours”, bring the dinner to a close—at least as far as Cookery is concerned; and, when they are well prepared and daintily dished, they are the consummation of all that is delicate and good. In no other department of the work has the culinary artist so freely indulged his fancy, or created such delectable kickshaws; and, though Italy be the cradle of the ice-worker’s art, though the Neapolitans have deservedly maintained their reputation as authorities in this matter, to French workmen, certainly, is due the credit of those innovations which have perfected this important branch of dietetic science.

The Making of Ices

Whatever be the kind of ices required, they should always be prepared in advance; for none of these preparations can be made reaiy at a moment’s notice.

There are two distinct operations in the confection of ices:—

The making of the preparation.
The freezing and the moulding of the preparation. I shall begin by dealing with the second operation, which remains the same for all ices, and is the essential part of the procedure.

To freeze an ice preparation is to surround it with broken ice, mixed with sodium chloride (sea-salt or freezing salt) and saltpetre. The action of these two salts upon the ice causes a considerable drop in the temperature, which speedily congeals any contiguous liquid. Subject to their nature, ices are either moulded and frozen directly in their moulds, like the light ices: iced Biscuits, iced Soufflés, Puddings, Mottsses, Parfaits, Bombes, &c.; or first frozen in a special utensil called a freezer, and then moulded and frozen afresh. Cream and syrup ices are prepared by the second method; and this I shall now describe.

The freezers, in which the freezing takes place, are generally wielded by hand, either directly or by means of some mechanism. They should be of pure tin, and fitted, at their base, on to a central pivot which turns in a socket, fixed in the wooden case which holds the freezer.

Having hermetically closed the latter, surround it with broken ice containing three lbs. of salt and eight oz. of saltpetre per twenty-five lbs.

The freezer should be one-third of its height out of the ice, in order that no particle of salted ice may accidentally fall into the preparation while it is being frozen. The ice should be snugly massed, by means of a special pestle, round the freezer. This operation constitutes the packing, and should be effected at least ten minutes in advance if possible.

Having thus prepared the freezer, pour into it the preparation to be frozen and then either keep it in motion by rocking the utensil to and fro, by grasping the handle on the cover (if the apparatus is worked by hand), or by turning the handle if the utensil is on a central axle, fitted with the usual mechanism. In either case, the rotary movement of the utensil causes the preparation to splash continually against the sides of the freezer, where it rapidly congeals, and the congealed portions are removed by means of a special spatula, as quickly as they form, until the whole becomes a smooth and homogeneous mass. The delicacy and creaminess of the ice depend a great deal upon the care with which this freezing operation is effected; hence the preference which is now given to freezers fitted with a mechanism whereby two fans revolve inside in a direction opposite to that of the body of the machine, and thus not only detach the congealed portions of the preparation under treatment from the sides of the receptacle, but also work it with a regularity impossible to human motion.

The Moulding of Ices

Having thus frozen the preparation, it may now be set in rock-form on a napkin, as it used sometimes to be served in the past, or in glasses. But as a rule it is put into special moulds, having closely-fitting covers. These moulds should be carefully filled, and banged on a folded napkin, that the ice may settle and drive out any air which might be the cause of holes being found in the preparation. When it is filled, place the mould in a receptacle of a suitable size, and surround it with broken ice, prepared as for the packing. The mould should remain at least an hour in the ice,in the case of an ordinary ice, and an extra two hours if the ice be light and not previously frozen as are the Bombes.

When about to serve, take the mould out of the ice; wash it to rid it of the taint of salt; dip it in tepid water for an instant, that the surface of the preparation inside may melt and separate easily from the mould. Overturn the mould; and turn out the ice upon a folded napkin lying on a dish.

Preparations for Simple Ices

Preparations for simple ices are of two kinds: those made from cream, and those made from syrup; the latter being principally used for fruit ices.

As the quantities of sugar and eggs used for these preparations vary exceedingly, the following recipes have been based upon a working average.

If creamier ices be required, all that is needed is an increase in the sugar and egg-yolks per quart of milk while, if the ices be; required harder but less creamy, the two ingredients above mentioned should be proportionately reduced.

As an example of the difference that may exist between cream preparations, I might instance the case of ice-cream, which may be made from seven to sixteen egg-yolks, and six oz. to one lb. of sugar per quart of milk. In regard to ices made from syrups and fruit, their preparations may measure from 15° to 30° or 32°. (saccharometer) respectively.

Ice-cream Preparations (Generic Recipe)

Work two-thirds lb. of sugar and ten egg-yolks in a saucepan until the mixture reaches the ribbon-stage. Dilute it, little by little, with one quart of boiling milk, and stir over a moderate fire until the preparation veneers the withdrawn spoon. Avoid boiling, as it might decompose the custard.

Strain the whole into a basin and stir it from time to time until it is quite cold.

N.B.—For the various ice-cream preparations, the amount of sugar and number of egg-yolks, as also the procedure, do not change. They are only distinguishable by the particular flavour or infusion which may happen to characterise them.

Various Ice-Cream Preparations

Almond Ice-cream

Finely pound three and a half oz. of freshly-skinned sweet almonds and five bitter almonds; adding to them, little by little, in order to facilitate the pounding, a few tablespoonfuls of water.

Set this almond paste to infuse, twenty minutes beforehand, in the boiling milk, and prepare the cream as directed above, with the same quantities of sugar and egg-yolks.

Asparagus Ice-cream

Parboil six oz. of asparagus-tops or sprew for two minutes. Thoroughly drain them quickly pound them, together with a few; tablespoonfuls of milk, and set this asparagus paste to infuse in the boiled milk.

Filbert Ice-cream

Slightly torrify three and half oz. of filberts; finely pound them, together with a few tablespoonfuls of milk, and set the resulting paste to infuse for twenty minutes in the boiled milk.

Coffee Ice-cream

Add two oz. of freshly-grilled and crushed coffee seeds to the boiled milk, and let them infuse for twenty minutes.

Or, with an equivalent amount of ground coffee and half a pint of water, prepare a very strong infusion and add it to one and a half pints of boiled milk.

Chocolate Ice-cream

Dissolve eight oz. of grated chocolate in half pint of water, and add thereto one quart of boiled milk, in which a large stick of vanilla has previously been infused. For this preparation, eight oz. of sugar and seven egg-yolks will be found sufficient, if the chocolate used be sweet.

Walnut Ice-cream

Finely pound three and a half oz. of well-peeled walnuts with a few tablespoonfuls of water, and set them to infuse for twenty minutes in boiling milk.

Pistachio Ice-cream

Pound two oz. of sweet almonds, and two and a half oz. of freshly-peeled pistachios; moistening them with a few drops of milk. Set the paste to infuse for twenty minutes in the boiled milk.

Pralined Ice-cream

Pound and rub through a sieve fouroz. of almond pralin, and add thereto one quart of previously-prepared vanilla-flavoured custard.

Tea Ice-cream

Add one pint of very strong tea to one and a half pints of boiled milk, and make the preparation in the usual way.

Vanilla Ice-cream

When the milk has boiled, infuse in it one large stick of vanilla for twenty minutes.

N.B.—If these various preparations be required more creamy, the milk may be wholly or partly replaced by fresh cream. Also when the preparation is congealed, it may be combined with one sixth pint of whipped cream per quart.

Preparations for Fruit Ices

The base of these preparations is a syrup of sugar at 32° (saccharom.), to which a purée of fruit, an essence, or a liqueur is added, which will give the ice its character. All these preparations require lemon juice, the quantity of which varies according to the acidity of the fruit used, but which, even in the case of the tartest fruits, should not measure less than the amount that maybe extracted from a whole lemon per quart of the preparation.

Orange juice may also be used, more especially for red-fruit ices; while the juices of the orange and the lemons combined throw the flavour of the fruit under-treatment into remarkable relief.

In the season the juices are extracted from fresh fruit, pressed and rubbed through tammy. When the season is over the preserved juice of fruit is used.

All red-fruit ices are improved, once they are set, by an addition of half pint of raw, fresh cream per quart of the preparation.

The Making of Fruit Ice Preparations

These preparations are made in two ways as follows:—

Rub the fruit through a fine sieve, after having pounded it if its nature admit of it. Dilute the purée with an equal quantity of cold sugar syrup at 32° (saccharom.), and add lemon juice in a quantity subject to the acidity of the treated fruit.

This mixture of ingredients should always be cold, and should be tested with the hydrometer. If the instrument marks morethan the proper degree, dilute the preparation with a little water; if it mark less, add syrup until the required degree is reached.

Pound the fruit with an average quantity of ten oz. of sugar per lb.; but remember that this proportion may be modified either way, subject to the sweetness of the fruit used.

Rub the whole through a sieve; and then, to obtain the proper degree of strength, add the necessary quantity of filtered water.

Liqueur-ice Preparations

These preparations are made by adding to the syrup or the cream which forms, the base of the, ice a given quantity of the selected liqueur, the latter being generally added when the preparation is cold.

The proportion of one-fifth pint of liqueur per quart of syrup may be taken as an average. Subject to the requirements this liqueur flavour may be intensified with strong tea for rum ices: with orange-rind for Curaçao-flavoured ices, with fresh, crushed cherry-stones for Kirsch ices, &c.

These preparations should always contain some lemon-juice, and their strength should reach the average degree indicated for fruit ices.

Various Fruit-Ice Preparations

Apricot Ice

Take one pint of fresh apricot purée, one pint of syrup, and the juice of two lemons. The strength of the preparation should measure 18° or 19° (saccharometer).

Pineapple Ice

Set to macerate for two hours one pint of grated or pounded skinned pineapple in one pint of syrup. Rub the whole through a sieve, add the juice of one lemon and a few drops of Kirsch, and test the preparation, which should measure from 18° to 20°.

Banana Ice

Set one pint of pounded banana pulp to macerate for two hours in one pint of Maraschino-flavoured syrup. Add the juice of three lemons, and rub through a sieve. This preparation should measure from 20° to 21°.

Cherry Ice

Crush one pint of stoned cherries, and pound their stones. Set the whole to macerate for one hour in one pint of syrup, flavoured with Kirsch. Rub through a sieve and add the juice of a half-lemon. The preparation should measure 21°.

Lemon Ice

Set the zests of three lemon peels to infuse for three hours in one pint of cold syrup. Add the juice of four lemons and of two oranges, and strain the whole. The preparation should measure 22°.

Strawberry Ice

Mix one pint of strawberry purée with one pint of syrup, and add thereto the juice of two oranges and of two lemons. Or pound two lbs. of strawberries with one lb. of powdered sugar; add the juice of oranges and lemons as above; rub the whole through a sieve, and add the necessary amount of filtered water to bring the preparation to 16° or 18°.

Raspberry Ice

Proceed as for №2766, and use the same quantities.

Red-currant Ice

Mix one pint of red-currant juice witli one pint of syrup. In view of the natural acidity of the fruit, lemon-juice may be dispensed with. The preparation should measure 20°.

Tangerine Ice

Throw the zests of the rinds of four tangerines into one and one-half pints of boiling syrup. Let the whole cool; rub it through a sieve, and finish it with the juice of six tangerines, two oranges and one lemon. The preparation should measure 21°.

Melon Ice

Mix one pint of very ripe melon pulp with one pint of syrup, the juice of two oranges and one lemon, and one tablespoonful of orange-flower water. Rub the whole through a sieve. The mixture should measure 22°.

Orange Ice

Throw the zests of the rinds of four oranges into one quart of boiling syrup. Let the whole cool; add the juice of four oranges and one lemon, and rub it through a sieve. It should measure 21°.

Peach Ice

Proceed as for №2761, using wall peaches if possible.

Pear Ice

Peel, core, and pound some fine William pears, with one lb. of powdered sugar per two-thirds lb. of the fruit; and add thereto the juice of two lemons per lb. of pears. Rub the whole through a sieve, and add enough filtered water to bring it to 22°.

Plum Ice

Proceed as for №2761, bringing the preparation to 20°.

Grape Ice

Add to one and one-half pints of the juice of sweet, pressed grapes, the juice of three lemons and the necessary quantity of powdered sugar to bring the preparation to 20°. Rub the whole through a sieve.

Violet Ice

Put half a lb. of cleaned violet petals into one and one-half pints of boiling syrup. Let them infuse for ten minute; strain the whole through a sieve; let it cool, and finish it with the juice of three lemons. The preparation should measure from 20° to 21°.

Various Ices

Glace Alhambra

Take a Madeleine-mould; clothe its bottom and sides with vanilla ice-cream and fill it with Chantilly cream, combined with fresh strawberries, macerated for two hours in Kümmel, which should afterwards be added to the Chantilly cream.

Glace Carmen

Take a fluted mould. Garnish it with vertical and alternate layers of raspberry ice, coffee ice, and vanilla ice-cream.

Glace Comtesse Marie

Take a special square mould, even or ornamented on the top. Clothe it with strawberry ice; fill it with vanilla ice-cream; and, after turning it out, decorate it, by means of a piping-bag (fitted with a grooved pipe), with vanilla ice-cream..

Glace Coucher de Soleil

Select one pound of fine very ripe strawberries, and put them in a silver timbale. Sprinkle them with ten ounces of powdered sugar and one liqueur-glass full of Grand-Marnier liqueur cover the timbale and keep it on ice for half an hour.

Then rub the strawberries through a sieve; and, with their purée, make a preparation after the directions given under Fruit Ices. Freeze this preparation in the freezer, and, when it is set, combine with it one pint of Chantilly cream. Now cover the freezer; surround it afresh with ice if necessary, and keep it thus for thirty-five to forty minutes. This done, dish the ice preparation with care in pyramid form in crystal bowls.

N.B.—This ice gets its name from its colour, which should be that of the western sky during a fine sunset.

Glace Dame-Jeanne

Take a Madeleine-mould; clothe it with vanilla ice-cream, and fill it with Chantilly cream, combined with pralined orange flowers.

Glace Dora

Take a Madeleine-mould clothe it with vanilla ice-cream, and fill it with Kirsch-flavoured Chantilly cream combined with pineapple dice and Bar red-currant jam.

Glace Étoile du Berger

Take a star-shaped mould, or a Madeleine-mould with a star on its bottom. Clothe it with raspberry ice, and fill it with Benedictine flavoured Mousse.

Turn it out upon a regular disc, consisting of a thick layer of white spun sugar, lying on a dish. This spun sugar throws the ice into relief, and emits rays which dart out from between the points of the star.

Glace Fleurette

Take a square mould. Garnish it with strawberry and pineapple ice, laid in very regular, superposed layers. After turning it out decorate with lemon ice.

Glace Francillon

Take a square mould; clothe it with coffee ice, and fill it with liqueur-brandy ice.

Fromage Glacé

These ices are made in fluted moulds, and generally with two differently flavoured and coloured ices, set vertically in the mould.

Glace des Gourmets

Take a “bombe” mould. Clothe it with pralined, vanilla-ice cream. Fill it with alternate layers of chestnut ice flavoured with rum, and vanilla-flavoured Chantilly cream. When the ice is turned out, roll it in pralined splintered almonds.

Moulded Ices

These ices are made in large or small moulds.

The large ices are moulded in tin moulds, fitted with hinged covers, and ornamented with some design. The small ones, which are generally served at evening parties, or are used to garnish larger ices, are made in similar moulds, shaped like flowers, fruit, birds, leaf-sprays, &c.

Any ice preparation may be used for these ices; but, as a rule, the preparation should have something in keeping with the design of the mould used.

Small moulded ices may be kept packed until they are served. They may also be turned out in advance and kept in the refrigerator.

Glace des Iles

Take a Madeleine-mould; clothe it with vanilla ice-cream, and fill it with pineapple ice.

Glace des Iles

Take a Madeleine-mould. Fill it with vanilla ice-cream, combined with half its bulk of Chantilly cream and candied fruit, macerated in Kirsch.

Mandarines Glacées

Cut the tangerines on top, with a round, even cutter, in such- wise as to remove a roundel of their peel with the stalk attached, and two leaves adhering thereto.

With the juice of the tangerines prepare some tangerine ice, after the directions given under Fruit-ice Preparations. Fill the tangerines with this ice; cover them with the roundels removed at the start; and, with a brush, sprinkle the rinds of the fruit with water, and place them in a refrigerator.

As soon as the tangerines are coated with frost, serve them on a napkin.

Mandarines Glacées aux Perles des Alpes

Empty the tangerines as above, and garnish them inside with tangerine mousse, with which Chartreuse bon-bons have been mixed. Cover them, and frost them as directed above.

Glace Marie-Thiérèse

Take a Madeleine-mould; clothe it with chocolate ice, and fill it with vanilla-flavoured Chantilly cream.

After turning out, decorate it with pineapple ice.

Meringues Glacées

Garnish some meringue shells with some kind of spoon-moulded ice, and set them on a napkin.

Or, garnish the shells more sparingly and join them together in twos.

Glace Plombière

Take a parfait mould. Garnish it with vanilla-ice cream, combined with candied fruit, macerated in Kirsch; spreading the preparation in alternate layers with apricot jam.

Coupes

We are now concerned with bowls garnished, either with differently-flavoured ices, or with ices combined with Chantilly cream or candied fruit. The bowls used for this purpose should be of crystal.

Coupes d’Antigny

Three-parts fill the bowls with Alpine-strawberry ice, or, failing this, four-seasons strawberry ice, combined with very light and strongly-flavoured raw cream. The two most perfect examples of this cream are the “Fleurette Normande”, and that which in they South of France is called “Creme Niçoise”, and which comes from Alpine pastures.

Upon the ice of each bowl set a half-peach, poached in vanilla-flavoured syrup; and veil the whole thinly with spun sugar.

Coupes Clo-clo

Garnish the bottom of the bowls with vanilla-ice cream, combined with fragments of candied chestnuts, macerated in Maraschino. Setacandiedchestnutinthemiddleoftheice,and surround it by means of a piping-bag with a border of Chantilly cream, containing strawberry purée.

Coupes Dame Blanche

Three-parts garnish the bowls with almond-milk ice. Upon the ice in each bowl set an overturned half-peach, poached in vanilla-flavoured syrup, the hollow of which should be filled with Bar red-currant jam. Surround the peaches with a thread of lemon ice, laid by means of a piping-bag.

Coupes Denise

Garnish the bowls with Moka ice, and sprinkle the latter with sweets containing liqueur (preferably rum). Cover with Chantilly cream laid on by means of the spoon.

Coupes Edna May

Garnish the bottom of the bowls with vanilla ice-cream, and upon the latter set some very cold stewed cherries. Cover the latter with a cone of Chantilly cream, tinted pink by means of a fresh raspberry purée.

Coupes Elizabeth

These coupes do not contain ice. They are garnished with very cold stewed choice bigaroon cherries, poached in a Kirsch- and cherry-brandy–flavoured syrup. The fruit is covered with Chantilly cream which is laid on by means of a spoon, and sprinkled with powdered spices in which cinnamon should predominate.

Coupes Emma Calve

Garnish the bottom of the bowls with pralined vanilla ice-cream. Upon the latter set som eKirsch-flavoured stewed cherries, and cover the latter with raspberry purée.

Coupes Eugénie

Garnish the bowls with vanilla ice-cream, combined with broken candied chestnuts. Cover the ice with Chantilly cream and upon the latter sprinkle some crystallised violets.

Coupes à las Favourite

Garnish the bowls vertically, half with Kirsch-Maraschino–flavoured ice, and half with vanilla ice-cream. Border them with a thread of pineapple ice, and in the middle set some Chantilly cream combined with strawberry purée.

Coupes Germaine

Garnish the bottom of the bowls with vanilla ice, and distribute over it half-sugared cherries, macerated in Kirsch. Cover the cherries with a dry purée of chestnuts, squeezed out to resemble vermicelli, and border the bowls with Chantilly cream.

Coupes Gressac

Garnish the bottom of the bowls with vanilla ice-cream, and upon the latter in each bowl set three small macaroons, saturated with Kirsch. Upon the macaroons set an overturned poached half-peach, the hollow of which should be garnished with Bar red- currant jam. Surround the peaches with a border of Chantilly cream.

Coupes Jacques

Garnish the bowls vertically, half with lemon and half with strawberry ice. Between the two ices, on top of the bowl, set a tablespoonful of a macedoine of fresh fruit, macerated in Kirsch.

Coupes à la Malmaison

Garnish the bowls with vanilla ice-cream, combined with peeled Muscadel grapes. Veil with spun sugar.

Coupes à la Mexicane

Garnish the bowls with tangerine ice, combined with pineapple cut into very small dice.

Coupes Mireille

Garnish the bowls, half with vanilla ice-cream, and half with red-currant ice with cream. In the middle of each bowl set a nectarine poached in vanilla-flavoured syrup, the stone of which should be replaced by Bar white-currant jam.

Decorate with Chantilly cream, and cover with a veil of spun sugar.

Coupes Petit Duc

Garnish the bowls with vanilla ice-cream. Set in each a poached half-peach garnished with Bar red-currant jam. Surround the peaches with a thread of lemon ice.

Coupes Rêve de Bébé

Garnish the bowls, half with pineapple ice and half with raspberry ice.

Between the two ices set a line of small strawberries, macerated in orange juice. Border the bowls with Chantilly cream, and sprinkle the latter with crystallised violets.

Coupes Madame Sans-Gêne

Garnish the bottom and sides of the bowls with a layer of vanilla ice-cream. Fill them with Bar red-currant jam, and cover the latter, by means of a spoon, with Chantilly cream.

Coupes Tutti-Frutti

Sprinkle the bottom of the bowls with various fresh fruits cut into dice garnish the bowls with strawberry, pineapple and; lemon ices, spread alternately with layers of the same fruits.

Coupes Vénus

Half-fill the bowls with vanilla ice-cream.

In the middle of each bowl set a small peach, poached in vanilla-flavoured syrup, with a very red, small cherry upon it.

Border the peaches with a thread of Chantilly cream.

Light Ices

These ices differ from those dealt with above, in that they are moulded and frozen directly, without a sojourn in the freezer.

To this class belong the ices most commonly served and the best; and, since their preparation requires no special utensils, they may be served everywhere: such are the “Iced Biscuits”, the “Bombes”, the “Mousses”, the “Parfaits”, the “Puddings”, and the “Iced Souffles”.

These different kinds of ices greatly resemble one another, and their names, which are puzzling at times, are only a matter of fancy.

Various Preparations

The old iced-biscuit preparation consisted of an English custard, prepared from one lb. of sugar, twelve egg-yolks, and one pint of milk.

When the custard was cooked, it used to be strained into a basin, left to cool (being fanned the while), and then placed upon ice, and finished with the whisk. Originally this cream was moulded at this stage; but now it is customary to add one quart of whipped cream to it; which operation renders the recipe more like that of a Bombe, which, in its turn, resembles that of the preparation for Mousses.

Iced biscuits

Preparation for Iced Biscuits

Whisk in a copper basin, in a bain-marie, twelve egg-yolks and one lb. of powdered sugar, until the paste gets very firm and reaches the ribbon-stage.

Take the basin off the fire, and whisk until the whole is quite cold. Then, add eight oz. of Italian meringue and one pint of whisked cream.

The Moulding of Iced Biscuits

Whisk in a copper basin, in a bain-marie, twelve egg-yolks and one lb. of powdered sugar, until the paste gets very firm and reaches the ribbon-stage.

Generally, the preparation moulded in the covers is of a different flavour and colour from the one filling the middle of the mould.

For example, one of the covers may be garnished with straw- berry, and the other with violet preparation, while the central portion may hold a vanilla-flavoured preparation. After having frozen them for three hours, in a pail filled with freezing ice, and turned them out, these bricks are cut up vertically into rectangles, on the cut sides of which the differently coloured layers are distinctly marked. Place these rectangles in special paper cases; decorate them on top, if the directions admit of it, and place them in a refrigerator until about to serve.

Nearly all Bombe preparations may become the base of biscuits, which are then named after them; e.g.: from Bombe Odessa, Odessa Iced Biscuits may be prepared.

Various, Iced Biscuits

Iced Biscuit Bénédictine

Mould the base with strawberry ice, the middle with Bénédictine ice, and the top with violet ice. Freeze and cut up as directed.

Iced Biscuit Marquise

Mould with Kirsch and strawberry ices, alternated twice.

Iced Biscuit Mont-Blanc

Mould the base with a rum-flavoured preparation, the middle with a chestnut preparation, and the top with a vanilla-flavoured preparation.

Iced Biscuit Napolitaine

Mould the base with a vanilla-flavoured preparation, the middle with strawberry ice, and the top with a preparation of pralined biscuit.

Iced Biscuit Princesse

Mould and leave to set a biscuit-pralined preparation. After having cut up the moulding, surround it with splintered and pralined almonds.

Decorate the pieces with vanilla ice-cream and tangerine ice.

Iced Biscuit Sigurd

Mould the base with strawberry and the top with pistachio biscuit preparation. When the biscuit is frozen, cut it into rectangular slices, and sandwich each slice between two sugar wafers.

Bombes Generic Recipe

Originally, Bombes were made from an ordinary ice preparation, in spherical moulds; hence their name, which is once more justified by their arrangement, consisting as it used to do of superposed and concentric layers, the outermost of which was very thin. Nowadays, Bombes are more often moulded in the shape of shells, but the preparation from which they are made is much more delicate than it was formerly.

Preparation for Bombes

Gradually mix thirty-two egg-yolks with one quart of syrup at 28°. Put the whole on a very moderate fire, whisking it as for a Génoise, and, when the preparation is firm enough and taken off the fire, continue whisking it over ice until it is quite cold. Then add the selected flavour, and one and one-third quarts of stiffly-whipped cream.

The Moulding of Bombes

First clothe the bottom and sides of a mould with the ice preparation denoted by the name of the Bombe. This coat, which should vary in thickness in accordance with the size of the mould, should be somewhat thin, and made from an ordinary ice preparation, which is suited better than any other kind to this class of dish.

The middle is then filled with a Bombe preparation, flavoured as directed, or with a Mousse preparation. The whole is then covered with a round piece of white paper, and the mould is hermetically sealed with its cover, set to freeze, and left for two or three hours in the ice.

When about to serve, take the mould out of the ice; wash it with cold water; dip it quickly in tepid water; dry it with a towel, and overturn the mould on a napkin or on a block of ice.

Various Bombes

Bombe Aboukir

Having clothed the mould with pistachio ice, fill it with a pralined Bombe-preparation, combined with chopped pistachios.

Bombe Africaine

Clothe the mould with chocolate ice, and fill it with an apricot Bombe-preparation.

Bombe Abricotine

Clothe the mould with apricot ice, and fill it with a Kirsch- flavoured Bombe-preparation, laid in alternate layers with stewed apricots.

Bombe Aïda

Clothe the mould with strawberry ice, and fill it with a Kirsch- flavoured Bombe-preparation.

Bombe Alméria

Clothe the mould with Anisette ice, and fill it with a pomegranate Bombe-preparation.

Bombe Alhambra

Clothe the mould with vanilla ice-cream, and garnish it with a strawberry Bombe-preparation. After turning it out surround the Bombe with a crown of fine strawberries macerated in Kirsch.

Bombe Américaine

Clothe the mould with strawberry ice, and fill it with a tangerine Bombe-preparation. After turning out decorate the Bombe with pistachio ice.

Bombe Batavia

Clothe the mould with a pineapple ice and fill it up with a strawberry Bombe-preparation, combined with candied ginger cut into dice.

Bombe Bourdaloue

Clothe the mould with vanilla ice-cream, and fill it up with an Anisette Bombe-preparation.

After turning out decorate the Bombe with crystallised violets.

Bombe Bourdaloue

Clothe the mould with vanilla ice-cream, and fill it up with an Anisette Bombe-preparation.

After turning out decorate the Bombe with crystallised violets.

Bombe Brésilienne

Clothe the mould with pineapple ice, and fill it with a vanilla and rum Bombe-preparation combined with pineapple dice.

Bombe Camargo

Clothe the mould with coffee ice, and fill it with a vanilla Bombe-preparation.

Bombe Cardinal

Clothe the mould with a red-currant and raspberry ice, and fill it with a pralined vanilla Bombe-preparation.

Bombe Ceylan

Clothe the the mould with coffee ice, and fill it with a rum Bombe-preparation.

Bombe Châteaubriand

Clothe the mould with apricot ice, and fill it with a vanilla Bombe-preparation.

Bombe Clarence

Clothe the mould with banana ice, and fill it with a violet bombe-preparation.

Bombe Colombia

Clothe the mould with Kirsch ice, and fill it with a pear Bombe-preparation. After turning out decorate the Bombe with half-sugared cherries.

Bombe Coppélia

Clothe the mould with coffee ice, and fill it with a pralined Bombe-preparation.

Bombe Czarine

Clothe the mould with vanilla ice, and fill it with a Kümmel Bombe-preparation. After turning out decorate it with crystallised violets.

Bombe Dame-Blanche

Clothe the mould with vanilla ice, and fill it with an almond milk Bombe-preparation.

Bombe Danicheff

Clothe the mould with coffee ice, and fill it with a Kirsch Bombe- preparation.

Bombe Diable Rose

Clothe the mould with strawberry ice, and fill it with a Kirsch Bombe-preparation, combined with half-sugared cherries.

Bombe Diplomate

Clothe the mould with vanilla ice-cream, and fill it with a Maraschino Bombe-preparation, combined with candied fruit.

Bombe Duchesse

Clothe the mould with banana-ice, and fill it with a pear Bombe-preparation flavoured with Kirsch.

Bombe Fanchon

Clothe the mould with pralined ice, and fill it with a Kirsch Bombe-preparation, containing some coffee-drops.

Bombe Fédora

Clothe the mould with orange ice, and fill it with a pralined Bombe-preparation.

Bombe Florentine

Clothe the mould with raspberry ice, and fill it with a pralined Bombe-preparation.

Bombe Formosa

Clothe the mould with vanilla ice-cream, and fill it with a strawberry Bombe-preparation, combined with big strawberries.

Bombe Formosa

Clothe the mould with coffee ice, and fill it with a Bombe-preparation flavoured with liqueur-brandy.

Bombe Frou-Frou

Clothe the mould with vanilla ice-cream, and fill it with a rum Bombe-preparation, combined with candied fruit.

Bombe Grande Duchesse

Clothe the mould with pear ice, and fill it with a Chartreuse Bombe-preparation.

Bombe Gismonda

Clothe the mould with pralined ice, and fill it with an Anisette Bombe-preparation, combined with Bar white-currant jam.

Bombe Havanaise

Clothe the mould with coffee ice, and fill it with a vanilla and rum Bombe-preparation.

Bombe Hilda

Clothe the mould with filbert ice, and fill it with a Chartreuse Bombe-preparation, combined with filbert pralin.

Bombe Hollandaise

Clothe the mould with vanilla ice-cream, and fill it with a Curaçao Bombe-preparation.

Bombe Jaffa

Clothe the mould with pralined ice, and fill it with an orange Bombe-preparation.

Bombe Japonaise

Clothe the mould with peach ice, and fill it with a tea mousse-preparation.

Bombe Jeanne d’Arc

Clothe the mould with vanilla ice-cream, and fill it with a chocolate pralined Bombe-preparation.

Bombe Joséphine

Clothe the mould with coffee ice, and fill it with a pistachio Bombe-preparation.

Bombe Madeleine

Clothe the mould with almond ice, and fill it with a vanilla and Kirsch Bombe-preparation, combined with candied fruit.

Bombe Maltaise

Clothe the mould with blood-orange ice, and fill it with tangerine-flavoured Chantilly cream.

Bombe à la Maréchale

Clothe the mould with strawberry ice, and fill it with alternate layers of pistachio, orange and vanilla Bombe-preparation.

Bombe Margot

Clothe the mould with almond ice, and fill it with pistachio Bombe-preparation. After turning out, decorate with vanilla ice-cream.

Bombe Marie Louise

Clothe the mould with raspberry ice, and fill it with a vanilla Bombe-preparation.

Bombe Marquise

Clothe the mould with apricot ice, and fill it with a Champagne Bombe-preparation.

Bombe Mascotte

Clothe the mould with peach-ice, and fill it with a Kirsch Bombe-preparation.

Bombe Mathilde

Clothe the mould with coffee ice, and fill it with an apricot Bombe-preparation.

Bombe Médicis

Clothe the mould with brandy ice, and fill it with a raspberry Bombe-preparation.

Bombe Mercédès

Clothe the mould with apricot ice, and fill it with a Chartreuse Bombe-preparation.

Bombe Mignon

Clothe the mould with apricot ice, and fill it with nut Bombe-preparation.

Bombe Miss Helyett

Clothe the mould with raspberry ice, and fill it with a vanilla Bombe-preparation.

Bombe Mogador

Clothe the mould with coffee ice, and fill it with a Kirsch Bombe-preparation.

Bombe Moldave

Clothe the mould with pineapple ice, and fill it with a Curaçao Bombe-preparation.

Bombe Montmorency

Clothe the mould with Kirsch ice, and fill it with a cherry Bombe-preparation. After turning out, surround it with half-candied cherries.

Bombe Moscovite

Clothe the mould with Kümmel ice, and fill it with a bitter-almond Bombe-preparation, combined with candied fruit.

Bombe Mousseline

Clothe the mould with strawberry ice, and fill it with Chantilly cream, combined with strawberry purée.

Bombe Nabab

Clothe the mould with pralined ice, and fill it with a liqueur-brandy Bombe-preparation, containing candied fruit.

Bombe Nélusko

Clothe the mould with filbert pralined ice, and fill it with a chocolate Bombe-preparation.

Bombe Néro

Clothe the mould with filbert pralined ice, and fill it with a chocolate Bombe-preparation.

Take a dome-mould and clothe it with vanilla ice-cream with caramel; fill it with vanilla Mousse, combined with small, imitation truffles, the size of small nuts, made from chocolate.

Turn out the Bombe on a thin cushion of Punch Biscuit, of the same diameter as the Bombe. Cover the whole with a thin layer of Italian meringue; and, on top, set a small receptacle made of Italian meringue dried in an almost cold oven. Decorate the sides by means of a piping-bag with meringue, and set the whole in the oven to glaze quickly.

On taking the Bombe out of the oven, pour some hot rum into the bowl, and set a light to it when serving.

Bombe Saint Laud

Clothe the mould with raspberry ice, and fill it with alternate layers of melon Bombe-preparation and Chantilly cream.

Bombe Nesselrode

Clothe the mould with vanilla ice-cream, and fill it with Chantilly cream, combined with chestnut purée.

Bombe Odette

Clothe the mould with vanilla ice-cream, and fill it with a pralined Bombe-preparation.

Bombe Odessa

Clothe the mould with apricot ice, and fill it with a strawberry Bombe-preparation.

Bombe Orientale

Clothe the mould with ginger ice, and fill it with a pistachio Bombe-preparation.

Bombe Patricienne

Clothe the mould with vanilla ice-cream, and fill it with a pralin and chocolate Bombe-preparation.

Bombe Petit Duc

Clothe the mould with strawberry ice, and fill it with a hazelnut Bombe-preparation, combined with Bar red-currant jam.

Bombe Pompadour

Clothe the mould with asparagus ice, and fill it with a pomegranate Bombe-preparation.

Bombe Prophète

Clothe the mould with strawberry ice,and fill it with pineapple preparation.

Bombe Richelieu

Clothe the mould with rum ice; fill it with a coffee Bombe-preparation, and distribute coffee drops upon it after turning.

Bombe Rosette

Clothe the mould with vanilla ice-cream, and fill it up with red-currant-flavoured Chantilly cream, combined with red-currants.

Bombe à la Royale

Clothe the mould with Kirsch ice, and fill it with a chocolate pralined Bombe-preparation.

Bombe Santiago

Clothe the mould with Brandy ice, and fill it with a pistachio Bombe-preparation.

Bombe Sélika

Clothe the mould with pralined ice, and fill it with a Curaçao Bombe-preparation.

Bombe Skobeleff

Clothe the mould with Vodka ice, and fill it with Kümmel-flavoured Chantilly cream.

Bombe Skobeleff

Clothe the mould with peach ice, and fill it with a Champagne Bombe-preparation.

Bombe Succès

Clothe the mould with apricot ice, and fill it with Kirsch-flavoured Chantilly cream, combined with candied apricots cut into dice.

Bombe Sultane

Clothe the mould with chocolate ice, and fill it with a pralined Bombe-preparation.

Bombe Suzanne

Clothe the mould with pink rum ice, and fill it with vanilla Bombe-preparation, combined with Bar red-currant jam.

Bombe Tortoni

Clothe the mould with pralined ice, and fill it with coffee Bombe-preparation, containing coffee seeds.

Bombe Tosca

Clothe the mould with apricot ice, and fill it with a Maraschino and fruit Bombe-preparation. After turning out, decorate the Bombe with lemon ice.

Bombe Trocadéro

Clothe the mould with orange ice, combined with candied orange-rind, cut into small dice; and fill with alternate layers of Chantilly cream and roundels of filbert Génoise, cut in graduated sizes, and saturated with Curaçao syrup. Sprinkle some orange-zest dice on each roundel of Génoise.

Bombe Tutti-Frutti

Clothe the mould with strawberry ice, and fill it with a lemon Bombe-preparation, combined with various candieti fruits, cut into dice.

Bombe à la Valencay

Clothe the mould with pralined ice, and fill it with Chantilly cream, combined with raspberries.

Bombe Vénitienne

Clothe the mould half with vanilla and half with strawberry ice and fill it with a Maraschino and Kirsch Bombe-preparation.

Bombe Victoria

Clothe the mould with strawberry ice, and fill it with Plombière ice.

Bombe Zamora

Clothe the mould with coffee ice, and fill it with a Curaçao Bombe-preparation.

Iced Mouses

The composition for mousses is prepared either from English cream or from syrup. The last method is specially suited to fruit mousses.

Preparation for Iced Fruit Mousses

This is a cold syrup at 35°, to which is added an equal quantity of a purée of the fruit under treatment, and twice that amount of very stiff Chantilly cream.

Preparation of Iced Mousse with Cream

Make an English cream from one lb. of powdered sugar, sixteen egg-yolks, and one pint of milk, and leave it to cool.

When it is quite cold, add to it one pint of raw cream, two-thirds oz. of powdered tragacanth gum, and the flavour which is to characterise the preparation.

If the mousse be a fruit one, add to it one pint of a purée of fresh fruit.

Whisk over ice,until the preparation gets very frothy put it into; moulds, lined with white paper; thoroughly close them, and keep them in a refrigerator for two or three hours, subject to their size.

Various Iced Mousses

After the same procedure, mousses may be prepared with Anisette, Coffee, Chocolate, Kirsch, Maraschino, Rum, Tea, &c. Apricots, Strawberries, Oranges and Tangerines, fresh Walnuts, Peaches, Vanilla, Violets, &c.

Parfait (Generic Recipe)

Mix thirty egg-yolks with one quart of cold syrup at 28°. Put the mixture on a slow fire, and cook it as for an English cream; strain it, and whisk it on ice until it is quite cold.

Add three pints of very stiff, whisked cream and one-fifth pint of brandy or rum, in order to finish it; mould the preparation in Parfait moulds, and pack them in a freezer for from two to three hours.

N.B.—The term “Parfait”, which, formerly, was applied only to “Parfait au Café”, has become the common name for un-clothed ices, made from Bombe-preparations having but one flavour. And this is fairly logical, seeing that Bombe-preparations, but for a few insignificant distinctions, are exactly like Parfait-preparation.

It is therefore just as reasonable to make vanilla, chocolate, and pralined Parfaits, &c., as to make them with coffee.

Iced Puddings

Preparations of this class follow no hard and fast rules, and, in reality, they are not ices fat all. They are nothing else than iced entremets, the bases of which generally consist of thick English custard, the same as that which serves in the preparation of Bavarois.

The few following recipes, however, are exceptions to this rule.

Pudding de Castries

Clothe a Bombe mould with a thin layer of vanilla ice-cream, and fill it with two Bombe-preparations, spread in somewhat thick, alternate layers. One of the preparations should be of vanilla, on each thickness of which a layer of lady’s-finger biscuits, cut into dice and sprinkled with Anisette, should be spread; and the other preparation should be of tangerine.

Between the layers, sprinkle a few pinches of grated chocolate, and fill up the mould with a thickness of vanilla ice-cream.

Thoroughly close the utensil pack it for about two or three; hours. Turn it out on a folded napkin; sprinkle thereon a few red, crushed pralins; and serve an iced tangerine syrup separately.

Marie-Rose Pudding

Line a Charlotte mould with rolled gaufrettes; placing them snugly one against the other. By means of a piping-bag, fill the gaufrettes with very stiff strawberry ice, and then fill the mould with a vanilla pralined Bombe-preparation. Keep the mould in the refrigerator for three hours, and turn out the pudding on a napkin. Decorate it on top with pink and white Chantilly cream. Serve a chocolate ice-cream separately.

Pudding Miramar

Garnish an iced, Madeleine-mould with lady’s-finger biscuits, saturated with Chartreuse, and alternate them with thin slices of fresh pineapple, saturated in Kirsch, and pipped sections of tangerine, skinned raw.

Fill up the mould with a Bombe-preparation of pomegranate juice, flavoured with Kirsch; close the mould, keep it in ice for two hours, and turn out the pudding on a napkin when about to serve.

Serve an iced, vanilla syrup separately.

Pudding Seymour

Cut a Mousseline Brioche into thin slices, and set these to soak in raw, sweetened and Kirsch-flavoured cream. Peel and finely slice some peaches, and poach them in vanilla-flavoured syrup also peel some very ripe William pears.

Prepare a pink Bombe-preparation, flavoured with Kirsch and Orgeat; and then fill up the mould with alternate layers of the slices of Brioche and of fruit, with Bar red-currant jam added; and the Bombe-preparation.

Close the mould, keep it in ice for two hours, and turn out the pudding on a napkin.

Iced Soufflés

The preparation differs according as to whether the Soufflés be prepared with fruit, or with such flavours as Vanilla, Coffee, Chocolate, &c.

The last named are made with the Iced-Mousse preparation (№2916), which may also serve for the fruit Soufflé; but, in the case of the latter, the following preparation is preferable:—

Whisk the whites of ten eggs to a very stiff froth, and add to this one and one-tenth lbs. of sugar cooked to the small-crack stage. Transfer the whole to a basin; flavour according to fancy, and add one pint of a purée of fruit and one pint of very stiffly-whisked cream.

The Moulding of Large and Small Iced Souffles

Mould the large ones in ordinary Soufflé timbales, which should be lined with bands of white paper, fixed with butter, and overreaching the edges of the timbales by one and a half to two inches, that the preparation, in projecting above the brims of the utensils, may appear like a Soufflé when the paper is removed.

The small Soufflé are moulded in cases or in small silver cassolettes^ which are likewise wrapped in bands of paper, that the preparation may rise above their brims. As soon as they are moulded, put the Soufflé’s in a very cold refrigerator; and when about to serve them, carefully remove the bands of paper which, once the preparation has solidified, have served their purpose; and dish the cases or silver cassolettes on a napkin or on a carved block of ice.

Like the Bombes, and the Iced Biscuits, Iced Soufflés may be indefinitely varied, owing to the multitudinous combinations to which they lend themselves.

Sorbets (Sherbets)

Sherbets and their derivative preparations consist of very light and barely-congealed ices, served after the Entrées. They serve in freshening the stomach; preparing it to properly receive the roast.

They are at once appetisers and helps to digestion.

Preparation for Sorbets

Sherbets are made from any liqueur ice preparation at 15°; or they may be prepared as follows:—For one quart of preparation, take the juice of two lemons and one orange, half-a-pint of port wine, of Samos wine, of Sauterne, or other good wine; and add cold syrup at 22°, until the saccharometer registers 15°.

For liqueur sherbets, allow about one-fifth pint of liqueur per quart of the preparation; but remember that this is subject to the kind of liqueur used. For the quantity just prescribed, use syrup at 18° or 19°, which the subsequent addition of liqueur reduces to the proper degree. Whatever be the kind of liqueur, the latter should only be added when the Sherbet is completely frozen; that is to say, at the last moment.

Fruit Sorbets are generally prepared from the juices and syrups of aqueous fruits. Fruit purées are scarcely suited to this mode of procedure, and they are only resorted to in exceptional cases.

The Freezing of Sherbets.—Pour the preparation into the turbine or the freezer, which should have been previously packed, and keep the utensil on the move. Remove portions of the preparation from the sides of the receptacle as fast as they adhere thereto, and mix them with the whole, until the latter is completely congealed; remembering not to stir at all during the freezing process. When the preparation is firm enough, mix with it, gently, the quarter of its weight of Italian meringue or very stiffly whipped cream; and finish by the addition of the liqueur.

The Dishing of Sherbets.—Take some of the Sherbet prepara- tion in a spoon, and set it in Sherbet or Sherry glasses, shaping it to a point.

When the Sherbet is prepared with wine, sprinkle the preparation when it is in the glasses with a tablespoonful of the selected wine.

The consistence of a Sherbet, of what kind soever, should be such as to allow of its being drunk.

Various Sorbets

Having pointed out that Sherbets may be prepared from the juices of every fruit such as Pineapple, Cherries, Strawberries, Raspberries, Red-currants, &c., and from every wine and liqueur such as Port, Samos wine, Marsala, Johannisburg, Rum, Kirsch, Liqueur-Brandy, &c., and since the procedure is the same in every case, there is no need to devote a special article to each.

Sorbets à la Sicilienne

Keep a very green water melon in the refrigerator for three hours.

One hour before serving, open it on top, as directed under “Surprise Melon”, and withdraw the seeds.

Then, detach the pulp by means of a silver spoon, without withdrawing it from the fruit; sprinkle it with Maraschino, and put the whole back into the refrigerator.

Dish on fragmented ice or on a block of the latter, and serve the pulp before the diners in Sherbet glasses.

Granités

Granités answer the same purpose as Sherbets, while they may also be introduced into certain culinary preparations.

The bases of these preparations consist of very thin syrups made from fruit juices, and not overreaching fourteen degrees (saccharometer).

Granités consist only of iced syrups, and are not combined with any Italian or other meringue.

As in the case of the Sherbets, but more particularly in regard to these, the operator should remember not to stir the syrup during the freezing process, lest it turn; and when it is congealed, it sBiould form a light, granulated mass.

Marquises

Marquises are generally made from strawberries or pineapple, with Kirsch. The preparation is that of a Sherbet with Kirsch, registering 17° by the saccharometer. The freezing is done as for Granités; but it should be carried a little further.

When about to serve, mix the preparation per pint thereof with half a pint of very stiff Chantilly cream, combined with a strawberry or pineapple purée, subject to the designation of the Marquise.

Punch à la Romaine

Mix sufficient dry white wine, or dry champagne, with one pint of syrup at 22°, to reduce the latter to 17°; add the juice of two oranges and two lemons, a strip of orange and lemon zest, and let infusion proceed for one hour.

Strain the syrup and bring it to 18°.

Freeze in the freezer, until it is somewhat stiff, and mix it with the quarter of its volume of Italian meringue (prepared from two egg-whites and three and a half oz. of sugar).

When about to serve, complete with one-fifth pint of Rum, added little by little.

Serve the preparation in glasses, after the style of the Sherbets.

N.B.—For all Sherbets and Punches, one quart of the finished preparation should be allowed for every ten people.

Spooms

Spoom is a kind of Sherbet prepared from a syrup at 20°. Add to it twice as much Italian meringue as was added to the Sherbets.

Do not work it too briskly, that it may remain very light and frothy.

Spooms are made from fruit juices; but more often from such wines as Champagne, Samos, Muscat, Zucco, &c.

Serve it in glasses like the Sherbets.

Chapter XXI Drinks and Refreshments

N.B.—The quantities given below are calculated to be sufficient for fifteen glassfuls.

Bavaroise

Work eight oz. of powdered sugar with eight egg-yolks in a saucepan, until the whole becomes white and reaches the ribbon stage. Then add consecutively: one-fifth pint of capillary syrup, one pint of freshly made, boiling hot tea, and the same amount of boiling milk; whisking briskly the while,that the drink may be very frothy. Complete at the last moment with one-third pint of the liqueur which is to characterise the Bavaroise, i.e. either Kirsch or Rum.

If the Bavaroise be flavoured with vanilla, orange or lemon, let the flavour infuse in the milk for fifteen minutes beforehand. If it be flavoured with chocolate, dissolve six oz. of the latter, and add the milk to it, flavoured with vanilla.

If it be coffee-flavoured, set three oz. of freshly-torrified and concassed coffee to infuse in the milk or flavour with one pint of freshly-made coffee.

Bavaroise is served in special glasses, and it must be frothy.

Bischoff

Put into a basin one bottleful of Champagne, one Sherry-glassful of “tilleul” infusion, one orange and one lemon, cut into thin slices, and enough syrup at 32°C to bring the preparation to 18°C. Let maceration proceed in the cool for an hour. This done, strain the whole; freeze it like a Granité, and finish it with four liqueur-glassfuls of liqueur-brandy.

Serve in bumpers.

Iced Coffee

Pour one and a half pints of boiling water, gradually, over ten oz. of freshly-ground coffee, and strain it gently. Put this coffee into a bowl with 20 oz. of loaf-sugar, and let the latter dissolve while the coffee cools. Then add one quart of very cold, boiled milk, in which half a stick of vanilla should have infused, and one pint of very fresh cream.

Freeze the whole in a freezer, taking care to keep the preparation almost liquid, and serve it in very cold cups.

Lemonade

Dissolve half-lb. of loaf-sugar in one quart of filtered water. Add the juice and the zests of the rinds of two lemons, and let infusion proceed in the cool for three hours. Pass the whole through a fine strainer; add one syphonful of seltzer water, and serve with a thin roundel of lemon in each glass.

Pineapple Water

Finely chop one and a half lbs. of fresh or preserved pineapple put it into a basin and pour over it one quart of boiling syrup at 20°C. Let it cool, and infuse for two hours.

Strain through a woollen bag; add a piece of ice and sufficient seltzer water to reduce the liquid to 9°C. Keep the preparation in the cool for a further twenty minutes, and complete it, when about to serve, with three liqueur-glassfuls of Kirsch.

Cherry Water

Stone two lbs. of very ripe cherries, and rub them through a sieve. Put the purée into a basin with the stones, crushed in the mortar, and let the whole macerate for one hour. Then moisten with one pint of filtered water, and strain the juice through a woollen bag, or muslin folded in two and stretched.

Add a piece of well-washed ice and six oz. of loaf-sugar, and put the whole in the cool for twenty minutes. Flavour, when about to serve, with four liqueur-glassfuls of Kirsch.

The saccharometer should register 9°C when inserted into this preparation.

Raspberry-flavoured, Red-currant Water

Rub through a sieve, over a basin, twelve oz. of red and white currants, and four oz. of very ripe raspberries. Add to the currant-water one pint of filtered water, six oz. of loaf-sugar, and one piece of washed ice. Keep the whole in the cool for twenty minutes, and stir it from time to time with a silver spoon, that the sugar may dissolve.

Degree the same as in №2939.

Melonade

Rub one lb. of just-ripe melon pulp through a sieve. Put it into a basin and pour over it one pint of boiling syrup at 20°C. Let the whole cool and infuse for two hours, and strain it through muslin or through a woollen bag. Add a piece of very clean ice and sufficient seltzer water to reduce the syrup to 9°C. Keep the preparation in the cool for a further twenty minutes, and finish it, when about to serve, with two tablespoonfuls of orange-flower water.

Kaltschale

Peel and slice one-half lb. of peaches and an equal quantity of pineapple; add four oz. of ripe, melon pulp, cut into dice, and four oz. of a mixture of raspberries and red and white currants, cleared of their stalks. Put these fruits in a silver timbale and keep the latter on ice. Set a little cinnamon to infuse in a half-bottleful of boiling, white wine; add six oz. of sugar and the zest of one lemon; and let the whole cool. Then add half a pint of a mixed purée of strawberries and red-currants to this infusion.

Filter the whole, and complete it by the addition of a bottle of champagne.

Pour this preparation over the fruit, and serve the timbale very cold.

Kaltschale

Proceed as for lemonade, but use the juice and zests of orange rinds instead of those of lemons, and the juice of only half a lemon. Put very thin slices of orange in the glasses.

Punch with Kirsch

Throw a good half oz. of tea into one quart of boiling water, and let it infuse for ten minutes. Put into a punch or salad-bowl one lb. of loaf-sugar; strain the infusion of tea over the sugar, and dissolve the latter; stirring the while with a silver spoon.

Add one and a half pints of Kirsch, set it alight, and serve in glasses.

Punch with Rum

Make an infusion as above, with the same amount of tea and one quart of boiling water. Strain it over one lb. of loaf-sugar, in a punch-bowl, and let the sugar dissolve.

Add a few thin slices of lemon, and one and a half pints of rum, and set light to it. Serve with a slice of lemon in each glass.

Punch Marquise

Put into a small, copper saucepan one quart of Sauterne wine, half-lb. of loaf-sugar, and the zest of the rind of one lemon bound round a clove. Dissolve the sugar; heat the wine until it becomes covered by thin white froth, and pour it into a punch-bowl after having withdrawn the zest and the clove.

Add half a pint of burnt brandy; set it alight and let it burn itself out.

Serve with a thin slice of lemon in each glass.

Iced Punch

Prepare a Marquise Punch as above; when the wine is hot, take it off the fire; throw in a good half oz. of tea, and let the whole infuse under cover for ten minutes.

Pass the whole through a fine strainer; add one orange and one lemon, peele draw and cut into slices, and some heated rum. Set alight; leave to cool, and reduce to 15°C. Then freeze like a Granité, and serve in glasses.

Hot Wine

Pour one bottleful of red wine over ten oz. of loaf-sugar, set in a small, copper basin. Dissolve the sugar. Add one orange zest, a bit of cinnamon and mace, and one clove. Heat the wine until it is covered by thin froth, and then pass it through a fine strainer.

Serve with a thin slice of lemon in each glass.

Hot Wine with Orange

Pour half a pint of boiling water over ten oz. of loaf sugar. Add the zest of one orange and let infusion proceed for fifteen minutes. Withdraw the zest, and mix one bottleful of heated Burgundy wine with the infusion.

Serve with a roundel of orange in each glass.

Wine à la Française

Put eight oz. of sugar into a salad-bowl, and sprinkle thereon a few tablespoonfuls of water, that it may dissolve. Add one bottleful of excellent Bordeaux wine or red Burgundy, and the half of a lemon cut into thin slices. Stir the whole well with a silverspoon, and serve with a slice of lemon in each glass.

N.B.—Always remember to free the lemons and oranges used of all pips, which would lend a bitterness to the drink.

Claret Cup

Put into a crystal bowl one oz. of loaf-sugar, the rind of one lemon and three slices of the latter, an equal quantity of orange, one strip of cucumber peel, one tablespoonful of Angostura Bitter, and a liqueur-glassful of each of the following liqueurs:—Brandy, Maraschino and white Curaçao.

Complete with one and a half bottles of red wine and a bottle of Soda. Cover and let the whole infuse. Strain, add a few pieces of very clean ice and a few leaves of fresh mint.

Chapter XVIII Fruit-stews and Jams

Plain Stewed Fruit

Fruit for stewing is used whole, halved or quartered, and cooked or poached in a syrup, of a flavour in keeping with the fruit.

Dish these preparations in tazzas, bowls or deep dishes; cover them with their syrup, reduced or not; and, in certain cases, thicken the latter with arrowroot. They may be served hot or cold; but in any case, the fruit used should not be too ripe.

Mixed Stewed Fruit

These preparations generally consist of stewed, fresh fruit of one or several kinds; combined with fruit purées.

Quince and apple jellies are greatly used, either in coating the preparations or in bordering them with dice, &c.

With this class of stewed fruits, which are merely a matter of fancy and taste, candied and preserved fruits are almost always used as auxiliary constituents.

Jams

Under this generic title the following preparations are classed:—

Those in which the fruit is treated directly with the sugar.
Those in which the juice alone, owing to its gelatinous nature, produces, together with the sugar, consistent jellies.

The amount of sugar used is subject to the nature of the fruit and its sweetness; but in the case of nearly all tart fruits, the weight of sugar should equal that of the fruit, or nearly so.

If too much sugar be used, the flavour is impaired; while crystallisation will follow very shortly afterwards; if too little be used, the jam has to be overcooked in order to be made sufficiently consistent, and the flavour is once more impaired by protracted evaporation; finally if the time allowed for cooking be inadequate, rapid fermentation will be the result.

In making jam, therefore, the operator should base his measure of sugar upon the nature of the fruit he intends treating.

The Cooking, Potting, and Sealing of Jams

The time allowed for cooking any jam whatsoever can only be approximately decided, and it is a gross mistake to suppose the case otherwise, since the matter is wholly dependent upon the intensity of the fire, and the resulting speed of the evaporation of the vegetable moisture. Theoretically, a jam is all the better for having been cooked quickly, seeing that it may thus more easily preserve its colour and flavour.

For all that, unless great care and attention be exercised, a whole-fruit jam ought not to be made on a too violent fire, lest it burn. Conversely, when jellies are in question, wherein the juice alone of the fruit is treated, the fire should be as intense as possible; in order that the required degree of consistence, which marks the close of the operation, may be reached as speedily as possible.

The degree of consistence is the same for all jellies, and may be ascertained thus: when the steam given off by the preparation loses its density, and the boiling movement becomes perceptible, it may be concluded that evaporation has ceased, and that the real cooking-process, which is very rapid, has begun. At this stage frequently take the skimmer out of the saucepan.

The jam adhering to it falls off, at first very quickly; then, in a few minutes, it is seen to accumulate towards the centre of the skimmer and to fall therefrom slowly at lengthy intervals, in large drops.

This stage, which is indubitably indicative of the cooking being at an end, is called the “nappe” and is equivalent to the large-thread stage in the cooking of sugar; and, as soon as it is reached, the jam should be taken off the fire. Allow it to cool for seven or eight minutes, and pour it into pots, which, if of glass, should be gradually heated, lest they crack.

The following day, set a round piece of white paper saturated with rectified glycerine, on each pot, and drop these pieces of paper directly upon the jam. Rectified glycerine will be found preferable by far to the commonly-used sugared brandy.

Then close the pots with a double sheet of paper, fastened on with string, and place them somewhere in the dry.

Apricot Jam

Cut the apricots in two, and use very ripe fruit, grown in the open, if possible. Break the stones, skin the almonds, and cut them in two. Allow three-quarters of lb. of loaf-sugar per lb. off fruit. Put this sugar in a preserving pan with one-third pint of water per two lbs. of sugar, and, when the latter is dissolved, boil for a few minutes, carefully skimming the while. Add the apricots, set the whole to cook on a moderate fire, and stir incessantly, especially towards the end, when the jam is more particularly prone to burn on the bottom of the saucepan. Take the jam off the fire as soon as it reaches the “nappe” stage, as explained above, and mix the almonds with the jam.

Cherry Jam

Stone the cherries, and allow one and a half lbs. of loaf-sugar per two lbs. of the fruit; taking care to have equal weights of sugar and fruit if the latter be not over sweet. Put the sugar in the preserving pan; moisten it with water that it may dissolve, and boil it for five minutes, skimming carefully the while. Add the cherries and a half-pint of red-currant juice, and cook over a fierce fire until the “nappe” stage is reached.

Remarks:—

The addition of red-currant juice is advocated for this jam, seeing that by ensuring the proper consistence it obviates prolonged cooking; and, as I have already pointed out, red fruit is all the better, and preserves a more perfect colour, when it is cooked rapidly.
When the fruit begins to boil, carefully skim it, otherwise the scum hardens, and not only spoils the jam but often sets it fermenting.

Strawberry Jam

This is one of the most difficult jams to make. There are several ways of preparing it, and the one I give strikes me as the quickest and simplest. Clean the fruit, which should be just ripe. Only wash it when absolutely necessary, as, for instance, when mould has stuck to it.

Allow twelve oz. of sugar per lb. of fruit. Put this sugar in a preserving pan, sprinkle it with water that it may dissolve, and cook it to the large-hall stage (see №2344), taking care to skim thoroughly when boiling begins. Throw the strawberries into the sugar, and set the preserving pan on the side of the fire for seven or eight minutes; that is to say, until the moisture of the fruit has dissolved the sugar to a syrup.

Return the saucepan to a fierce fire, and cook the strawberries for ten or twelve minutes, remembering to carefully remove the scum that forms.

Then withdraw the strawberries by means of a slice and drain them in a basin. Continue cooking the syrup rapidly, until the “nappe” stage shows signs of appearing, then return the strawberries for five minutes; that is to say, until the “nappe” stage is completely reached.

Fill the pots, little by little, that the strawberries may be well distributed in them and not rise in a mass to the top, as often happens when the receptacles are filled too quickly.

Orange Marmalade

Select some oranges about equal in size, of a good colour, free from blemishes, and with thick and soft rinds. The latter consideration is important, seeing that the parboiling operation effected more perfectly when the rinds are thick and supple.

Prick them somewhat deeply with a small, pointed stick (in order to precipitate the cooking process), and throw them into a preserving pan of boiling water. Boil for thirty minutes the oranges, cool them, and put them under a running tap for twelve hours, or more if possible; or soak them in constantly changed,cold water for twenty hours. The object of this operation is to soften the rinds and extract their bitterness.

This done,drain the oranges quarter them, remove their pips; and filaments, and rub them through a coarse sieve.

Take the same weight of sugar as of orange purée. Melt the former in the preserving pan, and boil it for five or six minutes, skimming carefully the while. Then add the orange purée, and one-quarter pint of good apple juice per lb. of the former.

During the first stage of the cooking process, skim with great care, and during the second stage, stir almost incessantly until the “nappe” stage is reached.

Plum Jam

Allow twelveoz. of loaf-sugar per lb. of stoned plums.

Dissolve the sugar; skim, set it to boil for seven or eight minutes, and proceed for the cooking as directed under apricot jam.

Remarks

It is a mistake to let the plums macerate in the sugar for some hours previously, for the acid they contain causes them to blacken, and the colour of the jam is thus spoiled.
In order to have greengage jam of a fine, green colour, do not cook more than from six to eight lbs. of it at a time, and cook that quantity as quickly as possible.

Rhubarb Jam

Rhubarb jam is one of the most difficult and tedious to make owing

to the abundant moisture contained by the vegetable;
to its proneness to burn on the bottom of the saucepan, especially towards the close of the cooking process.

If it be desired very green, select suitable natural rhubarb; if it be desired pink, only take the central stalks which are bordered with red, or use forced rhubarb. In any case, it is best not to make more than five or six lbs. at once.

Suppress the ends of the stalks, cut what remains into pieces; by means of a small knife, scrape off the adhering skin and cut the stalks into three-inch lengths. Allow thirteen oz. of loaf-sugar per lb. of rhubarb. Dissolve the former, boil it for seven or eight minutes, and then throw the rhubarb into it. Cover the preserving pan and put it on the side of the stove for about twelve minutes that the fibres of the rhubarb may be disaggregated, and at the end of that time become like vermicelli.

Then set the saucepan upon a fierce fire, and stir constantly until the preparation reaches the “nappe” stage, whereupon the jam is finished.

Tomato Jam

There are also several ways of making this jam, of which the following seems the most expeditious:

The first fact that should be grasped is that the amount of pulp that can be used represents about one-fifth of the tomato, and this itself depends upon the kind of tomato used, and whether it be just ripe, nearly so, or very ripe.

In order to obtain one lb. of pulp, therefore, five lbs. of tomatoes should be used, or thereabouts.

Finely slice the tomatoes, and rub them through a sieve. Put the juice and the purée into the jam-saucepan, and boil for five minutes, stirring the while.

This done, pour the whole into a napkin, stretched between the four legs of an overturned stool, as for straining a jelly; and let it drain thoroughly.

At the end of the operation, therefore, all that remains on the napkin is the mere vegetable pulp, freed of all moisture.

Allow the same weight of sugar as of pulp. Put the former into the jam-saucepan, together with a small glassful of water; let it dissolve, and cook it to the small-ball stage (see the cooking of sugar); taking care to skim it well as soon as it begins to boil. A stick of vanilla may be put with the sugar before boiling it; or the jam may be flavoured with a good tablespoonful of vanilla sugar when it is taken off the fire; in any case, the jam ought to be flavoured with vanilla.

When the sugar has reached the small-ball stage, add the tomato pulp to it, and one-fourth pint of red-currant juice per lb. of pulp. Owing to the fact that tomato pulp of itself has no cohesive properties the mixing of red-currant juice with it is essential.

Set the preserving pan upon a fierce fire, stirring incessantly the while, until the “nappe” stage is reached; then let the jam cook for a few more minutes.

Black-currant Jelly

Take some very ripe black-currants: clean them put them; into the preserving-pan with half a glassful of water per two lbs. of fruit, and let them boil.

While this preparatory operation is in progress, the skins of the currants burst, and their juice flows into the pan. At this stage, transfer the fruit to a sieve lying on a bowl—a much simpler method than crushing and pressing them in a twisted towel.

Allow as many lbs. of sugar as there are quarts of juice this sugar into the preserving-pan; dissolve it, and cook it to the small-ball stage; thoroughly skimming the while. Add the black-currant juice, combined per quart with half pint of white-currant juice.

Move the utensil to the side of the stove for a few minutes, that the sugar may dissolve, and then cook the jelly on a fierce fire, carefully skimming the while, until the “nappe” stage is almost reached.

Remarks: The object of adding the white-currant jelly is to modify the blackness of pure black-currant jelly.

Quince Jelly

Select very ripe fruit; cut it into slices; peel and pip these, and throw them into a basin of fresh water.

Then put them into a preserving-pan with three and a half pints of water per lb. of quinces, and cook them without touching them. This done, transfer them to a sieve, and let them drain. Return the juice to the pan, together with twelve oz. of loaf-sugar per oz.; dissolve the sugar; and set the whole to cook on a fierce fire, meanwhile skimming with care, until the “nappe” stage is almost reached.

As soon as the jelly is cooked, strain it through a piece of muslin stretched over a basin; and by this means, a perfectly clear jelly will be obtained.

Red-currant Jelly (Method A)

Take some red and white currants, in the proportion of two-thirds of the former to one-third of the latter, and combine with them, per two lbs., three oz. of raspberries. Crush the three products together in a basin, and then press them in small quantities at a time, in a strong towel, in order to extract their juice. Put the juice in the preserving-pan, together with eight oz. of loaf-sugar per pint. Thoroughly dissolve the sugar, and set the whole to cook over a very fierce fire; meanwhile skimming carefully—more particularly at first, until the “nappe” stage is reached.

N.B.—The yield of juice from red-currants equals about two-thirds or three-fourths the weight of the raw fruit.

Red-currant Jelly (Method B)

Take the same quantities of white and red currants and of raspberries, as above. Carefully clean the fruit; wash it in cold water, and put it into the preserving-pan, with one wineglassful of water per lb.

Cook the whole gently on the side of the stove for ten or twelve minutes; transfer the fruit to a sieve, lying on a basin, and let it drain.

Put the juice into the preserving-pan, with twelve oz. of loaf-sugar per lb., and proceed with the cooking as before.

Red-currant Jelly (Method C)

Take the same quantities as above of white-currants, red-currants, and raspberries. Remove the currants from their stalks by means of a fork, and collect them in a basin; clean the raspberries, and allow twelve oz. of loaf-sugar per lb. of the fruit.

Dissolve the sugar in the preserving-pan with a little water and cook it to the small-ball stage; meanwhile skimming care- fully.

Throw the currants and the raspberries into it the side of the fire for seven or eight minutes, that the juice may exude from the fruit; and then cook on a fierce fire, skimming very carefully the while, until the “nappe” stage is reached.

White-currant Jelly

This is made from fresh, very ripe white-currants and two oz. of raspberries per lb. of the latter. Any one of the three methods given above may be followed in its preparation, although Method C will be found to yield the clearest jelly.

Red-currant Jelly, Prepared Cold

Prepare the juice as directed under №2965. Add to it one lb. of icing-sugar per quart, and keep the whole in the cool for two or three hours, taking care to stir it frequently with a silver spoon in order to dissolve the sugar. Fill the pots and keep them uncovered for two or three days.

This done, cover them in the usual way, and set them in the sun for two or three hours per day for two days.

This jelly is as fragile as it is delicate, and should be kept in the dry.

Orange Jelly

In order to make one quart of orange jelly, take twelve oranges, each weighing about five oz.; one-third pint of good apple juice, one lb. of loaf-sugar, and a tablespoonful of grated orange sugar. The latter is obtained by rubbing the rinds of the oranges with loaf-sugar, and then grating the sugar so coloured and flavoured with a hard knife.

If the jelly be desired garnished, insert a fair-sized, candied orange-rind cut into small strips.

Preparation:—Thoroughly press the oranges and filter the juice prepare the apple juice, and set the sugar to dissolve with; a few drops of water.

Add the orange and apple juice to the sugar, and cook the jelly like the preceding ones. Leave it to cool for ten minutes; mix with it the orange sugar and the candied rind, and pour it into pots.

Apple Jelly

Proceed exactly as for quince jelly, and strain the apple juice without pressing the fruit. Do not cook the latter over much, lest the juice becomes mixed with pulp. Nevertheless, this should be very carefully poured away; for, in spite of the greatest care, there is always a certain amount of deposit.

Put the juice into the preserving pan, with thirteen oz. of loaf-sugar and one-third of a stick of vanilla per quart.

Cook, and strain through muslin, as in the case of quince jelly.

Tomato Jelly (1st Method)

Prepare the tomatoes as directed under №2962.

Per lb. of drained juice allow one good pint of apple jelly, twenty oz. of sugar, and a large vanilla stick.

Put into the preserving-pan the sugar, the apple jelly, and the vanilla-flavoured tomato juice, and put the utensil on the side of the fire for five minutes.

This done, set the whole to cook on a fierce fire, until the "nappe" stage is reached.

Tomato Jelly (2nd Method)

Take the same amount of juice as in the preceding case.

Use red-currant jelly instead of apple jelly, and prepare the former from red and white currants in the proportion of one-third of the former to two-thirds of the latter. Use the same amount of vanilla as above. Put the latter into the preserving-pan; dissolve it with a little water; add the vanilla, and cook it to the small-crack stage (see №2962); remembering to skin carefully at the start.

Add the tomato pulp and the red-currant jelly to the cooked sugar put the whole on the side of the stove for a moment in; order to reduce the sugar; and then proceed with the cooking on a very fierce fire until the “nappe” stage is reached.

Errata

Where significant alterations have been made to the original 1907 edition, they are noted below:

General

&c.
In the original, “etc.” and “&c.” are used interchangeably; this edition uses “&c.” throughout.
Carcase
Whilst it is an acceptable variant spelling, it has been changed to the O.E.D.’s preferred “carcass”.
Coffee-spoonful
In the original, coffee-spoonful and coffeespoonful are used interchangeably, I have used coffee-spoonful throughout.
Coulis
Cullises changed to Coulis
Gray
Changed gray to grey.
Half glaze
In the original, half glaze and half-glaze are used interchangeably, I have used half glaze throughout.
Meat glaze
In the original, meat glaze and meat-glaze are used interchangeably, I have used meat glaze throughout.
Profiteroles
Changed the, now rather archaic, profiterolles to profiteroles.
Recipe references
In the original, both “Formula 102” and “Formula №102” are used to refer to recipes, this edition uses “Formula №102” throughout.
Sauté-pan
In the original, sauté-pan and sautépan are used interchangeably, I have used sauté-pan throughout.
Pineapple
Pine-apple has been changed to pineapple throughout.

Specific

Formula №10 (

White Veal Stock, Poultry Stock

)

The original contains a misprint for the last listed ingredient:

Ingredient | Amount
Quantity | Unit
faggot, including 1 oz. of parsley, 1 bay leaf, and a of parsley, 1 bay leaf, and a | 1

Based upon Escoffier Online’s translation from the Complete guide, I have changed it to:

Ingredient | Amount
Quantity | Unit
Faggot, including 1 oz. of parsley, 1 bayleaf, and a small sprig of thyme. | 1

Consommé aux Profiteroles
Corrected formula reference from formula №28 to formula №228.
Consommé Richelieu
Existing list was inline for the first item and then a block list for the second two items. Changed all to inline.

Part II Recipes and Modes of Procedure

In Part I. of this work I treated of the general principles on which the science of cookery is founded, and the leading operations constituting the basis of the work.

In Part II. I shall proceed from the general to the particular—in other words, I shall set forth the recipes of every dish I touch upon, its method of preparation, and its constituent parts.

With the view of making reference as easy as possible, without departing from a certain logical order, I have adopted the method of classifying these recipes in accordance with the position the dishes they represent hold in the ordinary menu, and thus, starting with the hors-d’œuvres, I go straight on to the dessert. I was compelled, however, to alter my plan in the case of eggs, which never appear on the menu of a dinner save in Lent.

These I have therefore placed immediately after the hors-d’œuvres, which, like eggs, should only be served at luncheons, for reasons I shall explain later.

It will be seen that I have placed the Savouries before the Entremets, instead of after the Ices, as is customary in England. My reason for this apparent anomaly is that I consider it a positive gastronomical heresy to eat fish, meats, fowl-remains, &c., after delicate Entremets and Ices, the subtle flavour of the latter, which form such an agreeable item in a dinner, being quite destroyed by the violent seasoning of the former.

Moreover, the very pretext brought forward in support of this practice, so erroneous from the gastronomical standpoint, namely, “that after a good dinner it is necessary to serve something strange and highly seasoned, in order to whet the diner’s thirst”, is its own condemnation.

For, if appetite is satiated and thirst is quenched, it follows that the consumer has taken all that is necessary. Therefore, anything more that he may be stimulated to take will only amount to excess, and excess in gastronomy, as in everything else, is a fault that can find no excuse.

At all events, I could agree to no more than the placing of the Savouries before mild Entremets, and, even so, the former would have to consist of light, dry preparations, very moderately seasoned, such as Paillettes with Parmesan, various kinds of dry biscuits, and small tartlets garnished with cheese soufflé.

In short, if I expressed my plain opinion on the matter, I should advise the total suppression of Savouries in a dinner.

Chapter XV Relevés and Entrées

The difference between Relevés and Entrées needs only to be examined very superficially in order for it to be seen how entirely the classification hangs on the question of bulk. Indeed, with very few exceptions, the same alimentary products—butcher’s meat, fish, poultry, and game—may be used with perfect propriety in the preparation of either Releves or Entries. And if the mode of preparation and the nature of the garnishing ingredients are sometimes dissimilar, it is owing to that difference in bulk referred to above, on account of which the Relevés, being more voluminous, are usually braised, poëled, poached, or roasted; while the Entrées, consisting of smaller pieces, are chiefly sautéd, poached, or grilled.

In the menus of old-fashioned dinners à la Française, the line of demarcation between Relevés and Entrées was far more clearly defined, the latter being generally twice, if not thrice, as numerous as the former. The first service of a dinner for twenty people, for instance, comprised eight or twelve Entrées and four soups, all of which were set on the dining-table before the admission of the diners. As soon as the soups were served, the Relevés, to the number of four, two of which consisted of fish, took the place of the soups on the table; they relieved the soups; hence their name, which now, of course, is quite meaningless.

The Russian method of serving greatly simplified the practice just described. Nowadays a dinner rarely consists of more than two soups, two Relevés (one of which is fish), and two or three Entrées for the first service. Very often the fish Relevé, instead of being a large piece of fish, only consists of fillets of sole, of chicken-turbots, &c., or timbales, which are real entrées; while the Relevés (consisting of large pieces of butcher’s meat or game), instead of being served as commonsense would dictate, i.e., after the fish Relevé, when the diner’s appetite is still keen, are placed, according to English custom, after the Entrées.

Thus, as the two above examples show, the parts played by the Relevés and Entrées respectively are very far from being clearly defined; and I therefore resolved to treat of them both in the same chapter, and to append a few grills (usually accompanied by various sauces and garnishes), which are really only luncheon-roasts. The indications given concerning the class to which the recipes belong will suffice to avoid confusion.

Glossary

Abats
Stands for such butcher’s supplies as heads, hearts, livers, kidneys, feet, &c.
Aiguillettes
See №1755.
Ailerons
See №1583.
Amourettes
See №1288.
Anglaise
To treat à l’Anglaise, see №174.
To cook à l’Anglaise, means to cook plainly in water.
A preparation of beaten eggs, oil, and seasoning.
Attereaux
See №1219.
Baba-moulds
A kind of small deep cylindrical mould, slightly wider at the top than at the bottom.
Bain-Marie
A hot-water bath in which utensils containing various culinary preparations are immersed to keep warm, or for the purpose of poaching or cooking.
Barquettes
See №314.
Biscottes
A kind of rusks.
Blanch
Blanched
See №273.
Brandade
See №127.
Brunoise-fashion
See Cut below.
Canapés
See №316.
Caramel Stage
See Stages in the Cooking of Sugar, below.
Casserole (En)
See №250.
Cassolette
A kind of hot hors-d’œuvre, moulded to the shape of a small drum.
Cèpes
A kind of mushroom (Boletus edulis).
Chartreuse-fashion
See №1220.
Chiffonade
See №215.
Chinois
A very small green candied orange.
Chipolata
A kind of small sausages.
Choux
A kind of cake made from Pâte à Choux, q.v.
Cisel
Ciseled
To cut a vegetable after the manner of a chaff-cutting machine.
Clothe
Clothed
Clothing (of moulds)
See №916.
Cocotte (En)
See №250.
Concass
Concassed
To chop roughly.
Contise
To incise a piece of meat at stated intervals, and to insert slices of truffle, or other substance, into each incision.
Crépinettes
See №1410.
Croustade
See №2393.
Croûtons
Pieces of bread of various shapes and sizes, fried in butter. In the case of aspic jelly, croûtons stand for variously shaped pieces used in bordering dishes.
Cut, Brunoise-fashion
To cut a product into small dice.
Cut, Julienne-fashion
To cut a product into match-shaped rods.
Cut, Paysanne-fashion
To cut a product into triangles.
Dariole-moulds
Small Baba-moulds, q.v.
Darne
See №184.
Daubière
An earthenware utensil used in the cooking of Daubes.
Écarlate (À l’)
Salted meat is said to be à l’écarlate when it is swathed in a coat of scarlet jelly.
Escarole
Batavia chicory.
Feuilletés
A kind of puffs made from puff-paste.
Flute (French, soup)
A long crisp roll of bread.
Fondue
A cheese preparation;
A pulpy state to which such vegetables as tomatoes, sorrel, &c., are reduced by cooking.
Fumet
A kind of essence extracted from fish, game, &c.
Galette
A large quoit, made from puff-paste or short-paste, &c.
Gaufrette
A special wafer.
Génoise
See №2376.
Gild
Gilding
Gilded
To cover an object with beaten eggs, by means of a brush;
To give a golden sheen to objects by means of heat.
Gratin
Gratined
See №268 to 272 inclusive.
Hatelet
An ornamental skewer
The word sometimes stands for Attereaux.
Julienne
Julienne-fashion, see Cut.
Langoustine
A small variety of the Spiny Lobster.
Large-Ball Stage
See Stages in the Cooking of Sugar, below.
Large-Crack Stage
See Stages in the Cooking of Sugar, below.
Large-Thread Stage
See Stages in the Cooking of Sugar, below.
Macédoine
A mixture of early-season vegetables or fruit.
Madeleine-mould
A mould in the shape of a narrow scallop-shell.
Manied (said of butter)
See №151.
Marinade
See №168.
Meringue
See №2382. Meringued = coated with meringue.
Mirepoix
See №228.
Mise en place
A general name given to those elementary preparations which are constantly resorted to during the various stages of most culinary operations.
Morue
Newfoundland or Iceland salt-cod.
Mousses
A class of light, hot or cold preparations of fish, meat, poultry, game, &c., and sweets, moulded in large moulds in sufficient quantities for several people.
Mousselines
Same as above, but moulded in small quantities at a time, enough for one person.
Mousserons
A kind of mushroom.
Nappe Stage
See Stages in the Cooking of Sugar, below.
Orgeat
A beverage made from syrup and almonds.
Oxalis
A Mexican vegetable, allied to sorrel, of which the roots principally are eaten.
Paillettes au Parmesan
See №2322.
Palmettes
Palm-shaped pieces of puff-paste, used in decorating.
Panés à l’Anglaise
Treated à l’Anglaise, see Anglaise.
Pannequets
See №2403.
Papillate
See №1259.
Pâte à Choux
See №2373.
Paupiette
A strip of chicken, of fish fillet, or other meat, garnished with forcemeat, rolled to resemble a scroll and cooked.
Paysanne-fashion
See Cut.
Pluches
The shreds of chervil, used for soups.
Poële
Poëling
See №250.
Poêle (À la)
See №395.
Pralin
See №2352.
Pralined
Having been treated with Pralin, q.v.
Printanier (Eng. Vernal)
A name given to a garnish of early-season vegetables, cut to various shapes.
Profiteroles
See №218.
Râble
The back of a hare.
Ravioli
See №2296.
Ribbon Stage
See №2376.
Rissole
To fry brown.
Salpicon
A compound of various products, cut into dice, and, generally, cohered with sauce or forcemeat.
Sauté, Sautéd
A process of cooking described under №251.
A qualifying term applied to dishes treated in the way described under №251.
Savarin-mould
An even, crown-shaped mould.
Small-Ball Stage
See Stages in the Cooking of Sugar, below.
Small-Crack Stage
See Stages in the Cooking of Sugar, below.
Small-Thread Stage
See Stages in the Cooking of Sugar, below.
Soufflé
Name given to a class of light, hot or cold preparations of fish, meat, poultry, game, &c., and sweets, to which the whites of eggs are usually added if the preparation is served hot, and to which whisked cream is added if the preparation is served cold.
Soup-Flute
See Flute.
Stages in the Cooking of Sugar:—

Small-Thread
Large-Thread
Small-Ball
See №2344.
Large-Ball
Small-Crack
Large-Crack
Caramel
See №2344.
Nappe
See №2955.

Subrics
See №2137.
Suprême
A name given to the fillet of the breast of a fowl. The term has been extended to certain of the best parts of fish, game, &c.
Terrine
A patty.
Terrine à Pâté
A special utensil in which patties are cooked.
Tomatéd
Preparations are said to be tomatéd when they are mixed with enough tomato purée for the shade and flavour of the latter to be distinctly perceptible in them.
Vesiga
The dried spine-marrow of the sturgeon.
Zest
The outermost, coloured, glossy film of the rind of an orange or lemon.